<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DAI Online Publications</title>
    <link>http://dai-global-developments.com</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 14:50:13 -0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with DAI’s Susan Scribner: Preparedness, Response, and Global Health Security</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-with-dais-susan-scribner-about-preparedness-response-and-global-health-security</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-with-dais-susan-scribner-about-preparedness-response-and-global-health-security</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pandemics begin with a single case but don’t stay that way: since 2000, avian influenza has killed 440 people in 14 countries, Ebola more than 11,000 people in 10 countries, and severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) 770 people in 37 countries. The first deaths were reported locally in Hong Kong (1997), Guinea (2013), and China (2002), respectively. HIV/AIDS was first contracted by a human from a primate in West Africa—since 1981, AIDS has killed 35 million people, including 675,000 in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crises galvanized the U.S. government to enact programs to help at-risk countries contain emerging diseases, and these programs are working. For example, programs funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and implemented by DAI, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-stamping-out-pandemic-and-avian-influenza-stop-ai&quot;&gt;STOP AI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-respond&quot;&gt;RESPOND&lt;/a&gt; programs, were credited with limiting the spread of avian influenza and substantially strengthening outbreak response capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, USAID doubled down on this work in global health security, launching the Emerging Pandemic Threats-2 suite of programs. The EPT-2 suite includes the DAI-led &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-preparedness-and-response-pr&quot;&gt;Preparedness &amp;amp; Response (P&amp;amp;R)&lt;/a&gt; program team, working in target countries to strengthen national systems in the prevention, detection, and response to emerging pandemic threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project uses the One Health approach—the combined efforts of the human health, animal health, and environmental sectors—to reduce time to detection and confirmation of public health events. Developments asked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/susan-scribner&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DAI’s Susan Scribner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, below, P&amp;amp;R’s Project Director and Vice President of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/health&quot;&gt;DAI Global Health&lt;/a&gt;, about this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-pic-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-pic-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AIDS, Ebola, others … what causes a pandemic-threat disease and what factors cause them to spread?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were zoonotic diseases—diseases that happen when a pathogen from an animal spreads to humans. Increasingly, we’re finding human intrusion into animal ecosystems, increased animal-based food production, growing international trade, and expanding international travel have increased the opportunity for “spillover” into human populations. There are 7.5 billion people on this planet, with increasing global travel. Human beings are more mobile than ever—which means pathogens are, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P&amp;amp;R works with international partners to help governments in 15 countries—why were these countries targeted for USAID investment preventing, detecting, responding to, and containing emerging pandemic threats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are countries at high risk. They have a history of disease outbreaks, warm climates, and growing human populations that have been encroaching on wildlife areas. Some countries may also lack a health-systems infrastructure, which makes them more vulnerable to these threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was the tipping point that prompted this response—both the global health security effort and the Preparedness &amp;amp; Response program in particular?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international community has spent an enormous amount of time and money over the years reacting to HIV, Ebola virus disease, and avian influenza, to name a few. When it comes to health security, loss of lives, and economic and societal disruption, an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot afford to just respond to pandemic threats anymore; we need to be proactive about preventing them. That means working to improve country government systems and planning for preparedness and response, which is where P&amp;amp;R sits. By focusing on systems and planning, the P&amp;amp;R program helps bridge the gap between traditional health-systems strengthening activities and specific global health security needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&amp;amp;R Target Countries:&lt;/strong&gt; Bangladesh, Cameroon, Cote D&amp;#39; Ivoire, Ethiopia, Guinea, Indonesia, Kenya, Laos, Liberia, Mali, Sierra Leone, Tanzania, Thailand, Uganda, Vietnam.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does the &lt;a href=&quot;http://preparednessandresponse.org/&quot;&gt;P&amp;amp;R project&lt;/a&gt; strengthen systems and planning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project uses the One Health approach to ensure that national systems and plans bring the right resources to the table. That means medical doctors working with veterinarians, local health care providers working with emergency responders, the private sector working with the public sector. The multisectoral coordination mechanism that makes this possible is what we call a One Health platform, which we are developing in each of the 15 countries where we work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A One Health platform coordinates implementation of a variety of prevention, detection, and response activities to pandemic threats for the country government—everything from prioritizing zoonotic diseases or drafting a One Health strategy with the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, to integrating disease surveillance, to multisectoral planning and rapid response training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P&amp;amp;R helps launch and strengthen One Health platforms. We also work with established platforms, local stakeholders, and multilateral partners to help them implement preparedness and response activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-4-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-4-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Ebola countries—Liberia and Sierra Leone, where 8,700 people died—recently “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontpageafricaonline.com/index.php/health/5758-liberia-partners-institutionalize-one-health-approach-in-liberia&quot;&gt;launched&lt;/a&gt;” their One Health platforms. What does that mean in practical terms?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means the country is committed to supporting the One Health approach and addressing global health security, and they’ve put the systems and people in place to do it. But formalizing their One Health platforms is just the first step. These countries need to review and test their plans and the specific protocols and operating procedures that outline how the human, animal, and environmental health sectors will work together in different scenarios. They need to strengthen the relevant workforce, surveillance systems, and laboratory capacity to prevent, detect, and respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been great examples of the power of the One Health platforms already, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://bdnews24.com/health/2017/09/17/one-health-concept-important-for-bangladesh-who-representative&quot;&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/a&gt;’s and Uganda’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/globalhealth/healthprotection/fieldupdates/summer-2017/uganda-avian-influenza.html&quot;&gt;avian influenza responses&lt;/a&gt; and Uganda’s recent Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did the Ebola outbreak of 2014—the same year P&amp;amp;R was launched—teach us anything?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it taught us the importance of building a strong preparedness and response infrastructure during “peace time,” before the next outbreak strikes. It also highlighted the need to broaden the One Health community to include stakeholders in immigration, security, education, commerce, and the private sector—which can be a particularly important partner for mobilizing resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are typical challenges to creating One Health platforms?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many countries, health ministries are stronger and better resourced than the other sectors. This inequity extends beyond funding—animal health and environment sectors also tend to have weaker surveillance data and human resource capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working with the platforms to address some of these limitations, by improving the practice of One Health—coordinating advocacy, resource mobilization, strategy, planning, training, data sharing, surveillance, and rapid response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are next steps for P&amp;amp;R—and for global health security—in continuing to improve prevention, detection, and response?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our project and the One Health platforms we support move closer to accomplishing their planning and strategy objectives, training and guidance will take on a larger role in effective implementation. So we are looking at developing planning guidance for provincial and district implementation, as we’ve done in Indonesia. Recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/one-health-workforce/one-health-central-and-eastern-africa-network-officially-launched-in-cameroon-29eec092a774&quot;&gt;in Cameroon&lt;/a&gt;, we supported platform training for district-level emergency operations centers; we have also trained Rapid Response Teams for the West African Health Organization (WAHO) at the regional level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because so many improvements will need to be made at the subnational level, it is essential to build a network of One Health technical specialists. This is the network of doctors, epidemiologists, public health specialists, veterinarians, and environmental experts that DAI has spent the past 20 years developing, not just on P&amp;amp;R but also on the Stop AI and RESPOND projects before it, and several earlier bilateral projects in Indonesia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, P&amp;amp;R has also spent significant time in defining and simplifying technical guidance to the One Health approach. Our upcoming project technical guide includes a series of activity toolkits—toolkits the project is developing with feedback from both international and country government partners—that will make it easier for country platforms to implement these activities themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the global health security community has made so much progress in the past 10 years. But we are going to have to continue to do more to leverage the resources we have from both international and country government partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sourcing the Wadi: How Palestinian Workers Are Filling Niche Needs in Israel’s IT Sector</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/sourcing-the-wadi-training-palestinian-workers-to-fill-niche-need-in-israel-it</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 18:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/sourcing-the-wadi-training-palestinian-workers-to-fill-niche-need-in-israel-it</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Middle East hosts one of the fastest-growing high-tech industries in the world: Israel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2017/05/15/israels-high-tech-sector-is-thriving-and-now-china-wants-in-on-the-action.html&quot;&gt;Silicon Wadi&lt;/a&gt;. But the very speed of this growth means Israel’s tech sector also faces a shortage of skilled engineers. To deal with this shortage, Israel has turned largely to Eastern Europe as a source for IT workers. Though there is plenty of talent in Eastern Europe, the time difference is not ideal for collaborating and that talent is becoming costlier as global demand increases. This combination of circumstances means opportunities for Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/palestinian-market-development-programme-pmdp&quot;&gt;Palestinian Market Development Programme (PMDP)&lt;/a&gt; has seized upon this need by shifting Silicon Wadi’s sourcing focus close to home—to Palestinian IT firms. Funded by the U.K. Department for International Development and the European Commission, and in partnership with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portlandtrust.org/&quot;&gt;Portland Trust&lt;/a&gt;, PMDP identified the verification of software for microchips—or design verification—as a niche area of demand that fits wells with emerging Palestinian service capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Mira-Nasser-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Mira-Nasser-3&quot; title=&quot;The software engineer team at ProGineer in Ramallah that won a subcontract to provide design verification.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on business and workforce development, PMDP&amp;rsquo;s approach is beginning to pay off. A team of five software engineers at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.progineer.net/&quot;&gt;ProGineer&lt;/a&gt; in Ramallah recently won a subcontract to provide design verification for a multinational firm. The competitive award is a breakthrough for the Palestinian IT sector and showcases its ability to provide services to international clients. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is Design Verification?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global advances in computer hardware have forced semiconductor design to become more sophisticated. Higher-performing microchips utilize increasingly complex semiconductor designs, and this has spawned an entire industry specializing in design testing to increase performance and production efficiency. Israel—home to companies such as Intel, Cadence, Mellannox—is a world leader in design verification technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Palestinian Market Development Programme (PMDP)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PMDP improves market systems and competitiveness in the Palestinian private sector through technical assistance and matching grants. It addresses market system failures in specific sectors through market analysis and facilitation, and strengthens trade and investment linkages in collaboration with key commercial representatives. In the West Bank, the program has assisted more than 360 businesses (including 98 women-owned) with targeted grants, developing or enhancing more than 460 new products while helping nearly 200 businesses and increasing sales by £33 million. In Gaza, PMDP has assisted more than 260 businesses and helped develop or enhance 130 new products, increasing sales by £55.7 million and creating more than 1,600 jobs.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why Choose Palestinian Companies?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A closer look at the market opportunity revealed certain factors advantageous to Palestinian firms, including physical proximity to clients in Tel Aviv and Jerusalem (allowing for same time-zone operation and local travel), lower costs than in Israel, and similar costs to Eastern Europe. While the market opportunity was clear, the Palestinian market  remained undertested for design and verification services; prior to this engagement, only one service contract was being implemented by a Palestinian IT firm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian IT firms have two factors working against them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weak links and lack of awareness of business opportunities with multinational companies in the region; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited local opportunities to gain experience and professional training in design verification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----Mira-Nasser-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----Mira-Nasser-2&quot; title=&quot;Design-verification training under the Palestinian Market Development Programme included technical and practical components.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Palestinian value proposition was presented to Israel-based multinational companies, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cadence.com/&quot;&gt;Cadence&lt;/a&gt;, a provider of system design tools and software, expressed strong interest. Based upon this reaction, PMDP and The Portland Trust teams designed a three-stage intervention—applying DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/new-primer-market-systems-development-available&quot;&gt;principles of market systems development&lt;/a&gt;—aimed at stimulating commercial transactions between Cadence and Palestinian providers: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testing the waters:&lt;/strong&gt; Portland Trust asked Cadence to outline its service requirements and agree to a three-month “mock project” to test Palestinian capabilities. Four local Palestinian firms—Exalt, Progineer, Unit One, Appstown—put together teams of five members each to complete the test project. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training time:&lt;/strong&gt; A one-month, in-classroom training in system-design skills and testing software was delivered by a leading provider, Variest. The four Palestinian companies nominated 18 staff members to be trained. Feedback from the training was encouraging, with most of the participants scoring well on the end-of-course exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mock projects:&lt;/strong&gt; Following evaluation of the training, Cadence invited two teams to enroll in mock projects involving a live design-verification challenge. Eleven engineers from two shortlisted teams participated in the projects remotely over three months, with weekly visits to the Cadence campus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Deal is Struck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impressed by the mock project performance, Cadence extended its agreement to Progineer, creating five high-quality, full-time jobs—one team leader and four junior programmers—in Ramallah. This purely commercial engagement is a breakthrough for the Palestinian IT outsourcing industry. It proves the business value that Palestinian service providers can deliver to international clients, and showcases a model for how IT outsourcing can grow through effective structuring of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Mira-Nasser-IT-PMDP-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Mira-Nasser-IT-PMDP-1&quot; title=&quot;Group photo of the design-verification trainees under the Palestinian Market Development Programme.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable growth of the design-verification service line hinges upon Progineer successfully delivering results to Cadence and expanding to serve additional clients. Meanwhile, the other Palestinian firms—Exalt, Unit One, and Appstown—also have potential to tap market opportunities after taking design-verification training. “As awareness of Palestinian design-verification capabilities grows, there will be more interest from buyers, and local business development capabilities will grow stronger,” said PMDP Team Leader Maher Hamdan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PMDP plans to nuture this interest by supporting the growth of existing services, fostering additional business connections, and making design-verification training locally available. The team also plans to work with Palestinian universities to introduce design-verification courses to the IT curricula to further stimulate a generation of marketable IT employees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning Restrictive Social Norms in the Middle East into Job Opportunities for Women</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/turning-social-norms-in-the-middle-east-into-job-opportunities-for-women</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 10:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/turning-social-norms-in-the-middle-east-into-job-opportunities-for-women</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When deep-rooted social norms appear to limit the roles of women, one of the best tactics we can take in development assistance is to look for opportunities to turn those norms to women&amp;rsquo;s advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent example is in the Middle East, where our U.K. Department for International Development-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-egypt-and-palestine-arab-women-enterprise-fund&quot;&gt;Arab Women’s Enterprise Fund&lt;/a&gt; (AWEF) is assisting female-led value chains. In Palestine, AWEF is working with female sheep herders in rural areas to train these women as paraveterinary workers. A paravet functions like a veterinary assistant, nurse, or animal technician by providing basic but important treatment and testing for herds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestine has approximately 30,000 sheep herds, with an estimated 25,000 women playing active roles in their operation, especially among small herds of 35 or fewer animals. But AWEF’s analysis shows that the women-led herds suffer close to 30 percent productivity loss due to poor vaccinations and inadequate animal health care. Because most veterinarians are male, and gender mixing is discouraged, female herders cannot partake in veterinary services provided by men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_0039.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_0039&quot; title=&quot;A female paravet tending to her herd in Palestine.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Training a Cadre of Female Paravets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seizing the opportunity inherent in this restricted market, AWEF and its partners are training a cadre of 20 female paravets to provide much-needed services. These services improve the health of female-led herds as well as the incomes of the herders. Additionally, the female paravets are gaining the respect of their communities, earning more money for their families, and acting as role models for other women. By interacting directly with female paravets, Palestine’s women herders are learning about animal health care and improving their skills, instead of relying on their husbands or other men in their families who are too often ill-informed on herd health needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, women rarely held authority to make decisions around this family business. Social norms constrained their interactions with veterinarians, traders, and the male-dominant herding community. But as women paravets increase their services, it is anticipated that female herders will assume a greater sense of ownership and commitment to their traditionally unpaid work. Eventually, female herders will increase their capacity to manage herds and improve women’s overall role in livestock management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men in these communities will also benefit because female paravets’ services will add to household incomes while reducing or eliminating the expense of seeking assistance from veterinarians, whose clinics are often located far away from small villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWEF Disadvantaged Assessment Tool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWEF is the only market systems development project in the region with women’s economic empowerment as its core objective. The AWEF team developed and is now rolling out a gender-sensitive poverty mapping tool called the Disadvantaged Assessment, designed to identify areas in market systems where women’s disadvantages hinder their ability to find jobs or develop livelihoods. While the tool has yet to be fully implemented, its early findings in Palestine reveal that women are disadvantaged due to their high amount of time spent performing unpaid work, lack of decision-making authority around mobility, poor economic standing, and exposure to physical violence. In the coming months, the AWEF team will begin performing Disadvantaged Assessments on target locales and sectors.&lt;/aside&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Extending Herd-Care Services in Afghanistan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training women as paravets is also bearing fruit in other DAI-led projects. The U.S. Agency for International Development-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-regional-agricultural-development-program-radp-north&quot;&gt;Regional Agricultural Development Program-North&lt;/a&gt; (RADP-North), for example, trained 15 paravets (10 men, five women) in 2016, filling an important need for livestock owners. Trainees were equipped with tools and equipment to establish veterinary field units in the communities they now serve. RADP-North is on schedule to train another 20 paravets through 2017. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of RADP-North’s female trainees, Fatima, provides veterinary services to more than 500 farmers in 12 surrounding villages—encompassing more than 2,000 animals—while earning AFN 600 to 800 per day. “Recently, a woman called me and said that she had a newborn calf that was sick,” Fatima said. “I traveled to the area, checked the calf, and found that the calf was highly dehydrated due to acute diarrhea. The woman was so concerned about losing the calf, but I medicated the calf by injecting some vitamins, and within an hour, the calf began to improve. The woman was so happy and thanked me for saving her calf.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_8165.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_8165&quot; title=&quot;Aya Mletat started her sheep farm when she was just 20.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Earning Acceptance Among Men&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Palestine, Aya Mletat, a 30-year-old mother of two, established her own sheep farm at age 20. Today, Mletat trains and mentors both male and female herders in her community. According to Mletat, men who refused to deal with her at first have now accepted her consultations after seeing her paraveterinary skills in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWEF is finding opportunities within a culture of “constraints” in other Middle Eastern countries. In Jordan, AWEF is training women who run dairy-processing outfits to meet the standards required for local regulatory certification of their dried yogurt. This training helps these female-led small businesses to improve the quality of their products and increase sales in male-dominated markets. In Egypt, AWEF is teaching large businesses in the garment and citrus sectors to recruit women for positions—including senior and management roles—where the work and interactions would be culturally permissable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/nandi-hall&quot;&gt;Nandi Hall&lt;/a&gt;, the AWEF project director, said the team’s underlying goal is to identify social norms that open windows of opportunities for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“AWEF believes that social norms can shift when people begin to experience the economic benefits of new behaviours,” Hall said. “We hope to provide the opportunity for other women in traditional roles to be more encouraged to explore new roles by viewing social norms in a new light.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helping Eastern Partnership Countries Meet Their Commitments to Address Climate Change</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/helping-eastern-partnership-countries-meet-their-voluntary-commitments-to-reduce-emissions-address-climate-change</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 14:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/helping-eastern-partnership-countries-meet-their-voluntary-commitments-to-reduce-emissions-address-climate-change</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The economies of Eastern Europe have grown in recent decades largely on the backs of heavy industry, mechanisation, and agriculture. In many countries, this has led to significant greenhouse gas emissions, a reliance on inefficient technologies, and a policy environment that did not support green growth. As part of their commitments to global climate change agreements, signatory countries pledged to reduce emissions. After committing to cleaner ways, however, these countries faced a common challenge: where to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the six countries of the European Union’s Eastern Partnership now has a plan. Under Clima East, a 4½-year programme funded by the European Commission and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/russian-federation-clima-east-support-climate-change-mitigation-and-adaptation&quot;&gt;implemented by DAI&lt;/a&gt;, the countries—Armenia, Azerbaijan, Belarus, Georgia, Moldova, and Ukraine—assessed how to best reduce emissions and adapt their industries, agriculture, and households to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, this planning was well timed. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.climaeast.eu/&quot;&gt;Clima East&lt;/a&gt; originally launched in 2012 to continue support of the Kyoto climate agreements from 15 years earlier. But the Clima East team pivoted when the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) announced that participants of the 2016 Paris Conference would need to draft and submit, in advance, their Intended Nationally Determined Contributions (INDCs). The team was well placed to support the development of these INDCs and ensure they were technically sound and suitably ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-2&quot; title=&quot;In Azerbaijan, Clima East introduced techniques that reduce emissions of carbon and incentivize farmers to control animal numbers for better soil conditions and biodiversity. Credit: Clima East.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the Eastern Partnership nations are prepared to address and, over time, meet their Paris commitments to consume less energy, reduce emissions, and increase use of energy from renewable sources. They are also prepared to put strategies in place to support adaptation to a changing climate across a range of core economic sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clima East’s holistic approach to supporting these partner nations produced an array of results for each country. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Armenia&lt;/strong&gt;, the country’s Environmental Project Implementation Unit was accredited to access and implement funding from a major source—the global Adaptation Fund.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Azerbaijan&lt;/strong&gt;, gaps in the country’s land use, land-use change, and forestry inventory were identified and recommendations made on steps to improve local stakeholders’ capacities in this key area of greenhouse gas reporting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Belarus&lt;/strong&gt;, more than 200 people across 20 ministries, agencies, and other organisations were engaged and informed about international climate adaptation and mitigation best practices, including for planning agriculture adaptation and for obligations and opportunities under the Paris Agreement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Georgia&lt;/strong&gt;, roadmaps were produced to align with EU legislation in fluorinated gases, such as hydrofluorocarbons, and other ozone-depleting substances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Moldova&lt;/strong&gt;, civil society organisations were engaged in the crucial policy processes under way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Ukraine&lt;/strong&gt;, backlogged requests for improvements made by UNFCCC reviewers were addressed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brochure describing Clima East&amp;rsquo;s broader results is available here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1067656943.n159491.test.prositehosting.co.uk/wp-content-sec/uploads/2013/08/Clima-East-Final-Brochure-2017-PDF.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Supporting Preparations to Honor Commitments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe and its eastern neighbors are increasingly affected by rising global temperatures related to climate change. The World Bank, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/676601468249642651/pdf/761840PUB0EPI00LIC00pubdate03015013.pdf&quot;&gt;forecasts&lt;/a&gt; fluctuations in crop growing conditions by 2050 that will be especially difficult for small, poorer farms in the region to address. More frequent, more severe floods, droughts, and heatwaves are expected to affect industry, agriculture, and, ultimately, public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern Partnership nations acknowledged their increasing emissions of greenhouse gases in signing the Paris Agreement and resolved to significantly reduce their own emissions from 2020 forward. Before they signed the agreement, Clima East assisted Eastern Partnership countries in developing their INDCs. Equipped with these feasible goals, policy makers set out to develop plans on where and how their country could cut emissions, but the region’s climate scientists and lawmakers lacked the data and analytical tools needed to create accurate models of how to meet their commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clima East team and their ministerial counterparts analyzed leading emitters of greenhouse gases and identified ways to reduce emissions in sectors such as energy, agriculture, forestry, transport, waste, construction, and manufacturing. In Azerbaijan, for example, the counterparts achieved consensus on projections and created scenarios covering industrial processes, urban planning, and reforestation of degraded land. As a result, the government of Azerbaijan was able to submit its INDC ahead of Paris and set a target to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 65 percent from the country’s 1990 level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, policy makers in Belarus identified the need for specialized advice, and with Clima East&amp;rsquo;s assistance they were able to examine data and create a model that revealed untapped options for reducing greenhouse gases. With these new insights, Belarus increased its INDC emission-reduction goal from 25 percent to 28 percent of 1990 levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-4&quot; title=&quot;Regional workshop in Baku, Azerbaijan, about modelling tools for vulnerability assessments in the water and agriculture sectors. Credit: Clima East.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Using Data to Plan for Change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major long-term changes in temperatures and rainfall will affect which crops and varieties grow best and where. Clima East experts worked with local counterparts to assess and adapt to the impacts of climate change on their country’s agriculture sectors. These climate-smart agriculture approaches adapt farming and markets to anticipated changes. If ministries can better understand and plan for the implementation of climate-smart policies, farmers and others associated with agriculture value chains—including consumers—will benefit from increased security in food and livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clima East team knew that training specialists from partner countries was critical to promoting the long-term use of climate data in guiding policy. Clima East conducted regional events where climate specialists shared challenges and solutions in preparing their countries’ INDCs. These specialists also traveled to Germany and Poland to learn how these countries operate effective measuring and reporting mechanisms to track emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clima East supported specialists across the region to create complex emissions models and forecast impacts. For example, a 2014 workshop convened specialists from the six partner countries to train on an emissions modelling tool called Long-Range Energy Alternatives Planning. Participants received national data starter packs to begin emission assessments, which some countries immediately put to use in developing their INDCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-3&quot; title=&quot;Strategy roundtable in Belarus to adapt agriculture to climate change, organized and supported by Belarus&amp;#39; Ministry of Natural Resources and Environmental Protection. Credit: Clima East.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Readily Replicable Programme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In five years, Clima East engaged 40 national government institutions and hosted more than 50 groups from civil society, academia, the private sector, and local government. These efforts collectively prepared six Eastern Partnership countries to develop and implement INDC emission-reduction plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme is readily replicable to other countries and regions. One hundred and sixty countries have ratified the Paris Agreement and another 35 are in the process of doing so. Clima East has shown that if their policy makers and climate specialists are brought together and equipped with the right tools and information, they, too, can work out a path toward green growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Messe Frankfurt’s Purchase of Source Africa Trade Show Exemplifies the Potential of Market Systems Development</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/messe-frankfurts-purchase-of-source-africa-trade-show-exemplifies-the-potential-of-market-systems-development</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 20:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/messe-frankfurts-purchase-of-source-africa-trade-show-exemplifies-the-potential-of-market-systems-development</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, DAI began implementing the value chain portion of Southern Africa Trade Hub (SATH), a project funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID). SATH&amp;rsquo;s goal was to promote economic growth by fostering intraregional trade between select member states of the Southern African Development Community (SADC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During DAI’s initial work planning session, Mark Bennett, our textiles and garments specialist, was tasked with commercializing a business-to-business (B2B) trade event that previous USAID projects had been funding to the tune of about $150,000 per year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI&amp;rsquo;s value chain team found that a good deal of business was being transacted at these B2B events, so why should USAID continue to foot the bill by annually engaging a consultant to pull the event together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was there a better way to ensure that trade in textiles and apparels was conducted on a commercially sustained basis, driven by the industry itself, rather than relying on donors like USAID to make it happen? DAI had previously commercialized donor-driven business matchmaking activities using private operators in Serbia and South Africa, so we knew it could be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Source-Africa-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Source-Africa-2&quot; title=&quot;The 2017 Source Africa trade show featured 151 exhibitors from 17 countries as well as five fashion shows. Credit: Source Africa&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took nine months, but DAI found a South African trade show company, LTE, and convinced its leaders that this event in their own country could be good business. It then took another six months to get all parties to agree to a cooperation framework going forward. Finally, Bennett and value chain component lead Don Greenberg, with support from SATH’s leadership, mobilized funding support to complement LTE’s investment, and together the parties established the Source Africa trade show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Source Africa, organized by LTE with some support from SATH, took place in 2013 in Cape Town, now the home of the show every year. In its first year, Source Africa attracted about 100 exhibitors; by 2016, LTE sold 183 booths to exhibitors from 14 countries, with about 1,500 people attending the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Why%20Trade%20Shows%20May%202015.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Source-Africa-graphic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Source-Africa-graphic&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each show, LTE incurs most of the risk—paying for the venue, engaging the stand builders, hiring staff, designing logos and web sites, and so on. While development-oriented donors have continued to support Source Africa—including the USAID-funded, DAI-led &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa&lt;/a&gt; trade and investment hubs—direct donor support of LTE has fallen to extremely low levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having built up a nice profitable business creating linkages across Southern and Eastern Africa’s textile and garment industry, LTE helped achieve the purpose of our various trade hubs, but without USAID in the middle—a clear case of a donor working its way out of a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Source-Africa-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Source-Africa-1&quot; title=&quot;Nearly 1,400 attendees from 16 countries came to the 2017 Source Africa trade show. Credit: Source Africa&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month, the now highly successful Source Africa trade show was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fin24.com/Economy/messe-frankfurt-ready-to-take-sa-clothing-expos-to-next-level-20170908&quot;&gt;sold&lt;/a&gt; to Germany&amp;rsquo;s Messe Frankfurt group, the third-largest trade show organizer in the world. Messe Frankfurt runs 134 trade fairs and exhibitions worldwide. Approximately 90,000 exhibitors and 3.5 million visitors attend its exhibitions each year. Under Messe’s umbrella, Source Africa will surely soar to even greater heights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breakthroughs in trade require time, effort, and persistence—in any region of the world—but the result for developing nations is sustainable, inclusive economic growth that creates jobs and new wealth. The privatizing of Source Africa is one such breakthrough. It’s the kind of success—building local capacity to commercially fill market gaps by providing information and linking traders—that the global development community should be talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A: Unlocking Inclusive Economic Growth for Mozambicans by Building a Market for Digital Financial Inclusion</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-assisting-mozambiques-rural-poor-to-build-stability-and-economic-opportunity-through-digital-financial-inclusion</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 16:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-assisting-mozambiques-rural-poor-to-build-stability-and-economic-opportunity-through-digital-financial-inclusion</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While Mozambique’s economy is emerging—notably through the extractives sector—most Mozambicans remain very poor. Eighty percent still make a living from subsistence farming. One cause for their marginalization is that most have no connection to the wider economy or to basic financial services such as saving, borrowing, and electronic payments. This limits the ability of Mozambique’s 12 million rural poor to grow their livelihoods and perpetuates their isolation and poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2014, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-financial-sector-deepening-fsdmoc&quot;&gt;Financial Sector Deepening Moçambique&lt;/a&gt; (FSDMoç) project is working to create access to financial services for at least 2.6 million households and 1,000 small and growing businesses. This access will enable Mozambique’s households and enterprises to use responsibly delivered finance to pay for seed and fertilizer, pay electronically for necessities such as medicine, and safely deposit their savings, among other benefits. Banking electronically and with mobile phones will reduce the time, cost, and risk associated with transacting in cash only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fsdmoc.com/&quot;&gt;FSDMoç&lt;/a&gt; is funded by the U.K. Department for International Development and Swedish International Development Agency. &lt;em&gt;Developments&lt;/em&gt; recently discussed FSDMoç with two members of its Maputo-based team—Investment Manager Benedito Murambire, below right, who develops private sector investments that support financial inclusion, and Market Development Manager Helder Buvana, below left, who focuses on investments in agribusiness and financial technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----FSD-Moz-2-pics.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----FSD-Moz-2-pics&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How common is mobile technology in Mozambicans’ daily lives, and where do you see it going?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benedito:&lt;/em&gt; Mobile technology covers 82 percent of the population, but internet usage has not picked up at the same rate. Of those with coverage, 94 percent have used mobile phones for voice and 84 percent for text messaging. Thirty-one and 32 percent, respectively, have sent and received money, but only 23 percent have used social media, indicating low overall internet usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, the cost of 1 gigabyte of mobile broadband data in Mozambique is US$2.80, which compares favorably with, for example, neighboring Malawi at US$5.80. This lower cost provides opportunities for digital, including in financial services. But the use of cash still predominates, especially in rural districts. People are understandibly hesitant to try new things where their money is concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Bhairav-FSD-Moz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Bhairav-FSD-Moz&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will drive growth in digital financial services?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benedito:&lt;/em&gt; Need and demand, which are plentiful. Remittances now drive services via Vodacom Mpesa, Zoona, or the mobile wallets of six different banks, but other needs are emerging. In addition to buying farm and household goods and services electronically, people would pay their insurance premiums, taxes, and fees that way, and government employees such as teachers and nurses would receive their salaries. Drought victims and others could receive e-vouchers for emergency and disaster relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helder:&lt;/em&gt; While remittances now drive mobile money, down the road electronic transactions will not simply be led by telecoms and banks—other payment platforms will adapt, such as retailers, petrol stations, and agro-dealers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----FSDMoz-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----FSDMoz-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do people with little or no money need to have access to digital financial services?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benedito:&lt;/em&gt; Financial inclusion is about more than inclusion. Currently, the “unbanked” have to carry their cash, use their time, and travel to pay in person for everything—insurance, health care, water bills. Through its private sector partners, FSDMoç is facilitating better living by saving them the time and expense—and reducing the risk—posed by living cash only. People in developed countries, such as our donors in the United Kingdom and Sweden, are accustomed to saving time, seeking out convenience, and decreasing risk. FSDMoç is striving to deliver these same benefits for Mozambicans, and they do not need a lot of money to benefit. Eventually, all smallholders, households, shops, merchants, financial services providers, mobile network operators, and local government services will be connected and efficiencies will be gained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helder:&lt;/em&gt; This includes scaling up through agricultural value chains, which FSDMoç is doing, so that all members are connected digitally. We are currently working in Mozambique’s cotton value chain trying to connect all of its actors digitally—from small-scale cotton producers to transporters to storage operators to exporters. This helps expedite payments back and forth while creating better data and records and opening up crossborder transactions and trade. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----FSD-Moz-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----FSD-Moz-5&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What approach has FSDMoç taken to expand digital financial services?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helder:&lt;/em&gt; We work with multiple partners to influence Mozambique’s digital ecosystem. These include mobile network operators wishing to expand beyond cities, commercial banks developing safer loan products for rural borrowers—such as for solar home systems—and government agencies that need complementarity in their regulations, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important that we promote the innovation and new ideas required to connect these dots and make them work. In April, FSDMoç conducted the FinTech Challenge, where we received 22 applications from financial tech companies, with seven shortlisted to receive technical assistance from the FSDMoç team and £5,000 each. One of the winners is providing an accounting-based app for small and medium enterprises, for example, and another an app to help &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/breaking-a-wooden-box-under-a-mango-tree/?utm_source=daidotcom&quot;&gt;informal savings groups&lt;/a&gt; (known as xitiques). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;Winners in the FinTech Ideas Challenge&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FSDMoç launched the FinTech Ideas Challenge to identify scalable solutions in Mozambique from entrepreneurs, developers, technology startups, financial service providers, students, researchers, and others. From the 22 proposals received, seven were selected for technical assistance and £5,000 each:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX Information Technologies—xitique management app &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cartéira Movel (Mkesh)—xitique management app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heurística—credit management platform for individuals and small farmers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apauma Construções Soc. Unipessoal—online payment gateaway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publiaki  Serviços, ei—group lending management app &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick e-pay—USSD (Unstructured Supplementary Service Data) payment gateway&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PZC Services Lda—online invoicing system for SMEs&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are some of the more promising trends and opportunities?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benedito:&lt;/em&gt; Once there is a scalable digital ecosystem in Mozambique, we can expect electronic payment of premiums and claims for health or crop insurance, and the purchase of incremental construction materials for basic housing. This will materialize once there are ample digital transaction pools. In other words, once there is enough of a digital float in the system that enables cashing in and out of the system without delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also see ways in the short term to apply digital capabilities to benefit existing “bottom of the pyramid” local activities. This includes enabling groups to take out group loans with banks to buy seed and fertilizer, for example, and also to make group deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the magnitude of challenges faced by Mozambique’s poor, financial inclusion will only be sustainable if banks see the value of complementarity with financial tech or vice versa. If the banks play their cards right, they have access to a much larger client and partner base. If they act like a cartel, they will not gain access to a larger market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----FSDMoz-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----FSDMoz-2&quot; title=&quot;Laurinda Landa, age 25, is an M-Pesa Agent in Benfica Market in one of the townships of Maputo.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The success of mobile money in the region has generated a lot of news. What is the headline from Mozambique?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Helder:&lt;/em&gt; If we can increase the interoperability between users and suppliers at all levels, that will boost mobile money and payment channels, bring down transaction costs, and create a network effect. This is where the financial tech firms come in—to provide solutions and services that make mobile money and e-payments work better, and that make local financial institutions work better. For example, financial tech firms can develop software applications that help in logistics by facilitating payments between businesses and suppliers. Financial tech firms are the missing players in the system—as they emerge and grow, they will increasingly contribute to and help connect Mozambique’s fuller suite of digital services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benedito:&lt;/em&gt; We are working with the Banco de Moçambique (Central Bank) and the National Institute of Communications to enable and encourage financial tech firms to operate and help make the digital finance ecosystem more attractive and relevant for users. We plan to organise a supportive environment to incubate financial tech firms and create a “sandbox” approach where technology innovators are safe to test, learn, and collaborate with financial service operators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More Than Developing Apps: USAID Program Propels Cambodian Girls Into Global Technology Finals</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/its-not-all-about-the-app-narrowing-the-digital-gender-gap-usaid-program-propels-cambodia-girls-into-global-technology-contest-finals</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 14:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/its-not-all-about-the-app-narrowing-the-digital-gender-gap-usaid-program-propels-cambodia-girls-into-global-technology-contest-finals</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Women are far underrepresented in the tech world globally from bottom to top. The all-encompassing industry is looking into the mirror and seeing  men and boys dominating technology jobs, classrooms, and expert panels, a bias now widely noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usnews.com/news/data-mine/articles/2016-10-20/study-computer-science-gender-gap-widens-despite-increase-in-jobs&quot;&gt;for example&lt;/a&gt;, only 18 percent of U.S. bachelor’s degrees in computer science were earned by women, who are projected to hold just 20 percent of professional computing jobs by 2025. Developing nations face similarly stark gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excluding women and girls exacerbates the general shortage of skilled applicants to fill jobs in programming, coding, and systems administration, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/s/608090/tim-cook-apple-isnt-falling-behind-its-just-not-ready-to-talk-about-the-future/&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to Apple CEO Tim Cook. “Technology,” Cook says, “has an enormous issue with gender diversity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Technovation-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Technovation-2&quot; title=&quot;Team members from the Cambodia Identity Project: Mariya Chan Phan, Sabda Serei Yos, Soucheng Dara Lorn, Socheata Chea, and Leza Sorn.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the girls from Cambodia: These enterprising young women recently won a trip to San Francisco where they faced 11 other teams of young techies as finalists in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://technovationchallenge.org/world-pitch/&quot;&gt;Technovation World Pitch Summit in August&lt;/a&gt;. The global competition attracted more than 1,100 teams of girls ages 10 to 18, each competing to develop the best app to solve social problems. As global finalists, the girls received $5,000 from Technovation to further develop their idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cambodian entrants, 23 teams in all, were supported by the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/cambodia-development-innovations&quot;&gt;Development Innovations&lt;/a&gt; (DI) project, implemented by DAI, with co-funding from Cambodian private sector partners. The girls’ winning idea: an app called the Cambodia Identity Product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our mobile app allows local people to promote their products,” said team leader Lorn Dara Soucheng. “There are so many poor people here. Many kids who do not have jobs migrate to neighboring countries like Thailand to work. This is the reason that led us to create this app—to help Cambodians.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team thinks its app will promote the purchase of various local products, from farm produce to artisanal creations such as traditional silk scarves and jewelry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;App Contest: Gateway to Tech&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Cambodia, many parents steer girls toward careers in more established fields such as administration and finance, versus computer science or other tech-focused fields. To enter the Technovation competition, girls and their parents had to commit to the 12-week, open-source curriculum, which was developed by Iridescent, a U.S.-based education nonprofit that produces Technovation and supported the finalists’ travel and accommodation in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put out calls to girls to join the introductory session, DI joined with the Royal Government of Cambodia’s Ministry of Education, Youth, and Sports and used local and social media. In January, the girls went to work designing their projects, supported by more than 30 volunteer mentors recruited by DI from the business community and tech sector. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the team behind Cambodia Identity Product, this meant convening at the Royal University of Phnom Penh every Sunday with their mentor, Putthira, an iOS developer for a local software company who accompanied them to San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together they surveyed citizens to define the problem, used MIT AppInventor to build and refine the app, conducted market analysis, designed a business plan, and prepared a sales pitch. Private sector sponsors Digital Mobile Innovations, Smart, and Ezecom covered operational funds, hoping to develop digital literacy and potentially a pipeline of smart, connected young women with practical skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I learned a lot [about] coding, business, initiating business ideas to help better Cambodia society,” Soucheng said. “Plus, I learned how to share responsibilities in such a big project and about team collaboration.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6nP7En-NRJo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bigger and Better Things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing the app has proven more than a practical learning tool. The Technovation program strives to induct girls into technology and build the technical and professional skills needed to feed emerging economies for future generations. The girls who created Cambodia Identity Product are only 11 and 12 years old. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practical program is helping bridge the digital access divide in Cambodia. Learning one programming language prepares the girls to learn and write other codes in the future—including ones not yet invented—while the contest compelled them to think in terms of business, profit, and sustainability. Equipped with these skills, the girls can keep learning, join online communities, and pursue their technology dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Susan Wojnicki, the longtime Google executive and now CEO of YouTube, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/susan-wojcicki/tech-industry-gender-gap_b_9089472.html&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; recently in an address to the Anita Borg Institute: “Unless we make computer science a priority, we risk making gender, class, and racial disparities worse as jobs and opportunities flow to those who have a computer science background.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past participants of Technovation in Cambodia have told the DI team that they enrolled in software engineering majors at universities in Phnom Penh after being inspired by the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cambodia DI staff, the girls’ school—the Liger Learning Center—and our volunteer mentors are all proud of the girls’ remarkable achievement. Most important, though, is that with the girls now home from San Francisco, we look forward to helping them move their app idea to the next level, as well as encouraging them to mentor Technovation Cambodia’s next generation of all-girl problem solvers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A: Barry Finette on the Hopes and Challenges for THINKMD’s Life-Saving mHealth Platform</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-barry-finette-on-the-hopes-and-challenges-for-thinkmds-life-saving-mhealth-platform</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 17:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-barry-finette-on-the-hopes-and-challenges-for-thinkmds-life-saving-mhealth-platform</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DAI and THINKMD connected in 2016 through DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/innovation-action-challenge-winners-begin-implement-their-solutions-field&quot;&gt;Innovation into Action Challenge&lt;/a&gt;. Our strategic partnership will leverage DAI’s international development network to bring THINKMD’s digital health products to new markets, while THINKMD’s technology will enhance DAI’s global health toolkit. As part of this partnership, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-invests-in-thinkmds-clinical-assessment-technology&quot;&gt;DAI led THINKMD’s latest financing round&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founded in 2014, THINKMD soon introduced its first product, MEDSINC—a mobile health platform that enables non-healthcare professionals in marginalized locales lacking doctors, nurses, and clinics—to perform clinical assessment, triage, early treatment, and follow-up, especially on infants and young children. THINKMD’s second product, DATASINC, aggregates and analyzes public health and epidemiology data for a variety of uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thinkmd.org/&quot;&gt;THINKMD&lt;/a&gt; was co-founded by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thinkmd.org/barry-finette/&quot;&gt;Barry Finette&lt;/a&gt;, a professor of pediatrics, microbiology, and molecular genetics at the University of Vermont College of Medicine and Vermont Children’s Hospital. Finette’s expertise is in clinical and transitional research, and he is a clinical attending physician in general, emergency, critical, and acute care medicine. He has participated in numerous medical research projects and relief missions in countries worldwide. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Developments&lt;/em&gt; recently asked Finette, pictured below in the Philippines, about the prospects for MEDSINC. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Barry-pic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Barry-pic&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What sparked the idea for the MEDSINC platform?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For nearly 30 years, I have had the privilege to serve as a pediatrician for families around the world. The most difficult experience has been seeing children dying from treatable diseases such as pneumonia, dehydration secondary to diarrhea, and infections. The main reason for these preventable deaths is the vast shortage of healthcare professionals and limited healthcare delivery infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these locales, the best solution is to devise a way to transfer medical knowledge and basic but important skills to non-healthcare professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;My idea was to merge evidenced-based medicine for the clinical assessment, triage, and treatment of children with the power of mobile technology—then put it into the hands of minimally skilled frontline healthcare workers, thereby expanding healthcare capacity directly in the communities where the humanitarian need was greatest.&amp;quot;—Barry Finette&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What sicknesses or medical situations are most common in these locales that can be addressed remotely?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many low- and middle-income countries, perinatal and under-5 mortality is very high. MEDSINC evaluates these children using the same parameters that I would as a pediatrician—severity of respiratory distress, dehydration, malnutrition, and risk of infection. It also screens for common illnesses based on local epidemiology and prevalence through configuring the platform—these illnesses typically include malaria, meningitis, anemia, skin infections, urinary tract infections, ear infections, measles, and dysentery. Considering just these illnesses, expanded access to mobile-enabled triage and treatment recommendations could prevent, based on our current modeling, 300 child deaths per 1,000 MEDSINC users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In addition to people suffering and perhaps dying unnecessarily, what are the consequences of untreated ailments to local communities?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences are significant. High infant and childhood mortality damages every aspect of families’ lives. In communities, prevalent childhood illness devastates both emotionally &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; economically. Family members’ ability to work is undermined when they must care for a child or travel hours or days to try to see a doctor. These families are generally larger than those in countries with lower childhood mortality, and the ability to earn income is imperative. Direct and indirect costs to communities are compounded at regional and country levels. Through the implementation of MEDSINC, our models suggest that $19.4 million in productivity gains could be seen per 1,000 MEDSINC users by decreasing morbidity and mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/215518121&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There appears to be a great need for better local healthcare in many corners of the globe, but is there a calculated market demand for MEDSINC?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absolutely. The social impact opportunity is immense, but the market opportunity is just as great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current and projected technology offerings are configurable to many contexts to solve problems for customers in many sectors—including point-of-care assessment and treatment, humanitarian and emergency response and assistance, health system capacity building, and disease and outbreak surveillance. MEDSINC can fill needs that enable healthcare system efficiency and sustainability without sacrificing quality. We have tested MEDSINC with internationally recognized global health leaders on four continents and developed strategic and commercial partnerships with leading global healthcare groups and organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What were the most important requirements MEDSINC had to meet?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We studied, observed, and listened first to the beneficiaries—to understand their needs and design a scalable, efficient, mobile platform solution. The main design principle was simplicity over complexity in filtering out the noise and focusing on what mattered. The platform had to have a simple and intuitive user interface and it had to function on/offline, on any web-enabled device. Furthermore, we wanted the platform to act as a continuous learning and training tool for the user. Finally, the tool needed to connect the user to the broader health system as a knowledge acquisition network—facilitating data acquisition and storage, capturing real-time and geo-located health data, and enabling communication between users and healthcare professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Finette-QA-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Finette-QA-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where has MEDSINC been used so far, and how has that gone?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have performed validation and usability-accessibility testing in four continents and across a range of settings, from hospitals in the United States to rural communities in Burkina Faso and urban slums in Bangladesh. Our testings have shown that with minimal training, clinical assessments performed by frontline health workers using MEDSINC correlate from 80 percent to greater than 95 percent compared with physicians’ assessments. In July, MEDSINC was implemented with our initial adopter, Save the Children International in Dhaka, Bangladesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What have you learned from this experience that you have fed back into the product?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve always been ready to question the way things are and we have been willing to push boundaries and disrupt where appropriate. We see every validation testing, implementation, etc., as an opportunity to learn and improve upon the platform. We rigorously collect and assess user feedback—continuously iterating and ensuring a product-market fit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is DATASINC?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DATASINC is our data repository and analytics tool based on the data that MEDSINC generates through patient interactions. DATASINC translates aggregated MEDSINC data into informative dashboards and reports. This data and analysis offer actionable insights that organizations, governments, or companies can use to make strategic decisions regarding the health of their populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Finette-QA-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Finette-QA-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will be the effect of rolling out MEDSINC and DATASINC in resource-poor countries?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The knowledge and data we accumulate via DATASINC leads to new ideas and solutions. Developing a valuable data repository elevates healthcare knowledge, which expands capacity and delivery. Digital health platforms such as MEDSINC connect the existing health workforce in these countries with established, evidence-based medicine. By empowering these local health workers to deliver basic health services, we build up a country’s existing health infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;WHO-UNICEF estimates that 3 million children aged 5 and under die each year from illnesses that could have been prevented with appropriate clinical assessments and early therapeutic intervention. If left unresolved, the lack of basic healthcare in resource-poor countries alone will lead to 50 million preventable childhood deaths by 2030.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the business model for THINKMD and MEDSINC?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its core, THINKMD is a healthcare innovation company. We are initially focused on providing software and data analytics solutions to a wide range of users. The first products we offer are MEDSINC and DATASINC. We recently launched our first &lt;em&gt;commercial&lt;/em&gt; implementation of these platforms with Save the Children in Bangladesh. We have a pipeline of partners interested in adopting these products, and as we move our technology out further we’ll grow both MEDSINC and DATASINC revenues. Through growth in users, we’ll generate a profit margin that enables the venture to sustain itself and support internal operations, while continuing to innovate and deliver on our product roadmap of innovations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Finette-QA-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Finette-QA-4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you finding to be the main hurdles to implementing MEDSINC in developing and conflict-affected countries?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main hurdle we face is acceptance of our new technology, coupled with a slow adoption cycle among government and nongovernmental organizations. The process of confirming interest and getting adoption and contracts is traditionally quite slow for those types of entities and is something we must constantly navigate as a small and young company. That said, our persistence is starting to pay off and we are beginning to see partners adopt our products based on their acute need for our solutions, and the fact that we’ve done the appropriate testing and validation to prove that our products work and are user friendly. Our partnerships with groups like Save the Children, UNICEF, and DAI are each force multipliers in our pursuit of product adoption and scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What if anything has come so far from your partnership with DAI? Insights? New ideas for application?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collaboration between our teams has already yielded a lot of critical opportunities. Obviously, THINKMD neatly fits within DAI’s Global Health program, especially with DAI’s expertise and focus on tech-enabled healthcare data and analytics. We are engaged on a pipeline of potential projects and look forward to being on the ground implementing with DAI’s health-focused projects soon. In addition to health, we’ve been thrilled to see interest from other DAI programs, in arenas such as water, sanitation, and hygiene (WASH), governance, and countering violent extremism. Notwithstanding the healthcare focus of our software, the basic clinical and data-gathering solution we provide can add significant direct value to a number of different types of projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Possibilities: The Role of Governance in Countering Violent Extremism in Iraq</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-possibilities-the-role-of-governance-in-countering-violent-extremism-in-iraq</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 17:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Bryan Schuetz</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-possibilities-the-role-of-governance-in-countering-violent-extremism-in-iraq</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Can improving governance contribute to the fight against violent extremism? While the absence of good governance is often cited as a driver of violent extremism, it is less clear how the &lt;em&gt;presence&lt;/em&gt; of good governance can contribute to its reduction. In the case of Iraq, violence has not only been endemic for much of its modern history, but violence itself was the basis of governance and often glorified as a legitimate lever of change. This paper explores how improving governance can both inhibit radicalization and promote de-radicalization, drawing in part on examples taken from U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and other projects in Iraq, Afghanistan, and Sudan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/saladdin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;saladdin&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Obama Administration, the U.S. Government policy on countering violent extremism (CVE) was articulated by the Department of State and USAID in two papers appearing in 2011 and 2016, as well as in a White House conference on the subject in 2015. It would perhaps be more accurate to say that these documents reflect one aspect of the U.S. Government response, since the overwhelming majority of resources devoted to CVE have supported military or policing operations against violent extremist organizations. Daniel Aldrich has estimated that between FY 2001 and 2012, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.lib.purdue.edu/gpridocs/8/&quot;&gt;only 5 percent of the total&lt;/a&gt; amount spent on the “War on Terror” went to diplomatic and development efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While such “hard power” operations are no doubt critical, by definition they take place after radicalization has taken place. They address an existing problem rather than prevent its emergence. Within the U.S. Government, there is an ongoing debate as to whether CVE efforts should comprise mainly military operations or whether we need a greater emphasis on non-kinetic and non-lethal approaches. My supposition is that the latter approach not only mitigates violent extremism—it may also assist military operations when these are deemed necessary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Iraq, the effort to improve governance in general has been complicated by weak existing government structures. Since the U.S.-led invasion in 2003, Iraqi governments have had to contend with intense sectarian mistrust, which has led to near civil war-like conditions compounded by self-imposed problems of corruption and lack of transparency. Absent general security—real or perceived—Iraqis have taken shelter within their narrower ethnic or sectarian identities, urged on by unscrupulous politicians, religious leaders, and neighboring countries enacting their own agendas. Recent polling and events indicate that the current Iraqi government continues to be seen as a largely Shia institution that enjoys limited legitimacy among the country’s Sunnis. While extremism is not purely a Sunni phenomenon, their grievances have been exploited by transnational Sunni extremist groups including al Qaeda and, currently, ISIS.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various solutions have been proposed to address Iraq’s deficit of good governance. Efforts to strengthen local governance by increasing accountability and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.atlanticcouncil.org/blogs/menasource/the-role-of-decentralization-in-combatting-extremist-influence-in-iraq&quot;&gt;decentralizing power&lt;/a&gt; to the provinces have taken on particular importance. While these efforts are valuable in their own right, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/iraq/governance&quot;&gt;they do not directly take on the issue of violent extremism&lt;/a&gt;. They do, however, attempt to improve some of the conditions widely held to foster such extremism. Given that much of the recent literature on CVE emphasizes the importance of a local approach, the prospect of using planned programming to improve local governance to strengthen CVE efforts appears promising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/quadissya.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;quadissya&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is CVE?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the vast resources spent to address violent extremism, it has no universally agreed definition. Writing for the Foreign Policy Research Institute, Will McCants and Clinton Watts found “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fpri.org/article/2012/12/u-s-strategy-for-countering-violent-extremism-an-assessment/&quot;&gt;there is not a shared view of what CVE is or what it should do&lt;/a&gt;” when referring to U.S. Government policy initiatives. In their 2016 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pdf.usaid.gov/pdf_docs/PBAAE503.pdf&quot;&gt;Joint Strategy on CVE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, USAID and State defined CVE as “proactive actions to counter efforts by violent extremists to radicalize, recruit, and mobilize followers to violence and to address specific factors that facilitate violent extremist recruitment and radicalization to violence.” This definition implies that CVE takes place before radicalization by emphasizing the pre-emptive nature of the activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, efforts to suppress radicalization before it occurs must form a central piece of the policy response. Others have stressed that in order for CVE to be effective, it must also provide a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/markaz/2016/03/21/a-how-to-on-countering-violent-extremism/&quot;&gt;path back from radicalization&lt;/a&gt;—a redemption that may occur after incarceration or other legal sanctions but that also prevents a return to radicalization. Some observers have sought to distinguish between sympathizers of radical extremist groups and full-blown supporters (see McCants and Watts), while others note the difficulties in doing so, pointing out that members of violent extremist organizations often separate themselves from the community in which most sympathizers are found, although they communicate with them, often via social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the difficulty in defining CVE stems from difficulties in describing it. Understood from a larger social, cultural, and political context, violent extremism can be seen as the product of numerous factors, such as marginalization or as a religiously justified response to political circumstances. But as our focus moves down to the community and even to the individual level, other factors emerge that can only be understood in a local context. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jia.sipa.columbia.edu/national-strategic-framework-countering-violent-extremism-jordan&quot;&gt;researchers found&lt;/a&gt; that youth in Kenya were motivated to join al-Shabab largely because of the lack of educational opportunities, while young men in Saudi Arabia presented religious justifications for their radicalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A consensus holds that there is no “silver bullet” to tackle the multiplicity of causes leading to radicalization, just as there is no single path leading there. But considerable attention has been given to the various “push” and “pull” factors driving individuals toward violent extremism. In USAID and State’s &lt;em&gt;Joint Strategy&lt;/em&gt;, cited above, push factors “create the opportunities for violent extremists to gain traction,” while pull factors include those tactics used by extremist organizations to attract recruits. Push factors include systematic human rights violations, marginalization, ungoverned or poorly governed areas, and endemic corruption; pull factors include the perversion of religious doctrine or an appeal to an individual’s sense of self-worth or desire for advancement. Extremist organizations may also goad an individual to avenge perceived injustices. Implicit in all these factors is the idea that traditional political means are incapable of correcting the existing, intolerable situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Aldrich sees this last concept as an opening for the use of “soft power” in CVE: “recognizing the multiple factors which can radicalize individuals and either push or pull them to join violent extremist organizations, the soft approach to counter-terrorism seeks to decrease the likelihood of recruitment and dry up the labor pool for potential terrorists.” For Aldrich, soft power may “give potential recruits a viable alternative for which to live, not die,” a useful corollary to U.S. Admiral and Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff Mike Mullen’s recognition that “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foxnews.com/story/2008/09/10/mullen-cannot-kill-our-way-to-victory-in-afghanistan.html&quot;&gt;We cannot kill our way to victory&lt;/a&gt;.” In addition, kinetic operations can cause collateral damage that undermines CVE efforts by reinforcing the narrative of grievances against the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lister-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lister-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Should Be Expected from a CVE Program in Iraq?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the absence of good governance is one of the push factors driving extremist recruitment, and if—as the &lt;em&gt;Joint Strategy&lt;/em&gt; argues—local solutions are critical in addressing drivers of radicalization, then the role of local government in facilitating such solutions is clear and compelling. In the case of Iraq, however, local government is hampered by a low degree of trust, which stems in turn from those governments’ chronic inability to deliver basic services. The many causes of these failures include a lack of staff capacity but also structural problems such as an incomplete program of decentralization, which has led to confusion about roles and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any governance program broadly applicable to the problem of violent extremism in Iraq would at minimum seek to incorporate the following themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data&lt;/strong&gt;. Generally speaking, we need a more accurate rendering of the problems confronted by Iraqi communities. At present, we have mostly anecdotal evidence of the prevalence of specific drivers. For example, regarding the Sunni community, there are an estimated 25,000 fighters currently with ISIS in Syria and Iraq. While some of these are foreigners and others have been forcibly conscripted, we lack reliable information about where most of the fighters come from and the specific factors behind their radicalization.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legitimacy&lt;/strong&gt;. Only through government can the problems of political and social marginalization be addressed successfully in the long term. Additionally, good government can serve as a coordinating body for various strands of a locally implemented CVE policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Religion&lt;/strong&gt;. Given that much of Iraq’s violent extremism is the result of sectarian divisions, interventions need to pay specific attention to the role of religion and seek to recover a tolerant religious narrative to undercut that used by extremist organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Society&lt;/strong&gt;. Civic organizations can play a vital role in addressing those gaps that local governments are unable to fill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration&lt;/strong&gt;. Programs should emphasize both counter-radicalization and de-radicalization, the precise blend depending on local conditions. Where there are significant numbers of returnees from violent organizations, for example, in areas recently recaptured from ISIS, the de-radicalization components will be critical. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Youth&lt;/strong&gt;. CVE depends largely on how well we deal with the problems of youth in situations where extreme violence is the norm rather than the exception. The role of women is of equal importance given the degree to which mothers and other female authority figures influence young people toward or away from violent extremism (as in the case of the “Hakamat” singers in Sudan, discussed below).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lister-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lister-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Case Studies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the writing on CVE is theoretical in nature or offers possible interventions based on generic assumptions extrapolated to what is known of local conditions. In the following section, I attempt to shed some light on the possible approaches in Iraq by reference to approaches proven successful or relevant in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategic Communications&lt;/strong&gt;. USAID’s Kenya Niwajibu Wetu project (known as NIWETU, or “It’s our responsibility” in Kiswaheli), implemented by DAI, shows the importance of strategic communications. A stakeholder engagement forum of 64 participants found that existing counter-terrorism efforts were perceived as coercive, with inadequate attention paid to the rights of those targeted. The forum revealed there was only a limited understanding of what CVE efforts were supposed to accomplish, thanks in part to inadequate attention paid to these efforts by local media. Participants complained that massive security sweeps were exacerbating radicalization rather than diminishing it. And against this backdrop of escalating drivers there was no salient, credible counter-narrative to mitigate extremist messaging. Accordingly, the project decided to engage the Supreme Council of Kenyan Muslims to work with vulnerable youth groups to undercut radicalizing religious narratives, and it took immediate steps to engage the local community such as organizing football tournaments for young men. The bottom line: proactive and responsive strategic communications capacity is critical to the CVE enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Due Diligence and Aftercare&lt;/strong&gt;. In Singapore, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jia.sipa.columbia.edu/national-strategic-framework-countering-violent-extremism-jordan&quot;&gt;as Ghimar Deeb and colleagues report&lt;/a&gt;, security officials designed a complex set of criteria to determine whether a person detained for participating in a violent extremist organization could be released. The assessment included input from religious counselors, prison officials, psychologists, and case workers. In addition, the Aftercare Services Group provides counseling and practical support to families of detainees, including skills training and other forms of post-release help. Family members in general participate in rehabilitation programs where such participation is appropriate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moderate Islam&lt;/strong&gt;. While serving as the Department of State’s Senior Civilian Representative with the 173rd Airborne in Logar and Wardak Provinces, Afghanistan, I worked with Brigade leadership to host influential members of the Logar religious community in Jordan (taking advantage of the presence of a Jordanian battalion posted to our base). Not all the travelers to Jordan were religious figures; some won a place because they were believed to be influential in the broader community. The attendees came back impressed deeply by the peaceful coexistence between Christians and Muslims in Jordan and by seeing a devout Muslim country practicing a more moderate form of their religion. The goal of the visit was to undercut the Taliban message that coexistence between Islam and other religions could only be bought at the price of a compromised faith. While most programs operating in Iraq would not have the resources to fly people abroad, the critical point of disputing a radicalizing religious narrative remains valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative Livelihoods—for Men and Women&lt;/strong&gt;. The Toward Enduring Peace in Sudan (TEPS) program was the sole USAID-funded project in Sudan intended to serve development rather than humanitarian aims. The project worked primarily in conflict zones and sought to mitigate sources of conflict where these existed, but tried as well to help prevent a return to the fighting. As such, TEPS—while not explicitly a CVE program—served many of the same purposes of counter-radicalization and de-radicalization. Noteworthy is TEPS’ work in vocational training and alternative livelihoods for young men and for some of the female-headed households in these areas (of which there were many, due to extended periods of war). Virtually all the young men found employment following their training and after being provided a basic tool kit to help get them started. Similarly, mothers who took alternative livelihoods training reported that their children did not resort to the militias to support their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural Programming&lt;/strong&gt;. A second component of TEPS was peace messaging. Street theater and cultural festivals demonstrated the possibility of peaceful coexistence in areas long ravaged by war. Specifically, the program worked with the “Hakamat” singers, women who traditionally sang songs urging their husbands and sons to fight but in this case took a more conciliatory stance. Of note: Because of sanctions against the Sudanese government, the program could not work directly with national authorities and had to seek indirect approval from local government entities, with implementation though civil society organizations. Such organizations could also be powerful instruments of change in Iraq. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lister-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lister-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most observers believe that the Iraqi Government and its Western allies will prevail militarily against ISIS. But the military campaign will not, by itself, end the cycles of violence that plague Iraqi society. Peace and stability can only be achieved through the creation of government structures seen as legitimate by their constituents. While a political “grand bargain” remains elusive, efforts to make local governments more effective could be an important step in tamping down the violence as local governments tend to be present in areas which are more homogeneous demographically and therefore face fewer of the sectarian challenges that the national government confronts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Efforts to improve local governance could contribute to an overall CVE strategy in the country. In particular, harnessing local civil society organizations—inherently more flexible than government entities—could erect a formidable barrier to the spread of violent extremist organizations. Civil society organizations could take on some of the functions described above, such as bringing religious figures, lay leaders, and government officials together around a more tolerant vision of Islam. And such organizations could deal with the highly localized and in some cases individual factors leading to radicalization, as well as assisting with returnees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this framework, local security forces will still have an important role to play. In some cases, the de-radicalization efforts will have to take place either during or following the extremist’s incarceration. Counter-radicalization can lead to a more effective countering of recruitment techniques used by violent extremist organizations as well as a deeper understanding of the drivers of radicalization in the first place. But as seen in the case of Kenya, a CVE strategy focused exclusively on security can stigmatize an already vulnerable population and increase the likelihood of radicalization rather than reduce it. The purely civilian component of CVE is essential to ensure appropriate messaging and open communications between vulnerable populations and the government.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold Storage Expansion Drives Market Development in Uzbekistan</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/the-proliferation-of-cold-storage-in-uzbekistan</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/the-proliferation-of-cold-storage-in-uzbekistan</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We were amazed to see a packed audience in 2010 when our team from the Global Cold Chain Alliance (GCCA) traveled to Tashkent, Uzbekistan. Our Uzbek trainees came from many backgrounds—teachers, builders, businessmen—eager to learn about this vital link in the agricultural value chain. Most did not have experience in the cold chain, let alone a refrigeration facility to manage, yet they soon formed the foundation for the country’s remarkable cold chain development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a public policy directive issued in 2011 by the Government of Uzbekistan and supported by international financial institutions, the government established a preferential lending regime for the cold storage sector. Uzbekistan has since increased its refrigerated warehousing from 258,000 cubic meters in 2010 to more than 3.5 million cubic meters with technical assistance from the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) AgLinks, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/uzbekistan-aglinks-plus&quot;&gt;AgLinks Plus&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/uzbekistan-usaid-agricultural-value-chain-activity-uzbekistan-uzbekistan-avc&quot;&gt;Agricultural Value Chains&lt;/a&gt; (AVC) programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Farmers have enjoyed greater sales growth in high-value vegetables and fruits—such as grapes, cherries, and apricots—as a result of the crops’ longer lifespans. This boom in cold-storage infrastructure has enhanced Uzbekistan’s market capabilities, improving the abilities of farmers, transporters, grocers, and exporters to increase sales. In 2016 alone, for example, horticultural exports &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eurofresh-distribution.com/news/uzbekistan-increases-its-horticultural-exports&quot;&gt;jumped by 38 percent&lt;/a&gt;, to more than 800,000 tons of fruit and vegetables. These results have also enabled households in Uzbekistan to consume fruits and vegetables more readily and over a longer period of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Uzbek-cold-chain-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Uzbek-cold-chain-2&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Enthusiasm for New Ways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fall of the Soviet Union 25 years ago challenged Uzbekistan’s agricultural community to take on significant agricultural reform and job redistribution. Large farm collectives were broken up and redistributed to private farm enterprises, with infrastructure and agricultural practices needing rehabilitation and retooling to meet the needs of more market-oriented private farms and businesses.
In 2007, DAI launched the USAID AgLinks Uzbekistan program to consolidate the hard-earned gains made under earlier development assistance projects. In addition to building the capacity of private farmers, agroprocessors, and public sector entities, DAI partnered with the GCCA to help new entrants expand Uzbekistan’s cold chain by means of technical assistance designed to complement financial incentives—thereby supporting ongoing agricultural gains and facilitating economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;quote&gt;A “cold chain” manages the temperature of perishable products to maintain quality and safety from slaughter or harvest through distribution to the final consumer, essentially from farm to fork. The cold chain is composed of links, each essential to the integrity of food quality and safety. These links include postharvest activities, processing, transportation, storage and consolidation, retail, and, finally, a consumer’s refrigerator. An effective cold chain enables farmers to diversify production to include high-value perishable crops that increase earnings and benefit supporting industries such as transportation and export. High-value fruits and vegetables fetch higher prices than traditional crops such as cotton and potatoes.&lt;/quote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_copy_app_choice-9&quot; title=&quot;Devs -- Uzbekistan Cold Store&quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/dist/embed.js?9uz&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited shelf life hinders profitability. For example, using traditional means, grapes could only be kept a few months after harvest. Even if the grapes ended up in refrigerated cases at supermarkets, the product had usually been kept uncooled for several days before making it to that point. Following training provided by the AVC project, grapes are now being cooled within 8-12 hours and shelf life has been extended to up to 180 days through the combination of best cold storage practices and the introduction of sulphur dioxide pads to inhibit mold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/210491523&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Market-Driven Agricultural Expansion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proliferation of cold-storage facilities resulted from a combination of forces. First, market demand for fresh fruits required increased cold storage. Second, the Government of Uzbekistan, in collaboration with the World Bank, Asian Development Bank, and others, has emphasized lending to the horticultural industry through preferential loan programs orchestrated with local banks. Third, the technical assistance provided by GCCA through AVC and AgLinks assured these cold-storage facilities are managed using best technical practices. Finally, a rapid return on investment is enabling investors to repay their cold-storage loans and further expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These facilities range in capacity from 20 to 20,000 metric tons. Some of the smaller structures use air conditioners that have been adapted using CoolBot technology, while the larger facilities use commercial-scale refrigeration equipment. GCCA played a major role through the AgLinks Plus project in providing a technical training program for Uzbek refrigeration technicians in direct response to industry demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing number of facilities has also complemented the growing table grape, cherry, and apricot markets. These products now move much more easily into export markets in the region and beyond, growing capabilities and profits for farmers, logistics providers, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uzbekistan &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.int/uzbekistan/news/uzbek-agriculture-progress-and-achievements#&quot;&gt;prioritized agricultural growth&lt;/a&gt; as a means to help address social issues such as employment, wellbeing, and further urban and rural development, and the country itself deserves the lion&amp;rsquo;s share of the credit for its cold storage transformation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Government of Uzbekistan authorized USAID’s horticultural support program and sought  affordable credit options for cold chain developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Uzbek business community, specifically early-adopting producers and exporters, grasped the entrepreneurial opportunity to make the necessary investments in their own business capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collectively, the government and the private sector developed the linkages needed to access international markets willing and able to pay for high-value fruits and vegetables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Uzbek-cold-chain-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Uzbek-cold-chain-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Becoming a Cold-Chain World Leader&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With more than 2,000 cold storage facilities accounting for nearly 4 million cubic meters of capacity, Uzbekistan now ranks among the Global Top 20 in the Global Cold Chain Alliance’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gcca.org/resources/publications/white-papers-reports/global-cold-storage-capacity/&quot;&gt;Global Cold Chain Capacity Report&lt;/a&gt; for 2016, among the likes of China, Brazil, and Mexico. Yet, Uzbekistan still has work to do: it is estimated that total capacity needs to be up to 10 times the present amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AVC and GCCA will continue to promote the development of refrigerated transportation, increased food safety, and the use of larger facilities. It is likely the Uzbek cold chain will undergo  consolidation, reducing the number of facilities but increasing the total capacity, thus driving efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Global Cold Chain Alliance is proud to have partnered in this growth with DAI, USAID, and the people and Government of Uzbekistan in building the foundation for a world class cold chain. As its agricultural value chains continue to develop, Uzbekistan will increasingly become a leader in production, jobs creation, and economic growth in the Central Asian region.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Development Assistance to Catalyze Sound Investments in Emerging and Developing Markets</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-development-assistance-to-catalyze-sound-investments-in-emerging-and-developing-markets</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 13:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-development-assistance-to-catalyze-sound-investments-in-emerging-and-developing-markets</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Investment opportunities in manufacturing, agriculture, and health are as abundant globally as the capital to fund them, but investors in these and other sectors are rightly cautious about entering new countries and taking risks on small and growing businesses and productive infrastructure. Fortunately, there are many examples in these teeming markets of how capital supported by local development expertise and entrepreneurial energy has generated both financial returns and development results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and other donors are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-the-invest-project&quot;&gt;pursuing&lt;/a&gt; “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_Blended_Finance_A_Primer_Development_Finance_Philanthropic_Funders_report_2015.pdf&quot;&gt;blended finance&lt;/a&gt;” as an approach to attract productive capital into developing countries. Blending private capital with donor-funded local expertise and risk-mitigation instruments can leverage donor resources, yield competitive returns for investors, and increase stability and prosperity for citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it already has. DAI is helping to mobilize capital that generates profit and alleviates poverty by convening the right partners, developing solid business plans, structuring investment deals, addressing policy constraints, and realistically projecting and delivering positive outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Blended-pic-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Blended-pic-2&quot; title=&quot;American Apparel and Footwear Association (AAFA) President Rick Helfenbein, left, and DAI&amp;#39;s Juan Estrada of the East Africa Trade and Investment Hub. The AAFA, which represents more than 1,000 brands generating $361 billion in annual U.S. retail sales, recently signed a partnership agreement with the Hub to address constraints to competitiveness and expansion of the industry in East Africa.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Facilitating Trade and Investment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across East Africa, USAID and DAI have engaged transaction advisors CrossBoundary and used pay-for-results contracts to close investment deals. This program under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; (EATIH) has closed $51.1 million of investment transactions in two years for eight firms in the mobile technology, financial services, logistics, dairy, and poultry sectors. An additional $75 million in transactions is pending closure, with $133 million more in the pipeline. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, this pay-for-results approach has shortened the deal-closure timeline from 18 to 24 months to six to 10 months, thereby reducing transaction costs and leading to follow-on deals from other investors. DAI’s local team helps to nurture the pipeline from beginning to end: mapping capital, targeting geographies and sectors, validating opportunities, conducting due diligence, modeling financials, raising funds, structuring transactions, ensuring neutral intermediation, and planning the post-investment phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EATIH issued a second bid for investment transaction services focused on underserved, smaller, export-oriented businesses—specifically, those requiring some assistance to help them become investment ready and seeking up to $1 million in financing. Open Capital Advisors, which has offices in Kenya, Uganda, and Zambia, was contracted and has begun work on a pay-for-results basis. DAI is adapting this results-based model on USAID’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-hub-sath&quot;&gt;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; (SATIH) and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Blended-pic-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Blended-pic-7&quot; title=&quot;The Africa Sourcing and Fashion Week trade expo in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, promoted East African countries as sourcing and investment destinations for international buyers of apparel, textile, leather, and home decor.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;East Africa offers an abundance of small and growing businesses and uninvested capital. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eatradehub.org/&quot;&gt;To support investment&lt;/a&gt;, EATIH developed a deal pipeline for its roster of regional private equity and impact investors. The team also supported companies to become investor ready, while adhering to USAID requirements that investees have regional presence, create jobs, and encourage gender parity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, one multimillion-dollar investment by a private U.S. firm enabled MB PLC (Family Milk) of Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, to boost production from 20,000 liters per day to 60,000. Another private equity firm invested in a regional logistics company, enabling it to convert 100 trucks to cold storage, which is critical for growing agricultural value chains. These trucks are now transporting horticultural produce across borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2016, the Pretoria-based SATIH is also accommodating different types of investors, including pension funds. The pension fund model requires longer-term, equitable returns, with transactions in the $25 million to $500 million range. Investments of this profile tend to be large infrastructure projects such as toll roads or fiber optics, which would help with regional trade. SATIH also works to improve the enabling environment by working to align national investment policies with the Southern Africa Development Community (SADC) and is conducting an investor survey on the investment climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USAID’s support for constructive deal-making is not limited to Africa. Its Jordan Competitiveness Program (JCP) selected 15 companies from three target sectors—ICT, clean technology, and health care—to participate in a Growth Readiness Program. In collaboration with the American University of Beirut and Inventis Consulting Group, JCP designed and delivered technical assistance to each firm, facilitated pitches to investors, and ultimately helped six of the firms raise $17.6 million. American University is now exploring how to institutionalize the program to assist more of Jordan’s small and growing businesses to access capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobilizing Capital in Somaliland&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Somaliland, USAID and DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/somalia-partnership-economic-growth&quot;&gt;conducted the territory’s first business-plan competition&lt;/a&gt;. Local entrepreneurs wowed judges with their entries, the winners earning more than $1 million in matching grants to co-fund their growth in promising sectors such as agriculture, livestock, fisheries, and renewable energy. The businesses leveraged $12 million in local, diaspora, and foreign investor capital—leading, for example, to the development of the region’s first 100 kilowatt (kw) wind energy public-private partnership, which spurred investment by the private sector of an additional 2 megawatts in the wind sector.&lt;/aside&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fueling Ethiopia’s Growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ethiopia, the economy is growing yet remains overwhelmingly poor and rural, so the country is building at least 12 industrial parks to attract investment and create jobs in needful areas. Accordingly, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-private-enterprise-programme-ethiopia-pepe&quot;&gt;Enterprise Partners&lt;/a&gt; program is working with employers at the flagship Hawassa Industrial Park—which hosts firms making clothes for brands such as Tommy Hilfiger and Calvin Klein—by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/development-secretary-priti-patel-stresses-economic-growth-in-visit-to-ethiopia-industrial-park&quot;&gt;organizing training for an estimated 60,000 to 80,000 jobs&lt;/a&gt; in factory operations, warehousing, cleaning, maintenance, and transportation. Five factories are already exporting from the park and 30 other investors have booked production space. The park’s international tenants are covering 75 percent of recruiting and training costs. Similar foreign-funded and market-driven job development is anticipated at the other industrial parks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also under Enterprise Partners, the team is:
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporting the Government of Ethiopia to develop a foreign and domestic investment strategy to meet the demand for “fast fashion”—that is, the capacity to respond quickly to trends in the global apparel sector; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing a bank-managed loan facility where potential investors and investees of private capital in the Ethiopian equity market can use interest-free loans to hire high-quality investment advisors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Blended-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Blended-7&quot; title=&quot;Employees making clothing at the Hawassa Industrial Park in Ethiopia.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Helping Companies Overcome Capital Constraints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldbank.org/en/topic/financialsector/brief/smes-finance&quot;&gt;400 million small and medium-sized businesses in emerging markets&lt;/a&gt; represent hardworking business owners and real growth potential, but development actors and private investors have only scratched the surface of the opportunities at hand. These businesses’ demand for capital is sometimes being met domestically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the USAID/Kenya &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-financial-inclusion-rural-microenterprises-firm&quot;&gt;Financial Inclusion for Rural Microenterprises&lt;/a&gt; (FIRM) project, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/unlocking-capital-across-kenya-how-usaid-firm-pushed-the-frontier-of-financial-services-and-built-a-foundation-for-economic-growth/&quot;&gt;unlocked $1 billion-plus in financing&lt;/a&gt;, mostly for rural businesspeople. The FIRM team worked with more than 100 financial institutions to develop loan products, and demand for capital in marginalized areas did the rest, spurring investment in sectors such as agriculture, water, energy generation, and ICT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all, $186.3 million was leveraged under FIRM for private sector investments in agricultural and food value chains. A pipeline of clean energy projects was developed, with a $7 million deal for a hydroelectric power plant on the Yala River closed in December 2016. Another $120 million in Development Credit Authority guarantees supported $43 million in reduced-risk loans with 16 partner financial institutions. Most importantly, FIRM built a foundation of financial professionals and institutions that will serve the country’s markets for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_copy-061972071246&quot; title=&quot;Copy: &quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/dist/embed.js?j3F&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Poland, where the economy is growing but not energy efficient or environmentally sensitive, DAI and the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development helped &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/polseff-legacy-lower-energy-bills-for-businesses-across-poland-a-financing-model-to-scale-and-replicate/&quot;&gt;create the country’s energy finance sector&lt;/a&gt;. Over seven years, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/poland-polish-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-polseff&quot;&gt;Polish Sustainable Energy Finance Facility&lt;/a&gt; (PolSEFF) assisted five domestic banks to appraise and close more than 2,000 investment opportunities for business owners who had no way to capitalize new or upgraded equipment for heating, cooling, electric power, and insulation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The businesses’ investments, averaging €100,000, are paying for themselves through lowered energy costs. In training 840 bank and leasing staff on responsibly financing energy projects—and developing an online catalogue of more than 700 registered companies and 7,000 eligible products—PolSEFF is well positioned to help capitalize Polish energy needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy finance is a ripe market—DAI also manages the SEFF facility in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/morocco-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-morseff&quot;&gt;Morocco&lt;/a&gt; and is a consortium member in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/western-balkans-sustainable-energy-finance-facility-webseff-i-ii&quot;&gt;Western Balkans SEFF&lt;/a&gt;, which together with PolSEFF aim to manage €430 million for energy efficiency investments by small and growing businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact Bonds in Palestine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Palestine, World Bank &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/palestine-finance-for-jobs-f4j&quot;&gt;Finance for Jobs&lt;/a&gt; (F4J) aims to mobilize private investment and create jobs in the West Bank and Gaza by crowding in private investment, including by: 1) an Entrepreneurship Ecosystem Matching Grant Facility that targets early-stage investment funds for viable projects; and 2) a Development Impact Bond to be issued by the Palestinian Authority. F4J will build capacity in the Palestinian Authority through technical assistance, training, secondments, and internships, and by providing facilities, equipment, and software.&lt;/aside&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Facilitating Capital Flow for Water Infrastructure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will pay for clean water linked to good accessibility and service quality. In the Philippines, public investment for water supply and sanitation projects historically covered only about 20 percent of the need. USAID and DAI &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/innovative-fund-enables-philippine-water-utilities-to-invest/&quot;&gt;closed the financial gap&lt;/a&gt; by institutionalizing private financing for water supply and sanitation projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By leveraging development assistance from Japan, blended capital co-financing between the Philippine government and private banks, and risk-absorbing guarantees, the water industry mobilized more than PhP10.5 billion (US$234 million) in mostly private capital for water and sanitation infrastructure. More than 40 projects were funded, affording 1.3 million Filipinos access to safe water or improved services, with another 5 million projected to be served. Effectively, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/philippines-water-revolving-fund-support-program-pwrf&quot;&gt;Philippines Water Revolving Fund&lt;/a&gt; created by USAID and DAI shifted the Philippines’ water-financing paradigm from purely public to public-private. Today, private banks continue to originate loans with water districts and local government units driven by demand from water consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, to overcome the risk-return hurdle for water investments in Cambodia, water companies jumped at the chance to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aUlchUgIvyw&quot;&gt;acquire results-based financing&lt;/a&gt; to close the financial gap that had prevented the expansion of residential water hookups. By taking advantage of this capital, they extended services to 67,000 new customers in just 18 months while making operational upgrades that benefitted an additional 130,000 rural poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;395&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/37755989?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;703&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Capital—The Next Level of Development Partnering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international development community has been ramping up its partnerships since at least 2001, when USAID launched its Global Development Alliances initiative. Starting in 2010, under USAID’s Grand Challenges for Development program, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-grand-challenges-development-implementation-services&quot;&gt;administered global competitions&lt;/a&gt;—in water access, agricultural mechanization, health services, and literacy—that attracted thousands of entries, led to 104 awards between $100,000 and $2 million, and leveraged $124 million in external funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI itself has made the commitment to invest in companies that have good prospects of delivering reasonable returns while generating development results. For example, in 2002, USAID contracted DAI to assume management of Khan Bank (then known as the Agricultural Bank of Mongolia, an institution indispensable to rural Mongolians) and prepare it for sale. The DAI-led team transformed the failing bank, implementing new policies and procedures, developing and retraining staff, rebranding and marketing the organization, developing new products, and inculcating new values and behaviors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2003, the now-private Khan Bank has been one of the two largest banks in the country, and today it boasts the highest profitability and return on assets. Khan Bank has evolved into a full service universal bank with total assets of $2.7 billion and a network of 536 branches with over 5,000 employees. Equity has increased from $6.5 million to $333 million and loans outstanding rose from $67 million in 2004 to $1.6 billion in 2015. After the USAID engagement and privatization, Khan Bank’s new owners hired DAI directly and DAI took a small ownership stake via stock options based on performance &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.knightlab.com/libs/timeline3/latest/embed/index.html?source=1akaSFOqjWaQdClEsBv_I-TROc6SekbAnVJJAXiifct4&amp;amp;font=Default&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;hash_bookmark=true&amp;amp;initial_zoom=2#event-out-of-africa-the-nmb-connection&quot;&gt;targets&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, DAI has invested in small and growing businesses offering technological solutions to development problems: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In February 2017, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-invests-in-thinkmds-clinical-assessment-technology&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a financial commitment to ThinkMD, an early-stage global healthcare innovation company whose first product, MEDSINC, is a mobile clinical assessment platform that enables anyone, anywhere to assess the sickness of a child and provide triage and treatment recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In March, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-invests-in-mobileodt-a-breakthrough-provider-of-cervical-cancer-detection-tech?related-box&quot;&gt;invested&lt;/a&gt; in the mHealth service provider MobileODT, which combines advanced optical technology with smartphone capabilities to bring affordable cancer detection services to underserved communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In April, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-joins-forces-with-local-content-solutions-ltd&quot;&gt;acquired&lt;/a&gt; U.K.-based Local Content Solutions to complement DAI’s work in the oil, gas, mining, and infrastructure sectors in corporate social investment, government and community engagement, and local content and related supply chain management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-joins-investors-circle-ande-global-leaders-in-mobilizing-investment-and-capital-for-small-and-growing-businesses&quot;&gt;recently joined&lt;/a&gt; the Global Accelerator Network, Investors’ Circle and the Aspen Network of Development Entrepreneurs, global leaders in supporting small and growing businesses dedicated to improving their communities and the world. DAI has formed consortia with these and other organizations to pursue opportunities in blended finance. Together, we are confident that companies and investors will increasingly seek to invest capital in emerging markets that will generate positive financial and social returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Blended-pic-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Blended-pic-5&quot; title=&quot;A community health worker in Bangladesh using the MEDSINC platform developed by DAI partner ThinkMD.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Leveraging Development Assistance to Invest Profitably&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, USAID, other donors, and their implementing partners have a deep and growing well of in-country experience in the investment arena—experience on which investors can draw to reduce their risk in markets that have tremendous upside. At the same time, USAID’s assistance to investors is increasingly producing development results such as economic growth, expanded access to energy and water, and increased stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As USAID and other donors and investors explore these opportunities in blended finance, they can do so knowing that there is an abundance of local expertise and entrepreneurial energy primed to assist, in all corners of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PolSEFF’s Legacy: Lower Energy Bills for Businesses Across Poland; a Financing Model to Scale and Replicate</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/polseff-legacy-lower-energy-bills-for-businesses-across-poland-a-financing-model-to-scale-and-replicate</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 17:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/polseff-legacy-lower-energy-bills-for-businesses-across-poland-a-financing-model-to-scale-and-replicate</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While Poland’s private sector grew steadily in the post-Soviet era, its reliance on old energy equipment and poorly insulated facilities contributed to the country becoming one of the highest energy consumers in Europe. In 2010, when the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD) launched the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/poland-polish-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-polseff&quot;&gt;Polish Sustainable Energy Financing Facility &lt;/a&gt;(PolSEFF), few business owners had invested in energy efficiency measures compared with the European Union average, and Polish lending institutions were not prepared to finance these types of upgrades. As a result, business owners continued to pay unnecessarily high energy bills and emit unnecessarily high amounts of carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poland has since seen the emergence of a thriving energy finance sector. Under PolSEFF and PolSEFF 2, both managed by DAI, more than 2,000 businesses took out loans to finance new and upgraded equipment and insulation that reduced their energy usage and saved them significant money. Investments such as these might seem like an obvious choice, but creating and sustaining this new financial sector required multifaceted assistance from the PolSEFF team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Building an Energy Finance Sector&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EBRD’s sustainable energy financing facilities (SEFFs) work by offering large initial loans to financial institutions in a country for “on-lending” to businesses to pay for energy efficiency projects. Under both phases of PolSEFF, five partner financial institutions loaned more than €200 million from the EBRD to Polish small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs, or businesses with 250 or fewer employees). PolSEFF advisors trained staff members at these lending institutions to package and market the new loans, including how to calculate average return on investment from energy-efficient appliances and determine reasonable interest rates, down payments, and collateral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To connect lending institutions to borrowers, PolSEFF conducted publicity campaigns and events to promote the specialized loans to targeted businesses and provided technical advice on energy efficiency options to interested companies. The facility also offered 10 to 15 percent of the total loan for companies to keep as a grant, with funding provided by the European Union for PolSEFF and by the Polish National Fund for Environmental Protection and Water Management for PolSEFF 2. As word spread, PolSEFF found interested borrowers from numerous industries, from a frozen food manufacturer in need of a better cooling system to an advertising agency seeking a more efficient printing press. The PolSEFF team provided independent assessments on the viability of the proposed projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Mine_Master_conultant_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mine_Master_conultant_1&quot; title=&quot;PolSEFF consultants provided assessments to businesses.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since businesses and financial institutions were unsure of which products qualified as energy efficient under the loan terms, PolSEFF developed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Ww7Rydywh6Y&quot;&gt;List of Eligible Materials and Equipment&lt;/a&gt; (LEME), an online searchable catalogue of pre-approved energy-efficient products. The LEME continues to be widely utilized by lenders and borrowers, with more than 70 percent of products purchased and leased under PolSEFF coming from the catalogue. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Quick Returns on Investment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New business investments can take years before owners see a payoff, but many PolSEFF borrowers did not wait long to see a positive impact on their bottom lines. For example, Mine Master, a producer of drilling and bolting machinery for the mining industry, suffered from high heating costs due to poorly insulated production facilities. After deciding to invest in a new heating system and modern insulation, PolSEFF engineers advised Mine Master on the best type of insulation materials and quantity needed. “The results exceeded my expectations,” said Jerzy Nadolny, president of Mine Master’s management board. “We expected that we could achieve energy savings of 30 percent, but in fact we recorded savings of 50 percent, which is a lot for a company like us.” See the video below about Mine Master: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/68727241&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PH Jarex, a family-run flower business, used a PolSEFF loan to purchase a cutting-edge combined heat and power generator for its expansive indoor growing facilities. The company reduced its annual energy usage by 41 percent, saving €233,000 a year and reducing its carbon dioxide emissions by more than 3,000 tons. In addition to saving money, the updated generator offered another benefit that complemented the company’s product line. “The unit is equipped with a COdiNOx catalytic converter,” said Agnieszka Plasek, Managing Director at PH Jarex. “Normally the combustion products are emitted into the atmosphere, but we utilize the carbon dioxide instead of releasing it into the atmosphere; it is fed into the greenhouses where plants process it into oxygen.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/PH_Jarex.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;PH_Jarex&quot; title=&quot;PH Jarex, a family-run flower business, used a loan to purchase a cutting-edge combined heat and power generator for its indoor growing facilities.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Growing Impact of Energy Finance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2006, the EBRD’s sustainable energy financing facilities have provided more than €2.8 billion in financing to 104 financial institutions in 22 countries, which was on-lent to 75,000 clients. The EBRD recently re-branded SEFFs as GEFFs (Green Economy Financing Facilities), which now include financing for a wider range of resource efficiency, such as upgrades that reduce water usage. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s partnership with the EBRD and its energy financing facilities began in Bulgaria with management of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/bulgaria-energy-efficiency-and-renewable-energy-credit-line-support-rational&quot;&gt;Bulgarian Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Credit Line &lt;/a&gt; from 2004 to 2013. In addition to PolSEFF, DAI manages the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/morocco-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-morseff&quot;&gt;SEFF in Morocco&lt;/a&gt; and is a consortium member in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/western-balkans-sustainable-energy-finance-facility-webseff-i-ii&quot;&gt;Western Balkans SEFF&lt;/a&gt;. These facilities together aim to distribute €170 million to companies to finance energy efficiency projects. The EBRD expanded its work in Poland in 2016 by launching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/polish-residential-energy-efficiency-financing-facility-poland-reff&quot;&gt;Poland Residential Energy Financing Facility&lt;/a&gt;, managed by a consortium of the Polish Foundation for Energy Efficiency and DAI, to improve energy efficiency in the residential sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;PolSEFF&amp;rsquo;s Legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across more than 2,000 projects in all 16 of Poland’s provinces, PolSEFF helped the country’s private sector achieve annual energy savings of 342,000 megawatt hours and avoid more than 100,000 tons of carbon dioxide emissions per year—the equivalent of the annual energy consumption of 44,000 Polish households and carbon dioxide emissions of 50,000 cars. For its innovative use of market-driven financing to bring about these reductions, PolSEFF was honored with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/polish-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-wins-clean-energy-award&quot;&gt;Financing Deal of the Year award&lt;/a&gt; at the 2016 Central and Eastern European Clean Energy Awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/PolSEFF_award.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EBRDawardPolSEFF&quot; title=&quot;Anna Chmielewska, Principal Banker at the EBRD, accepting PolSEFF&amp;#39;s Financing Deal of the Year award at the 2016 Central and Eastern European Clean Energy Awards.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PolSEFF’s most enduring legacy will be establishing a self-sustaining energy efficiency financing market in Poland. By training 840 staff at five financial institutions, PolSEFF built the capability of lenders to carry on energy financing initiatives. For example, Bank BNP Paribas signed onto the Green Initiative sponsored by the European Investment Bank, which functioned similarly to the ERBD’s SEFF model, while continuing to lend PolSEFF 2 extension funds. Two additional lenders have taken loans from the EBRD for financing programs that will utilize PolSEFF’s LEME catalogue, and the remaining two expressed interest in taking new funds to continue similar programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By demonstrating the viability of innovative energy financing approaches, PolSEFF paved the way for future lending facilities. PolSEFF was the first EBRD facility to introduce loans for leasing equipment, and PolSEFF’s LEME will remain active for continued use. The EBRD is working on a larger, global LEME—the Technology Selector—which will widen categories to include water and material efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2017, at the 11th &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eudevdays.eu/&quot;&gt;European Development Days&lt;/a&gt; in Brussels, leaders from the European Commission and their development partners, including the EBRD, meet to share lessons learned and discuss trends and challenges. This year’s theme—“Investing in Development,” focusing on private sector engagement—marks a fitting opportunity to share the success and significance of PolSEFF, which exemplifies how market-driven, private sector-led solutions can reconcile business growth and reduced carbon emissions, and show that goals once viewed as mutually exclusive can in fact go hand in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://infogram.io/p/b932e0852df24b3c956c6b2abe4417fe.png&quot; alt=&quot;infogram image&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philippines Increases Tax Collections by $1.1 Billion Year Over Year—Without Raising Rates</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What would you do with an extra $1.1 billion? That amount represents the additional taxes collected by the Philippines government during the first quarter of 2017 versus the same period in 2016. This 12.2 percent increase—during the country&amp;rsquo;s tax-collecting season—followed the rapid adoption by taxpayers of an electronic tax-filing system introduced by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/philippines-facilitating-public-investment-fpi&quot;&gt;Facilitating Public Investment&lt;/a&gt; (FPI) program, implemented by DAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By increasing Q1 tax collections from PHP421.4 billion to PHP472.9 billion, or US$8.4 billion to $9.5 billion—without raising tax rates—the Philippines will be able to invest in its ambitious program to develop infrastructure and eradicate extreme poverty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_e_filing_soars_in_philippines_fueling_tax_revenue_growth&quot; title=&quot;E-Filing Soars in Philippines, Fueling Tax-Revenue Growth&quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/dist/embed.js?odf&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2013, FPI has assisted the Philippines’ Bureau for Internal Revenue (BIR) to improve its e-filing and e-payment systems, and recently the FPI team assisted the Department of Finance (DOF) in drafting comprehensive tax reform, including tax policy and administration. FPI continues to assist the DOF as the proposed reform goes through parliamentary debates and to facilitate numerous public-private policy dialogue events on the proposed changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since introducing electronic BIR forms in 2015, the Philippines government has &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-experiences-major-increase-in-electronic-tax-filing/&quot;&gt;seen the popularity of its electronic tax-filing option soar&lt;/a&gt;—from 1.9 million electronic returns in 2014 to 17.4 million in 2016. While only certain taxpayers were mandated to use e-filing, the BIR reported increased e-filing across all taxpayer categories as Filipinos found the new eBIRForms system to be stable and reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;Complementing its work on the revenue side, FPI is also ramping up its assistance to the Department of Budget and Management (DBM), including:
 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporting passage of a new Budget Law, currently filed for parliamentary discussion, that will establish a performance-based-budgeting process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparing a new Budget Manual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing a comprehensive system for monitoring and evaluating expenditures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving government procurement processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advising on budget decentralization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineering business processes related to budget preparation and execution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supporting the Philippines’ Open Government Partnership&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Homegrown Revenues for Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines’ achievement &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/long-term-fiscal-reform-takes-root-in-el-salvador-and-elsewhere/&quot;&gt;exemplifies an encouraging trend&lt;/a&gt; of developing countries undertaking fiscal reforms to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/when-tax-reform-leads-to-increased-funding-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;increase their domestic resource mobilization&lt;/a&gt;. At the July 2015 Third International Conference on Financing for Development in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia—attended by more than 110 heads of state, ministers, and officials from 38 countries—donors such as USAID and the U.K. Department for International Development pledged a doubling of assistance by 2020 for programs to mobilize domestic revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepping up domestic resource mobilization, the Addis attendees agreed, “is core to ensuring solid financing of the Post-2015 Development Agenda. [While] domestic public resources are a more stable and sustainable source of income, they also strengthen a legitimate relationship between citizens and the state and foster good governance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Philippines first attempted to introduce e-filing 17 years ago, it was one of just a few countries using the method. Electronic filing and payments seemed like a perfect solution for a country with a population dispersed across more than 7,000 islands. However, e-filing was never adopted in significant numbers due to persistent technical issues and the e-system’s complicated design. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faced with an unstable e-filing system and impending April 15 filing deadline, many taxpayers simply did not file or pay their taxes. In mid-2015, FPI provided a new design to the BIR that made e-filing readily available, convenient, and scalable. Compared to the old system or manual filing using paper returns, the new system has greatly improved taxpayer service and compliance. For taxpayers who need in-person service, waiting lines in regional tax administration offices have been reduced by hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_fiscal_space____philippines_fpi&quot; title=&quot;Fiscal Space -- Philippines FPI&quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/dist/embed.js?6L7&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Beyond Hardware and Software&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes more than rolling out new hardware and software to bridge a country’s fiscal gaps. FPI led a nationwide public awareness campaign, worked with mobile payment providers and local banks to expand channels and locations for tax payments, and intensively promoted good governance and anti-corruption transparency initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course there is always an opportunity to scrutinize how you spend the money that is raised, and spend it more wisely. For example, FPI’s technical assistance to the DBM streamlined key internal business processes and helped identify the opportunity to free up $500 million within the 2016 national government budget. Collectively, FPI’s activities have helped expand the Philippines government’s “&lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/how-tax-assistance-from-usaid-dfid-helps-developing-countries-to-manage-money-and-help-themselves/&quot;&gt;fiscal space&lt;/a&gt;” for investing domestically in its own development, a result we are confident will endure beyond the life of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Land Rights Real</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/making-land-rights-real</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Bryan Schuetz</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/making-land-rights-real</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Land rights are largely taken for granted in the developed world. Yet for many people in developing nations, land rights have no reality. In the developed world, land rights are almost always recorded in secure registers, but this is not the case elsewhere. It is estimated that as many as 90 percent of the world’s poorest people enjoy neither security of tenure nor secure access to land. In Africa, this means that more than 500 million and perhaps as many as 750 million people are living without any legal security or proof of claim to the land they are occupying. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The establishment and registration of formal or customary rights of occupancy are essential building blocks in ensuring people have security so that they are then protected from forced evictions or a denial of their occupancy right. Consequently, they are able to pass on these land rights to others through inheritance or transfer. Various studies have shown that tenure security encourages people to invest more in their land, leading to greater productivity (whether it be agricultural land or urban retail property). Ultimately, this investment translates into increased household income and reduced poverty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, we have seen a global shift in how large-scale registration of land rights is brought about. DAI is leading this global change by championing the low-cost “fit for purpose” approach to mass registration, which has been used to identify, demarcate, and register millions of land parcels at an average cost of less than US$10 per parcel—all in highly compressed time frames. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/rwanda-support-land-tenure-regularisation&quot;&gt;Rwanda&lt;/a&gt;, DAI completed the registration of more than 10 million parcels in less than five years; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-land-investment-transformation-lift&quot;&gt;Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt;, we are embarking on a similar project that will cover more than 14 million parcels. In both cases, the approach is community based and highly participatory. In other countries such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/cape-verde-preparation-comprehensive-field-operations-manual-and-completing&quot;&gt;Cape Verde&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-consultancy-and-technical-assistance-mca-mozambique-land-component&quot;&gt;Mozambique&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/tanzania-feed-future-tanzania-land-tenure-assistance-lta&quot;&gt;Tanzania&lt;/a&gt;, DAI has harnessed new technology (watch video below for more) to make field data collection simpler and faster. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/206238160&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting lessons have emerged from this unique experience, and we hope to share these insights in the &lt;em&gt;Making Land Rights Real&lt;/em&gt; series of articles, beginning with four articles covering a range of contexts: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owen Edwards captures much of the “best practice” developed through the new low-cost approach and emphasises the need for the process to reach all parts of the community and include all possible claimants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/sarah-maguire&quot;&gt;Sarah Maguire&lt;/a&gt; and the late Alice Lahai present an interesting case from a U.K. Department for International Development (DFID) project in Sierra Leone. Although the project was centred on security and justice issues, it found that a key way to strengthen women’s empowerment in the community is to improve their land rights. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This link between land rights and women’s empowerment is further supported by a recent DFID-commissioned rapid evidence assessment carried out by DAI as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-evidence-demand-core-services&quot;&gt;Evidence on Demand programme&lt;/a&gt;. Led by Geoffrey Payne, the DAI team carried out an extensive literature search to look at policies, strategies, and interventions that foster security of tenure and respect for legitimate land rights. We also looked at how investments have taken into account existing legitimate land rights in developing countries. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/richard-baldwin&quot;&gt;Richard Baldwin&lt;/a&gt;, DAI’s Global Practice Lead for Land Tenure and Property Rights, describes the findings of that study, which show that titling and registration have been by far the most successful strategy in protecting land rights, and that clarification of land rights has a significant impact on women’s empowerment. These findings argue strongly that the link between women’s empowerment and secure land rights should be more strongly emphasised in development programmes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While we consider land rights as a developing world issue, there are also issues closer to home. Karol Boudreaux provides a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/the-law-of-the-land-recent-cases-show-legal-support-for-local-people/&quot;&gt;case study&lt;/a&gt; describing a landmark case where historical claims by indigenous people in Canada have finally been recognised—making their land rights real at last. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We look forward to sharing additional articles in the coming months as part of this series.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Mobile Technology for First Registration of Land: Lessons Learned in Tanzania</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-mobile-technology-for-first-registration-of-land-lessons-learned-in-tanzania</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2017 14:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-mobile-technology-for-first-registration-of-land-lessons-learned-in-tanzania</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“In the 21st century,” as I write with my co-authors in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/from-land-tenure-regularisation-to-a-sustainable-land-register/&quot;&gt;companion piece to this article&lt;/a&gt;, “land administration systems will nearly always be developed using digital systems. Assuming they are well designed, then they are more secure, more efficient, more transparent, and more accessible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the test of any tool is with users in the field. This axiom of development is borne out by DAI’s experience implementing a land tenure registration activity in Tanzania, where a pilot of the open source Mobile Application for Secure Tenure (MAST) has yielded important lessons that we are now incorporating into the U.S. Government’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/tanzania-feed-future-tanzania-land-tenure-assistance-lta&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Land Tenure Assistance (LTA)&lt;/a&gt; activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Tanzania, the United States is supporting investment in agriculture to fight hunger and improve food security. Achieving this objective requires formalizing and strengthening rights to land and other productive assets. While Tanzania’s legal framework provides protections for land users, village-level land tenure can be insecure and vulnerable to outside interests. Land in many villages is often neither mapped according to use nor individually demarcated and legally registered. There is also disparity in how domestic and international investors access land, which may lead to illegal transactions or land grabs. These factors constrain economic growth and investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pic%201-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pic 1-1&quot; title=&quot;The Feed the Future Land Tenure Assistance activity in Tanzania seeks to assist villages in completing the land use planning process.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTA, a four-year project launched in December 2015, is designed to reduce land tenure-related risks and lay the groundwork for sustainable agricultural investment for both small holders and commercial investors. It focuses on the Southern Agricultural Growth Corridor of Tanzania and specifically the districts of Iringa and Mbeya, centered in Iringa in years 1 and 2 and extending to Mbeya in years 3 and 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_land_tenure_work_in_tanzania&quot; title=&quot;Land Tenure Work in Tanzania&quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/dist/embed.js?1di&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTA has three main objectives: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assist villages in completing the land use planning process and delivering individual Certificates of Customary Rights of Occupancy (CCROs) through the use of MAST;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build the capacity of village and district land governance institutions to complete land use plans, issue CCROs to village land owners, manage land resources, respect women’s land rights, and build agriculture-related business skills; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raise awareness and uptake of the MAST technology within the Government of Tanzania, civil society, academia, and the private sector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTA’s initial design was informed by a 2015–2016 pilot that tested &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pWJTxJVRPQc&quot;&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt; as a field tool for capturing and mapping parcel boundaries and attribute information—the claimant’s name and details—on an image background. Using mobile devices (in this case Android-based), the pilot tested MAST’s ability to formalize land for subsequent registration and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/more-than-500-rural-tanzanians-now-have-land-titles&quot;&gt;delivery of titles&lt;/a&gt; in three villages in Iringa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following completion of the pilot in June 2016, LTA was given a broader mandate to develop rapid, low-cost, transparent, and replicable procedures for land use planning, first registration, and subsequent land transactions. Implicit in these ambitions is the need to streamline procedures and service delivery at village and district levels so as to achieve full public buy-in at the lowest possible cost. Opportunities to integrate cost recovery and potential revenues are to be explored throughout the course of the work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MAST will play a key role in clarifying and registering land rights at scale and completing village land use plans. We will extend the outputs of MAST (individual CCROs) to provide a sustainable solution that can capture, manage, and maintain land rights and support transactions at district and village levels. For the latter, DAI is developing the Technical Register under Social Tenure (TRUST), which is intended to link seamlessly with the (improved) MAST functionality to provide for ongoing maintenance, transactions, and long-term sustainability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Guiding Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are MAST and by extension TRUST fit for purpose? LTA has established the following core principles that our technology must support and to which it must adhere:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LTA will clarify land rights through community/local attestation of boundaries and claims, and subsequent registration;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The process will be public, participatory, and transparent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It will allow all land users to record a claim, then determine whether title can be granted;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The decision to accept or deny title will be based on evidence; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The adjudication and award of title will be justly administered, with equal access to all; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The systems used will comprise a model based on clear procedures that can be adapted, replicated, and scaled; and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These systems will be manageable and sustainable at district and village levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MAST pilot—reviewed in the &lt;em&gt;LTA Inception Report&lt;/em&gt; and a separate needs assessment—made it evident that if these guiding principles are to be followed, LTA would have to make significant improvements and customisations to MAST. To take just one example, the use of small hand-held devices in the field is problematic because the screen is effectively restricted to a single operator—with the added difficulty of reading in the glare of strong sunlight—which hinders people from gathering around and agreeing on what they’re seeing, in turn reducing participation and understanding on the part of villagers and adjudicators. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/pic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pic&quot; title=&quot;A mix of paper and mobile technology gives greater sense of ownership and improves adjudication.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, we can address this challenge by printing out and/or posting the material in question, but the initial design of MAST did not allow for the printing and display of maps and attribute lists for public consultation. Other obstacles included the stability of internet connections and power supply in rural Tanzania, a material hindrance to the use of cloud-based platforms which in turn affects the management of data and devices in the field. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain issues such as the low quality of input data—and hence low-quality outputs—which in turn necessitate time-intensive “data cleaning,” are not necessarily technology problems. They have to do with the training of field operators and adjudicators. But they are exacerbated if the technology and associated processes are not conducive to accurate, participatory inputs; do not readily enable screening of inputs or prevent duplication of entries; and do not readily accommodate sorting and editing. Based on the needs identified through the pilot, LTA is making the following changes to MAST: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enhancing the accuracy of the mapping software and improving the training of field operators; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrading the parcel numbering system and display to support mapping and work in the field;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refining attribute editing capabilities to prevent erroneous entries in the field and back office;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revising the attribute process to make individual claimants unique, thereby allowing for better management and analysis of patterns in land holdings (such as gender ratios, the number of multiple parcel holders, family links, and so on); &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tightening claimant attribute data entry criteria to enable claims to be checked more effectively prior to titling;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modifying claimant attributes so that attestation of claims, disputed claims, boundary issues, unclaimed land, and planning breaches can be properly recorded and addressed;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding editing and sorting functions to enable more effective data quality checks and claimant searches; and &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enabling more effective batch processing and printing—for public display, consultation, adjudication, monitoring and evaluation, and publication of basic statistics and reporting. Eventually, LTA will require production of maps, titles, and field issuance procedures on an industrial scale.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ID%20(1).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ID (1)&quot; title=&quot;The LTA program is going to great lengths to ensure that claimants are properly identified and their claims documented.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these changes in MAST, LTA is working to address factors such as capacity in the district and village registries, and the availability of secure and appropriate floor space. In the short to medium term, as the modifications to MAST are rolled out and tested anew, LTA will move forward the current, paper-based systems and procedures in a phased transition to a more automated approach. This gradual introduction of TRUST into village and district land administration, appropriate for the current levels of support infrastructure, will be critical to longer-term sustainability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trials of the new version of MAST will commence in May and June 2017; detailed work on the design and implementation of TRUST begins in July. Overall, we must concede that the review and redesign of the MAST software has slowed LTA’s progress in the field and indeed raised questions about the effectiveness and cost of using mobile devices at scale in rural Tanzania. But that iterative process has turned out to be essential, and still guides our efforts to ensure the project and related processes and procedures can function at scale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall procedural requirements for large-scale, participatory land use planning and registration at the village level are well known—proven models exist. It is incumbent on LTA to demonstrate that MAST can add significant value to field data capture and TRUST to sustainable registry maintenance systems. We are pushing hard for those outcomes and look forward to reporting on our progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generation Rising: Young, Educated Afghan Women Enter the Workforce</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/out-of-hiding-assisting-young-educated-women-in-afghanistan-to-finally-enter-the-workforce</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2017 17:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/out-of-hiding-assisting-young-educated-women-in-afghanistan-to-finally-enter-the-workforce</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is hard to believe in the wake of the past few decades that 1960s and ’70s Afghanistan was relatively progressive for women, with many women and girls freely attending school, working professionally, and dressing fashionably. Since the 1990s, warlords and, later, the conquering Taliban subjugated females—forbidding girls from going to school and women from working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That tide of exclusion has been receding, if slowly. Thanks in part to outside assistance, Afghanistan’s female population is re-asserting its self-esteem. Modernization is picking up in the country’s main urban centers, where young women increasingly seek to enter the workforce and make their mark. To protect and build on these gains, the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-women-in-the-economy&quot;&gt;Promote: Women in the Economy&lt;/a&gt; (WIE) activity, implemented by DAI, is teaming with hundreds of Afghan employers and the Afghan government to integrate aspiring professional women into the mainstream economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----Afgh-WIE-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----Afgh-WIE-2&quot; title=&quot;Participants of a Job Readiness Training session learn how to prepare a resume and cover letter.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When WIE launched in July 2015, Afghanistan had scant employment opportunities for professional women. The WIE team has since established operations throughout the country and placed nearly 4,000 female interns in 600 businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the world’s youngest countries—nearly two-thirds of the population is under age 25—Afghanistan sits poised on the verge of youth-fueled growth. Each year, more than 100,000 female secondary graduates sit for the national &lt;em&gt;Kankor&lt;/em&gt; exam, and about half enroll in Afghan universities. With no memories of the “good old days” for women, they are resolved to chart their own course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I first came to Afghanistan in the 1970s, women had their space in society,” said &lt;strong&gt;First Lady Rula Ghani&lt;/strong&gt; in the 2015 Al Jazeera documentary, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZkanAs-KGFg&quot;&gt;No Country for Women&lt;/a&gt;.” “[Women] were respected within the family, they were respected if ever they took up jobs outside the family, they were respected in public spaces. It was a very civil society. Somehow, I hope it will come back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afgh-WIE-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afgh-WIE-6&quot; title=&quot;A midwife intern works with a patient at Sari Pul Public Hospital in Northern Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Demand in Health Care, Education, and Beyond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WIE team knew that young women would not quickly be accepted into many Afghan workplaces. While strides have been made in Afghanistan—including 3 million girls &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/afghanistan/promote/&quot;&gt;enrolled&lt;/a&gt; in schools and 62,000 in public universities since 2001—many educated women still struggle to get hired. Most would be the first female in their family to work outside the home; for many employers, it would be their first female hire. Both sides were ill-equipped to change. While the handicraft/carpet sector is dominated by women, with plenty of organizations helping the illiterate crafters, WIE’s remit was to assist educated Afghan women into the professional mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan suffers from 40 percent unemployment as well as a shortage of qualified job seekers, so we dedicated part of our first year to analyzing regions and markets to identify which job sectors lacked qualified or certified recruits. WIE found that education and health care—teachers and nurses—headed the list to the point where even very conservative locales were open to employing women in these fields. Strong demand for qualified hires also emerged in media, banking and finance, retail, and information technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_afghanistan_wie_interns&quot; title=&quot;Afghanistan WIE interns&quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/dist/embed.js?M6f&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Foot in the Door&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WIE blanketed the country to establish entryways into the workforce by hiring provincial internship and apprenticeship coordinators in 30 of Afghanistan’s 34 provinces. These coordinators, many of whom work in remote locations, receive support from full complements of staff working out of five regional offices—in Kabul, Jalalabad, Kandahar, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif. The WIE team and activities go where other donor-funded projects do not operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In identifying the skills gaps as well as job growth and placement potential, WIE cultivated and vetted a roster of training institutes across the country, with which we developed curriculum and certification courses under WIE’s Forward Together brand. Upon acceptance into the internship and apprentice program, young women enroll in Job Readiness Training, a 20-hour workshop where we coach them in resume writing, job interviewing, business communication, personal financial management, work ethics, and combatting potential harassment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afgh-WIE-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afgh-WIE-3&quot; title=&quot;A candidate enrolling into the WIE Internship and Apprenticeship Program.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our knowledge management portal tracks each intern as she moves through training, interviews, and internships. Each intern is paid through a cost-share arrangement between WIE and the employer, receiving stipends monthly via a mobile money system. Of the nearly 4,000 young women placed so far, more than 400 have graduated to full-time employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forward Together scholarships help women who have at least a high school education gain specific technical skills. WIE vets all training facilities—there are many in Afghanistan—to ensure their services and certifications are acceptable and demanded in local markets. Where no local facility is available, WIE works with local and international grantees to provide training in sought-after skills. WIE currently provides a curriculum in information technology and health care, and our curriculum will grow, diversify, and develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Promoting Female-Friendly Workplaces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WIE understands safety and security concerns when a daughter, sister, or wife goes out to work for the first time. We vet potential host companies and require they provide separate bathrooms and prayer areas for women and exhibit cleanliness and professionalism. Offices must be located in safe areas, as interns are responsible for traveling to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the internship, the coordinators consult the intern and host company to ensure interns are learning valuable skills, interacting and learning from colleagues, and contributing to the business. Approximately 10 percent of WIE interns have gone on to full-time placement with their host company or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afgh-WIE-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afgh-WIE-5&quot; title=&quot;A female business owner is paired with a recent MBA graduate student in the MBA Corps activity.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Assisting Female-Friendly Businesses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding truly women-owned businesses in Afghanistan is not easy, although there are some, notably in Kabul. So WIE also assists businesses with workforces of at least 10 percent women to perform better and increase revenues and sustainability. Vetted local business service providers provide much of the assistance in areas such as marketing and accounting. WIE is preparing a mini-grant system that will allow many more companies to afford these business services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USAID’s innovative Master of Business (MBA) Corps program demonstrates the value of trained managers to small-business owners, some of whom cling to traditional practices. So far, WIE has matched MBA graduates with 21 client businesses in Kabul, with the MBA Corps soon to roll out regionally. Under a six-month agreement, WIE consults with the student and host business to ensure each is bringing value to the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many business owners in WIE&amp;rsquo;s target market—women, plus male owners with at least a 10-percent female workforce—  are unaware of the financing available to them. WIE assists client businesses in choosing and applying for small, appropriate loans. To date, WIE has facilitated 17 loans totaling AFS 4.9 million (US$74,000) for small businesses in the provinces of Kabul, Herat, Balkh, Nangarhar, and Kandahar. WIE and the Afghanistan Microfinance Association manage the Microfinance Institute Training Program that so far has placed 64 young women—future loan officers, cashiers, and bankers—within lending institutions in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-e-Sharif. WIE has also hosted more than 100 businesses at Access to Finance Matchmaking Roundtables that pair potential borrowers and lenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Profile of Businesses Served by WIE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typical annual revenue: US$10,000 to $50,000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building ownership: 77 percent do not own their building; 19 percent own outright; 4 percent are financing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Factors that businesses say limit growth: general economic outlook, 41 percent; security and political situation, 28 percent; limited demand in local market, 16 percent; high competition, 9 percent; other, 6 percent; access to finance, 2 percent&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potential entrepreneurs and startups face myriad challenges beyond providing a product or service, including finance, human resources, marketing, and supply chain issues. WIE’s two business incubation centers in Kabul are assisting 35 startups that are women-owned or employ 10 percent women, providing administrative assistance to help these young companies get off the ground and eventually learn to implement these activities for themselves. These incubators are key to turning job seekers into job creators, generating jobs and wealth, boosting productivity, creating competition, and bringing innovative products and services to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afgh-WIE-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afgh-WIE-4&quot; title=&quot;Afghan interns display their Job Readiness Training  Certificates. Each intern must complete her JRT before entering an internship as it prepares her to enter a professional work environment for the first time.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Advocating for Women in the Economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WIE Technical Working Group includes members from Afghanistan’s government, education, workforce development, and private sectors who support women’s involvement in the mainstream economy. Currently, the group is working to build awareness and support of the Women Legacy and Inheritance Rights Policy, a compilation of the economic rights guaranteed to women by Islam under Sharia law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These rights include access to property, land, cash, inheritance and &lt;em&gt;mehr&lt;/em&gt;, a mandatory payment promised by a groom or groom&amp;rsquo;s father that legally becomes the bride&amp;rsquo;s property. In collaboration with Ministry of Hajj and Religious Affairs, WIE is developing this policy and a national action plan to teach religious leaders, women&amp;rsquo;s rights advocates, civil society, and legal associates in rights to legacy and inheritance, making it easier for women to inherit property and gain access to finance. The group is also supporting administrative procedures to enforce legal practices and mandate marriage registration.
Finally, WIE is rolling out a nationwide gender awareness program, designed to highlight the importance of all Afghans&amp;#39; contributions to their society and economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afgh-WIE-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afgh-WIE-1&quot; title=&quot;This 22-year-old from Herat started her own IT tech company after completing the WIE internship program.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ancient Land, Modern Times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghan villages have always been deeply traditional, and even today many do not have internet connectivity or even electricity. They juxtapose against major cities Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif,  where information technology is blooming and a number of good universities serve the rising generation. In between are numerous small and midsize cities &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-municipalities-raise-more-revenues-deliver-better-services-enhance-stability/&quot;&gt;working to improve services&lt;/a&gt; for their residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WIE activity, part of USAID’s Promote initiative to empower Afghan women, has two years remaining. Our team is confident that in concert with our partners we can bolster women’s inclusion in Afghanistan’s economy and further ensure that the progress made by Afghan women over the past decade endures and advances for the benefit of all Afghans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$93 Million Grain Deal Between East African Countries Demonstrates How the Region Can Feed Itself</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/83-million-grain-deal-between-east-african-countries-demonstrates-how-east-africa-can-feed-itself</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 18:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/83-million-grain-deal-between-east-african-countries-demonstrates-how-east-africa-can-feed-itself</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If East Africa grows enough food to feed itself, which it generally does, why are so many of its people going hungry? This question lies at the nexus of two of Africa’s key development challenges—food security and trade—where a recent milestone event may signal a massive change in fortunes for one of the most food insecure regions of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2017, food traders from six East African countries converged on Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/a-trade-solution-to-the-food-security-challenge-surplus-grains-worth-83-dollars-million-now-available-to-countries-in-need&quot;&gt;signed $93 million in contracts&lt;/a&gt;. The resulting sale of 279,000 metric tons of food grains  represents enough to feed 1.3 million households for six months in the recipient countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving food from areas of surplus to areas of need is a key objective of the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; (the Hub). But moving food across Africa is not as simple as, say, driving a truckload of fruit from Florida to New York. To move food from country to country in Africa, traders need to navigate numerous differences between countries, among them: grain standards, currencies, border customs, and protectionist policies, not to mention corruption, inadequate roads and modes of transport, and storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DAI-News----EATIH-grains-pic-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DAI-News----EATIH-grains-pic-4&quot; title=&quot;Traders convene March 7, 2017, at the multilateral grain trade facilitation forum in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During food shortages, East African countries have historically been more likely to turn to the World Food Programme or other donors for handouts rather than to one of their neighbors for trade. However, as demonstrated at the East African Grain Council’s first multilateral grain trade facilitation forum, when food trade barriers come down, food will follow the money, African farmers and others will get paid, and the hungry will get fed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Reveling in Deal Making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In assisting the grain council to organize the multinational forum, in cooperation with the Addis Ababa Chamber of Commerce and Sectoral Associations, the Hub team hardly had to twist arms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Held at the Hilton Hotel in Addis Ababa, the grain forum featured 40 Ethiopian traders eager to sell surpluses of beans, soya, chick pea, sorghum, millet, rice, sesame, and, especially, their bumper crop of maize. Maize grows well in Ethiopia, but the majority of Ethiopians do not eat it, preferring pulses such as chickpeas and lentils, along with meat. However, in neighboring Kenya and elsewhere, maize-based foods such as ugali, pap, and nzima are staples. Ethiopian farmers need income from their maize, and other countries need maize for food—the market opportunity is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joining the Ethiopian sellers, 50 buyers arrived from Kenya, Tanzania, Uganda (normally a maize seller, but suffering a 100-year drought), and other countries. Once together, the sellers and buyers found themselves to be like long-lost cousins, sitting across tables from each other and eagerly talking the same language—the language of business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Those of us in the business—academics, agricultural economists, development practitioners—were not surprised that the forum was able to facilitate so many cross-border transactions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Private Sector-Led Solutions to Food Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too many years, countries in Eastern and Southern Africa have relied too heavily on food handouts. The region, of course, faces recurring climate challenges such as drought that sometimes forces millions of people to seek food donations instead of growing their own or buying locally. Even during these harsh times, however, crops elsewhere in the region and continent are often growing well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selling maize is important to farm families in Ethiopia, as it enables them to buy sugar, cooking oil, and other nutritious foods, and pay for expenses such as school supplies. But when they cannot export their surplus, these families are more at the mercy of farming’s boom-bust cycle; that is, if they grow too much, they suffer from price collapse, and if they grow too little, they have nothing to sell, keeping them poor, hungry, and disheartened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To facilitate these business-to-business transactions and move the bumper maize crop, the Hub team helped remove  cross-border trade barriers, in part by convincing the respective governments that regional trade can drive national economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade Hindrances Between Ethiopia and Kenya/East African Community (EAC) Countries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Historical:&lt;/strong&gt; EAC countries were British colonies under one colonial administration; Ethiopia was never colonized and had little or no relationship with its neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrastructure:&lt;/strong&gt; A paved highway connecting Nairobi to Moyale on the Kenya-Ethiopia border only opened in 2016, replacing the dirt road that had enabled only small-scale local trade. A new one-stop border post facilitates transit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No trade linkages:&lt;/strong&gt; Ethiopia&amp;rsquo;s surplus-producing region in the northwest (Western Oromia and Amhara regions) is far from Kenya&amp;rsquo;s primary grain market around Nairobi. Until now, there were few linkages between the markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formal and informal barriers:&lt;/strong&gt; These have included protectionist policies and, on the Kenya side, arbitrary and capricious unofficial duties and customs charges that complicate large-scale trade and pricing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic isolation:&lt;/strong&gt; Ethiopia is not a signatory of the Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa (COMESA) Customary Union nor a member of the EAC or World Trade Organization; Ethiopian exports to EAC countries are subject to 50 percent duty and other restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standards:&lt;/strong&gt; The EAC follows its own regional standards for 1) grain quality; 2) truck freight load; 3) grain packaging; 4) sanitary, phytosanitary, and other health and safety rules; and 5) contracting and payment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storage at Ethiopia-Kenya border:&lt;/strong&gt; The underdeveloped border area lacks good storage, including bonded warehouses, to store grain for trading or trans-shipment.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Breaking Down Barriers to Food Trade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenya and Ethiopia might be neighbors, but the countries had never traded on a large scale, partly because Ethiopia is not a member of the East African Community, a six-nation economic and trade alliance. However, the trade relationship between these two East African economic leaders might be changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kenya recently completed a highway—the A2—and the country’s logistics companies are now getting used to sending their trucks north from Nairobi to the border post at Moyale to pick up Ethiopian goods. At the grain forum, the new land route made it easier for the Hub team to facilitate agreements on issues such as delivery terms and payment mechanisms. We also encouraged obsolete policies to be temporarily lifted. For example, Ethiopia, normally a significant maize producer, currently has an export ban on maize that was enacted &lt;em&gt;four years ago&lt;/em&gt; after a major drought. Shortly after the forum, traders were issued permits which allowed the deals to go forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EATIH-grain-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EATIH-grain-2&quot; title=&quot;Newly opened highway A2 that connects Nairobi with Moyale at the Kenya-Ethiopia border. Photo by David Stanley.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Eliminating Long-Term Calls for Food Assistance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founded in 2006, the East African Grain Council includes 10 member countries. The Hub team is assisting the council to find its stride as a food security champion. Across its 10 nations, there is plenty of room for consistent grain growth and harvests across the calendar. As the Hub strives to be catalytic by facilitating events such as the March 2017 grain forum, we are also building a sustainable systemic process so traders can carry on grain trade activities through the council without our intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grain forum was the type of trading event that the region needs to reduce dependency on food assistance. The Hub is facilitating its next big trading event, a rice trading forum near the common border of Rwanda, Uganda, and Tanzania. Small traders have bought into a structured process, with contract templates and payment methods agreed in advance. All that the buyers and sellers need to do is negotiate prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By promoting intraregional trade, we put the private sector in the driver’s seat to address food shortages and hunger in East Africa. Ultimately, open borders in East and Southern Africa should give rise to more stable markets that in turn attract investment that bolsters food security and economic growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other USAID-funded projects implemented by DAI are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/africa-africa-lead-ii&quot;&gt;building capacity&lt;/a&gt; and assisting African countries to adopt agricultural technologies, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-feed-future-southern-africa-seed-trade-project&quot;&gt;improved seed varieties&lt;/a&gt;, fertilizers, and agro-chemicals, as farmers are generally reluctant to invest in technologies unless their risk is reduced. In addition, DAI is managing a project funded by the U.K. Department for International Development that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-and-southern-africa-foodtrade-esa&quot;&gt;awards strategic grants&lt;/a&gt; to promising agribusiness partners in the region. Facilitating intraregional trade and reducing market uncertainty will further encourage technology adoption, increase productivity, and, ultimately, promote self-reliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USAID East Africa Trade and Investment Hub Select Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brokered partnership with American Apparel and Footwear Association, which represents more than 1,000 brands generating $361 billion in annual U.S. retail sales, to address constraints to competitiveness and expansion of the industry in East Africa while creating jobs in East Africa and the United States.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through March 2017, supported $224 million in exports through the African Growth and Opportunity Act (AGOA).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitated $51 million of new private sector investment and more than 1,400 buyer-seller export linkages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created more than 33,000 full- and part-time jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supported more than 600 food producers and food security organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assisted in drafting four policy and regulatory reforms.
Provided export capacity building assistance to more than 1,200 firms.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Land Tenure Regularisation to a Sustainable Land Register</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/from-land-tenure-regularisation-to-a-sustainable-land-register</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 16:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/from-land-tenure-regularisation-to-a-sustainable-land-register</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The evidence is clear: property rights are essential foundations for poverty alleviation and economic development. In Africa, it is less clear as to what may be the most effective way of establishing and especially maintaining those rights, with formal and customary tenure systems both offering degrees of security but radically different development possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several African countries are undertaking large-scale, systematic land tenure regularisation (LTR) programmes—programmes to formalise and protect land rights—in rapidly developing economic and social contexts. Such programmes have been based on various definitions of rights including a long-term emphyteutic lease (in Rwanda); a lifetime “holding” right (Ethiopia); certificates granting rights of occupancy or customary rights of occupancy (Tanzania); or customary land rights (Namibia). All of these countries are currently grappling with the problem of how to sustainably maintain those rights once assigned. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://pdf.usaid.gov/pdf_docs/PNABB825.pdf&quot;&gt;case of Kenya&lt;/a&gt; is an example where following the first registration programme, subsequent inheritance and sales were not registered because Kenyans did not understand the land registration system, lacked ready access to it, and faced inordinate costs in terms of time and money to use it. Informal transactions ended up causing more disputes than previously, in part because the traditional methods of dispute resolution were no longer usable since the land was now privately owned. Hence, the expected economic impacts—more land sales, greater access to credit, and consolidated holdings leading to more productive farmers—failed to materialise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, registration by itself is not enough. Establishing the register is an important first step, but maintaining that register requires that people understand the need for recording changes in land occupancy, are motivated to participate in the system, and have an effective facility for doing so. In Africa, it has proved very difficult to build and maintain the technical infrastructure to support ongoing land and property transactions, in contrast to Eastern Europe where demand and awareness is high and the infrastructure has been developed in a relatively short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, we believe, is a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fig.net/resources/publications/figpub/pub60/Figpub60.pdf&quot;&gt;fit for purpose&lt;/a&gt;” paradigm in the spirit of that laid out by Stig Enemark, Keith Bell, Christiaan Lemmen, and Robin McLaren. In this paper, we put forward such a model for a local, low-cost land register—the Technical Register under Social Tenure, or TRUST—that can be customised, deployed, and operated in a sustainable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Regularising Formal or Customary Land Rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Land matters in Africa have received a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oicrf.org/document.asp?ID=15378&quot;&gt;great deal of attention&lt;/a&gt; in the past 10 years. Population growth, demographic movements, and large-scale agricultural investment (especially since 2008) have placed land resources under pressure. Increasingly, land administration agencies are being pressed by the public, by investors, and by politicians, yet they have limited capacity, infrastructure, and financial resources to provide the secure land administration and management services these stakeholders demand. Recent initiatives—such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/docrep/016/i2801e/i2801e.pdf&quot;&gt;Voluntary Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; on the Responsible Governance of Tenure of Land, Fisheries and Forests in the Context of National Food Security; the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/3/a-au866e.pdf&quot;&gt;Principles for Responsible Investment&lt;/a&gt; in Agriculture and Food Systems; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uneca.org/sites/default/files/PublicationFiles/fg_on_land_policy_eng.pdf&quot;&gt;African Union&lt;/a&gt; land policy—have highlighted the importance of land governance and spelled out the proper goals of land policy. But they do not set out practical measures that can be implemented at a reasonable cost and on a reasonable time scale. That said, positive developments are emerging:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-cost mass registration at a national scale is now a reality.&lt;/strong&gt; The fit-for-purpose paradigm offers policy makers practical advice on reform based on simple solutions such as adopting general boundaries, using aerial images to identify boundaries, and agreeing acceptable accuracies for survey work. DAI pioneered such an approach &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/delivering-large-scale-land-certification-programmes-lessons-from-rwanda/&quot;&gt;in Rwanda&lt;/a&gt; where more than 10 million parcels were registered in five years at an average cost of less than US$7. This methodology is now being applied &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ethiopia-land-registration-ready-for-lift-off-now-what/&quot;&gt;in Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt; on an even larger scale. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The continuum of land rights model bridges formal and informal land rights.&lt;/strong&gt; Historically, we have distinguished strongly between customary and formal tenure systems. But the continuum of land rights model endorsed by UN Habitat (below) asserts that land rights can have a continuous spectrum, and it is possible to “register” or record any of these rights. In European land administration systems, we consider the formal registration as a kind of juridical cadastre, wherein rights, parcel extent, and position are legally established. Traditionally, we consider the recording of informal rights as something informal, and we regard the formal registration as superior. Hence we usually try to regularise informal land rights and convert them to some kind of formal right that can be formally registered (for example, in a lease). We could, though, look at this another way: why not record the informal right, especially if this right has strong social standing and is accepted as legitimate? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Graphic%20land.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Graphic land&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can register both formal and informal rights, and they can have legal and/or social legitimacy.&lt;/strong&gt; We can extend the continuum of land rights model by also considering the formal registration or informal recording of these rights. We simply record the informal or customary right, without converting it to a formal land right first. Increasing evidence suggests that customary land tenure systems and informal markets are able to support access to land and meet local land occupiers’ needs; indeed, this is a central tenet of Urban LandMark’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.africanminds.co.za/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/9781920489991_content1.pdf&quot;&gt;incremental tenure improvement approach&lt;/a&gt;, where local recording of land rights is regarded as a potential first step toward eventual formal recognition, while providing some level of recognition and evidence of occupation. This thinking suggests that we can often deliver legitimate land rights simply by recording the customary or informal rights—in line with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fig.net/resources/publications/figpub/pub52/figpub52.pdf&quot;&gt;Social Tenure Domain Model&lt;/a&gt;—and without converting all rights to formal rights as part of the registration process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LAND%20Diagram%202%20Land%20Rights%20-%20f2v1%5B3%5D.png&quot; alt=&quot;LAND Diagram 2 Land Rights - f2v1[3]&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/471197/land-tenure.pdf&quot;&gt;literature review&lt;/a&gt; by Geoffrey Payne and colleagues shows that a number of approaches and interventions have been successful in fostering legitimate tenure systems and achieving positive development outcomes. These approaches include freehold ownership through land titling; leasehold; land registration and land use certification; community land trusts; common or communal ownership; and private land rental. While we tend to place most emphasis on formal titling, Payne’s findings suggest that other tenure forms may also be effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Needed: Innovative Solutions to the Registry Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 21st century, land administration systems will nearly always be developed using digital systems. Assuming they are well designed, then they are more secure, more efficient, more transparent, and more accessible. However, land administration initiatives worldwide are littered with failed large information technology (IT) projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rumyana Tonchovska and Gavin Adlington have reviewed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.landandpoverty.com/agenda/pdfs/paper/tonhovska_full_paper.pdf&quot;&gt;various approaches&lt;/a&gt; used in modernising the land registration systems of Europe and Central Asia, where the World Bank committed more than $1 billion between 1990 and 2012. Rather than “big bang” IT projects, the most effective approach turned out to be incremental, step-by-step developments accompanied by strong local involvement. In most countries, land administration services are typically the responsibility of government and resourced by the relevant government ministry. To establish the required information management system, a responsible body—often a ministry—conceives and implements a large IT project to integrate all land-related geo-information and associated data, with the intention of cascading that information down to local agencies. The problem is that these projects tend to be of immense size, duration, and complexity, and they are often trying to meet the needs of quite separate business units. The projects can become bogged down in procurement, design, or implementation, and the funding requirements for roll-out, support, and operation can be unsupportable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Africa is no exception. In Africa, there are at present no automated land administration systems operating at a national scale and able to provide services at local, regional, and central levels. By contrast, many of the countries in the Europe and Central Asia region are now rated in the top 20 or so countries for ease of transfer of property rights, according to the World Bank’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doingbusiness.org/rankings&quot;&gt;Doing Business&lt;/a&gt; index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to this phenomenon, Robin McLaren in 2011 proposed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.clge.eu/documents/events/105/16310_RICS_Crowdsourcing_Report%20final%20WEB.pdf&quot;&gt;radical new approach&lt;/a&gt; to registering and then managing land rights,  whereby citizens or citizen groups can be engaged in a new, collaborative model, directly declaring their rights through an open data initiative using mobile devices. This proposal, in turn, led to the establishment of the MapMyRights and Cadasta initiatives. The latter is currently building a cloud-based platform to host field data collected in this manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, open source software—especially geospatial applications—is dramatically changing the price/performance relationship, and offers the prospect of geospatial solutions cascading to local districts without significant software licensing costs at that level. Open source solutions such as the Food and Agriculture Organization’s Solutions for Open Land Administration and Open Tenure (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.flossola.org/&quot;&gt;SOLA Open Tenure&lt;/a&gt;) have been trialed in Cambodia, Nigeria, and Uganda. Today, we see various registry solutions being tested: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traditional integrator/vendor solutions (such as the Integrated Land Management Information System now under construction in Tanzania)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open source generic solutions (such as SOLA Open Tenure)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Global technology platforms, with crowdsourcing or intermediaries (such as Cadasta)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While each approach has its advantages and disadvantages, we should recognise that the requirements for an urban land administration system—able to meet the needs of Dar es Salaam, say, or Addis Ababa—are quite distinct from what is needed by a village or district in rural Tanzania, or northern Namibia. Given the relatively robust property market in the larger urban centres, especially with regard to the value and volume of transactions, it is likely that cities enjoy enough demand to stimulate and sustain a functioning land administration unit suitable for their needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of the urban centres, the demands are quite different. In Tanzania, for example, the system is heavily decentralised and the administration is at the local district and village level for all village lands (70 percent of the country, encompassing an estimated 13,000 villages). Yet there is little chance of providing automated land registry services at that level. In Tanzania, accordingly, DAI is developing further the Mobile Application to Support Tenure (MAST) tool, which allows the recording of geospatial and other information using mobile technology. We are using MAST on the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/tanzania-feed-future-tanzania-land-tenure-assistance-lta&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Tanzania Land Tenure Assistance&lt;/a&gt; project to register land rights in 41 villages in the Iringa and Mbeya districts. Notably, though, this application allows the initial registration of land rights but does not support their ongoing management or updating. That is where TRUST comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;TRUST—Toward a Sustainable System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the fit-for-purpose principle, DAI’s Technical Register under Social Tenure system—TRUST—seeks to provide a local land registry based on open source software linked to a mobile device. Unlike Cadasta, the records will be managed locally, ensuring the communities themselves have ownership of and responsibility for the land administration system. The TRUST system is replicated to a remote host at least once every 24 hours. Where a national system exists, TRUST will feed data to it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI will deploy TRUST initially in Tanzania, where it will be linked to the MAST application, as illustrated below. TRUST will have a simple data model based on the Land Administration Domain Model (ISO 19152), and will accept data from MAST or other entry devices. The communities themselves (with DAI facilitators) will be responsible for data entry, and it will operate in accordance with the requirements of Tanzania’s Village Land Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LAND%20Diagram%203.png&quot; alt=&quot;LAND Diagram 3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the TRUST approach has several key advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communities can readily use it (and MAST) themselves, enabling them to carry out basic land administration services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The technology is low-cost, easy to use, and replicable—and, when deployed, should significantly reduce unit costs for increased volumes of transactions over the longer term compared to conventional registry solutions. It runs as an app, and to the user appears just like any other app.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is backed up daily. Importantly, any registration carried out using MAST—no matter how small or local—is immediately compatible with TRUST, enabling ongoing data management wherever data is being registered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Looking to the Long Term&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any sustainable solution for land administration must manage local needs as well as offer opportunities for economic development, including sound external investment in the community, where local people engage with outside investors to their mutual benefit. While there are now many resources to guide private investment around land, little has been written about how to put in place low-cost, sustainable solutions that support such transactions. In our trial of MAST/TRUST, we will focus on meeting that need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Longer-term sustainability entails both an effective mechanism for delivering land administration services and ongoing demand for them. TRUST can certainly provide the services, but will citizens demand them? Financing is also critical. In the European and Central Asian regions, many land administration agencies are now achieving significant cost recovery and in some cases even generating a surplus. This success is driven by land market activity. The figure below shows the land market model of development in Eastern Europe, where initial reforms and investment in land administration agencies established the infrastructure and capacity necessary for market activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LAND%20Diagram%204%20Land%20Beyond%20LTR%20v3.png&quot; alt=&quot;LAND Diagram 4 Land Beyond LTR v3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fig.net/resources/proceedings/2000/prague-final-papers/baldwin-dale.htm&quot;&gt;Lessons Learnt from the Emerging Land Markets in Central and Eastern Europe&lt;/a&gt;, Peter Dale and Richard Baldwin)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Eastern Europe, the European Union, the World Bank, and other donors led an intensive institution-building programme complemented by property privatisation, restitution, compensation, the creation of land registries and cadastral systems, and massive data creation programmes. As it became possible to transact, and financial instruments such as mortgages became available, the market took off and activity increased dramatically as demand grew. The result: within 15 years, most East European countries had built land administration systems supporting more mature, stable markets, with transaction levels similar to those of Western Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this model, the increase in capital availability and liquidity, access to credit, and the perceived security of tenure drove the market. However, this pattern is unlikely to be repeated in many African countries, so the demand will have to come from elsewhere. Just as we have seen a revolution in how LTR is carried out, so we need a revolution in how the registries can be established, operated, and financed. In Eastern Europe and Central Asia, demand rose as the economies aligned with Western European norms, and there was enough capital and liquidity generated by the economic transition to drive the property market (after initial reforms). In Africa, the demand needed to sustain land registration and administration services is more likely to come from investment-related activities (local and external), as well as normal community needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work toward a sustainable model of land tenure regularisation is underpinned by four observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The goal of a land administration programme should be not just a first registration of rights, but a system that supports transactions and maintenance of the registry so that legal and physical persons can effect transfer or disposal in a secure and transparent manner. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low-cost local registries built on the TRUST model can complement registration programmes and ensure that the investment in registration is protected and its benefits realised in rural areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greater community participation and leadership in the registration process—suitably supported by tools and facilitators—is the wave of the future and should be embraced accordingly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demand is a pre-requisite for sustainable land administration services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Africa, we see increasing pressure and demand from large-scale land investments. But this demand must be channelled in a way that delivers the benefits of investment yet protects the underlying interests of local individuals and their communities. Experience elsewhere (notably in Eastern Europe) shows that once we have achieved a critical mass of registration and deployed an effective registry maintenance system, then a land market emerges that stimulates investment and allows people to mobilise land and property assets in support of economic activity such as sales, leasing, real estate development, land improvement, and agricultural investment. It is from this land mobility that development benefits flow. 
First registration of rights, in and of itself, cannot support this mobility. But the TRUST application, premised on community participation and the availability of cheap and pervasive mobile technologies, promises to turn first registration into an ongoing register. We look forward to exploring its potential in Tanzania and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dialogue and Development in Ghana’s Oil and Gas Region</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/dialogue-and-development-in-ghanas-oil-and-gas-region</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 14:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/dialogue-and-development-in-ghanas-oil-and-gas-region</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2007, oil and gas was discovered off the coast of Ghana, leading to a boom in infrastructure projects and investment in the country’s Western Region, particularly in six coastal districts. Subsequently, large tracts of land have been taken over for the development of oil and gas infrastructure, businesses, pipelines, roads, and areas allocated for machinery repair. While this surge in activity has raised expectations for economic benefits among local communities, it has also spurred questions about resettlement and compensation, alternative livelihood and job opportunities, changes to land use, and food security. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under such circumstances, it is critical that communities have a platform where they can voice their concerns, ask questions, and access accurate information about oil and gas investments and their implications for local people. Since 2014, such a forum has been available to them, thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ghana-western-region-coastal-foundation-wcrf&quot;&gt;Ghana Western Region Coastal Foundation (WRCF)&lt;/a&gt;, a U.K. Department for International Development-funded programme focused on ensuring that oil companies’ corporate social responsibility efforts are effectively promoting development, preventing conflict, and stimulating inclusive economic growth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href=&quot;http://wrcfghana.org/&quot;&gt;WRCF&lt;/a&gt; funds a number of activities, its multi-stakeholder dialogue forum has proven to be one of the most successful. Local authorities, investors, and the oil industry participate to share their plans and expectations with communities, to promote accountability and transparency, and to foster the kind of positive relationships with constituents that favour smooth business operations. In 2016, after two years of conversations to bring together the various stakeholders in the Western Region, a Community Perception and Socio-Economic Survey found that decision making in WRCF’s target communities is indeed perceived as more inclusive now than in non-target communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/211697297&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Did the WRCF Forum Come to Be a Trusted Convener?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forum came into being after an initial assessment found that communities were not sufficiently organised to effectively present their concerns to government authorities and industry. By the same token, while government and industry had been involved in some consultations, these were not always well managed and their quality varied. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key component of the dialogue platform is the Citizens Advisory Council, composed of representatives of oil and gas companies (Tullow Ghana Ltd. and Ghana National Gas Company Ltd.), communities (represented by nine senior chiefs and queen mothers), government (leadership of district assemblies, the Fisheries Commission, and the Environmental Protection Agency), and civil society (nongovernmental agencies and the media). This body summons actors who appear at a public session of the Council to respond to issues raised by communities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But WRCF set out to make the multi-stakeholder dialogue process as extensive and inclusive as possible. To date, it has worked with 301 communities and recorded 1,263 issues raised by them, engaging more than 75,000 people in the process. The engagement begins at the very grassroots with household-level conversations conducted by volunteers, who collect these individual concerns for discussion at community meetings to identify common issues and prioritise the most pressing. Importantly, all the issues raised at the meetings are recorded, aggregated, and analysed, affording government and industry data-driven insights into the challenges facing residents of Ghana’s oil districts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Training in Consultation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a comfortable environment for people to air their opinions, the volunteers who solicit information and the facilitators who lead discussions are recruited from the communities themselves. Residents are more at ease and confident with familiar faces and people who understand the context first-hand. Training local Ghanaians to drive the consultation process also strengthens local capacity and improves the chances that the forum will be sustainable after the programme comes to a close. Overall, WRCF has trained 1,550 volunteers and 24 facilitators across the six districts (Shama, Sekondi Takoradi, Ahanta West, Nzema East, Ellembelle, and Jomoro). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/WB_Bernice_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WB_Bernice_1&quot; title=&quot;&amp;quot;One way to alleviate fears is to create a space to talk, a platform to bring different actors together to air their views.&amp;quot; – Bernice Sam, presenting at the World Bank Land and Poverty Conference, March 2017&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This training in turn allows active citizens to take on broader leadership roles. Communities now have people they can trust to facilitate community meetings, build consensus, and engage with the government and private sector around community needs. In Assuoko Essaman, for example, a facilitator appealed to a bank to help furnish a community health facility that had been defunct for two years. The bank provided GH¢5,000 for this purpose. 
Some graduates of the training programme have since been elected to serve in the local assemblies, and communities are collectively embarking on their own initiatives to address local challenges. In Beahu, for example, community members levied each other to rent a house for a health facility; in Asemko, they contributed to the construction of a permanent community meeting place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industry and government have been receptive to this new level of activism and communication. Local assemblies have included the concerns of communities in their district plans—to repair bridges and roads, for example—and companies are responding, too: the Ghana National Petroleum Commission expanded its scholarship scheme from four districts to six in response to concerns initially raised in the WRCF fora.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a key function of the forum is to ease apprehension so that problems can be aired in a comfortable environment, it has also emerged as a venue to share positive stories whose retelling benefits communities and investors alike. For example, people who have been compensated for the loss of their land have shared with neighbours the practical steps they took to receive compensation and explained what worked well and what didn’t—a learning process helpful to both community members and investors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Land Issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While WRCF was not designed with a specific “land focus” in mind, it has inevitably encountered issues relating to land ownership, land value, and land use. Oil-driven growth has spurred a population spike in anticipation of jobs and other economic opportunities and a rapid increase in cost of living. Land traditionally used for agriculture—both commercial and subsistence—is now being repurposed, with implications for local livelihoods, food security, and environmental degradation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Ghana%20DevAlts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ghana DevAlts&quot; title=&quot;In 2007, oil and gas was discovered off the coast of Ghana, leading to a boom in infrastructure projects and investment in the country’s Western Region, particularly in six coastal districts.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The land obtained by investors is in most cases inhabited and these incumbent communities need to be treated fairly and respectfully. Issues of resettlement and compensation are sensitive and can lead to disputes and conflict within communities or between locals and investors, particularly if rights to land are unclear. Land rights issues are especially pertinent to women and other marginalised groups, who may lack secure land rights (be they ownership, use, or control) or may be unfairly excluded from compensation received. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loss of traditional lands also has cultural and social significance for communities. And even if communities moved from their land are fairly compensated, there can be further issues relating to alternative livelihoods and skills development. In many instances, people previously engaged in rural livelihoods have relocated to urban areas, forcing a change in livelihood practices. While urban migration may not be a problem or unwelcome in itself, there may be problems if people lack sufficient skills or funds to pursue alternative livelihoods. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the 1,263 issues logged by WRCF in the community conversations, 49 were specifically related to land. With regard to compensation concerns, the Ellembele District—home to the Ghana Gas plant and its network of pipelines, new highways and access routes to the plant, and various mining or quarry operations—is the most affected. Some 14 percent of issues raised in Ellembelle relate directly to the livelihood concerns of community members who have seen their farmlands made over to oil, gas, and mining industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Land Valuation Division and Ghana National Gas Company have appeared before the Advisory Council to explain delays in compensation for lands compulsorily acquired by government for the gas plant, assuring residents of prompt payments once lands are unencumbered and real owners determined by a court of law. All responses from government and industry are fed back to the communities, which has built a foundation of trust between communities and the WRCF. Although the programme may not be able to solve every land and compensation dispute in all its intricacies, it has at least connected communities to those responsible for addressing their issues, and it has provided companies with data to inform their interventions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The oil and gas industry certainly appreciates the intermediary role that WRCF plays in relaying information from industry to communities and vice versa. Looking to the future, oil and gas companies may wish to take advantage of the data WRCF has collected by means of the multi-stakeholder forum and its grassroots community engagement. This data cuts across communities and districts in the Western Region, and it holds the promise that a systemic, collaborative approach focused on crosscutting issues—as opposed to each company limiting its interest to communities affected by its own operations—may yield wider development benefits across the coastal districts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Whole Spectrum: A Holistic Approach to Climate Resilience</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/the-whole-spectrum-a-holistic-approach-to-climate-resilience</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/the-whole-spectrum-a-holistic-approach-to-climate-resilience</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Climate change is a growing threat to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.defense.gov/News/Article/Article/612710/&quot;&gt;global stability and national security&lt;/a&gt;. Decades of fossil fuel combustion and unsustainable land use have contributed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.nasa.gov/climate_resources/24/&quot;&gt;carbon dioxide levels&lt;/a&gt; in the planet’s atmosphere that are higher than in the past 4 million years. With so much carbon dioxide trapping heat in the atmosphere, the planet is getting warmer. Last year—2016—was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/2016-was-the-hottest-year-on-record/&quot;&gt;hottest year&lt;/a&gt; on record and seas around the world have already risen an average of nearly 3 inches. We are already experiencing increased impacts from extreme events, such as floods and drought: while it is difficult to attribute any one event to the broader phenomenon of climate change, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/haiyan/fy14/fs22&quot;&gt;Typhoon Yolanda&lt;/a&gt; in the Philippines caused 6,100 deaths, displaced 4 million people, and damaged 1.1 million houses in 2013, with an estimated financial cost exceeding US$7 billion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change also &lt;a href=&quot;http://archive.defense.gov/pubs/150724-congressional-report-on-national-implications-of-climate-change.pdf?source=govdelivery&quot;&gt;magnifies existing risks&lt;/a&gt; to health and livelihoods, particularly in developing countries, which can drive refugee flows and conflict over basic resources, such as food and water. Poor people are more susceptible to climate-related diseases such as malaria and diarrhea. Higher food prices caused by climate-driven declines in agricultural productivity also threaten food security in poorer regions such as Sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia. Absent climate-informed development policies, climate change could &lt;a href=&quot;https://openknowledge.worldbank.org/handle/10986/22787&quot;&gt;force more than 100 million&lt;/a&gt; people into extreme poverty by 2030. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Addressing the global climate challenge requires a multifaceted and holistic approach, and DAI has been at the forefront of helping clients around the world reduce greenhouse gas emissions and adapt to the impacts of climate change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/214065469&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach works across the entire spectrum of climate change mitigation and adaptation, supporting countries in Asia, Africa, Europe, and the Americas to develop and implement international and national policies that catalyze individual action, such as increasing microfinance for climate-smart farming in Kenya or improving water use efficiency in Thailand. We translate and communicate scientific evidence and atmospheric modelling to inform action-oriented development programming, and bridge hard climate science with local knowledge. We also help governments and the private sector meet their commitments to reduce their carbon footprint and green their supply chains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In partnership with clients such as U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID), and the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development (EBRD), DAI has translated policy into action through real-world solutions. Our experience has shown the following approaches to be critical:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Bridge science and local knowledge to help communities adapt to the impacts of climate change.&lt;/strong&gt; Climate change is already causing shifts in agricultural planting seasons, fish migrations, and the timing and availability of critical water resources for drinking and irrigation. DAI is downscaling sophisticated climate modeling to help communities better plan for the future while integrating their local knowledge into the development and implementation of adaptation strategies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the USAID-supported &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southeast-asia-mekong-adaptation-and-resilience-climate-change-arcc&quot;&gt;Mekong Adaptation and Resilience to Climate Change&lt;/a&gt; project, for example, DAI facilitated community vulnerability assessments and the implementation of adaptation activities—such as water harvesting and the use of climate-smart rice varieties—that benefit 30,000 people in Cambodia, Laos, Thailand, and Vietnam. On the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/south-pacific-islands-coastal-community-adaptation-project-c-cap&quot;&gt;Coastal Community Adaptation Project&lt;/a&gt;, DAI supported local communities in 12 South Pacific Island nations to conduct climate change risk and asset mapping and then build climate-resilient infrastructure projects that benefit more than 20,000 islanders. DAI has also built adaptive capacity in environments as diverse as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/indonesia-apik-adaptasi-perubahan-iklim-dan-ketangguhan-or-climate-change-adaption&quot;&gt;Indonesia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-strengthening-adaptation-and-resilience-climate-change-kenya-plus-starck&quot;&gt;Kenya&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/Nepal-Program-for-Aquatic-Natural-Resources-Improvement-PANI&quot;&gt;Nepal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Expand climate-smart agriculture and catalyze finance for business models that reduce pressures on forests and land-based emissions.&lt;/strong&gt; Agricultural production and land use conversion account for 24 percent of the world’s greenhouse gas emissions, which makes it critical to reduce slash-and-burn farming and lower the greenhouse gas emissions associated with the production of key global commodities such as palm oil, livestock, wood products, and rice. Changing practices requires establishing appropriate incentives along the entire value chain; DAI applies economic drivers to encourage better environmental stewardship that reduces pressure on forests and lowers greenhouse gas emissions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to USAID’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/honduras-ProParque-GEMA&quot;&gt;ProParque&lt;/a&gt; project in Honduras, for example, eco-friendly fireplaces that run completely on sugar cane pulp rather than firewood have reduced production time by half—delivering both an economic and environmental benefit to local producers. On DFID’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-strengthening-adaptation-and-resilience-climate-change-kenya-plus-starck&quot;&gt;Strengthening Adaptation and Resilience to Climate Change in Kenya Plus&lt;/a&gt; project, DAI worked with microfinance institutions to increase investment in climate-smart dairy, cassava, maize, and sorghum value chains, which increases farmers’ resilience to drought and reduces greenhouse gas emissions. Again, we have employed our approach—incentivizing sustainable agriculture and reducing deforestation—with positive results in various contexts, from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/indonesia-orangutan-conservation-services-program-ocsp&quot;&gt;Indonesia&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/russian-federation-clima-east-support-climate-change-mitigation-and-adaptation&quot;&gt;former Soviet Union&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/philippines-environmental-governance-phase-ii-ecogov2&quot;&gt;Philippines&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/bangladesh-agricultural-value-chains-avc-program&quot;&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-innovation-agribusiness-inovagro&quot;&gt;Mozambique&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/liberia-support-unit-liberia-flegt-voluntary-partnership-agreement-vpa&quot;&gt;Liberia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Drive investment in clean and renewable energy and energy-efficient technology to accelerate the transition to a green economy.&lt;/strong&gt; Modern energy services are crucial to human well-being and to a country’s economic development, yet 1.2 billion people are without access to electricity and 2.7 billion rely on the traditional use of biomass for cooking, which is associated with approximately 3.5 million deaths annually from indoor air pollution. In more developed countries, outdated and inefficient systems that burn fossil fuels contribute to high levels of greenhouse gas emissions. DAI’s approach is to drive investment in clean and renewable energy and energy-efficient technology by removing barriers to investment and collaborating with governments and the private sector to create the enabling conditions for clean energy to flourish. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On EBRD-funded sustainable energy financing programs in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/poland-polish-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-polseff&quot;&gt;Poland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/morocco-sustainable-energy-financing-facility-morseff&quot;&gt;Morocco&lt;/a&gt;, DAI provided technical assistance to credit facilities focused on financing energy efficiency and small-scale renewable energy investments worth €270 million. The Polish program achieved energy savings of 166.4 GWh/year and avoided carbon dioxide emissions of more than 100,000 tons/year. DAI has catalyzed finance for clean energy and energy efficiency in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/honduras-ProParque-GEMA&quot;&gt;Honduras&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-financial-inclusion-rural-microenterprises-firm&quot;&gt;Kenya&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/somalia-partnership-economic-growth&quot;&gt;Somalia&lt;/a&gt;, and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Move communities beyond subsistence and create safety nets that build household resilience to shocks and extreme events.&lt;/strong&gt; Insurance company Swiss RE estimates that total economic losses from natural catastrophes and man-made disasters in 2016 was $158 billion, with approximately 10,000 people losing their lives. Climate change increases the risk of weather-related extreme events—such as droughts, cyclones, and floods—which disproportionately harm the most vulnerable communities, such as those in Africa’s Sahel region. DAI takes a holistic approach to increasing resilience by helping communities move beyond subsistence and reinforcing the base of economic, social, and environmental resources required for communities to recover from disasters and help them break out of the cycle of poverty. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In northeast Kenya, for instance, we are managing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-hunger-safety-net-programme-phase-2-hsnp2&quot;&gt;cash transfer program&lt;/a&gt; that scales up financial assistance from a base of 100,000 households to up to 375,000 households when the first signs of drought occur. Building household resilience to climate change is a feature of our work in Honduras and elsewhere in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/usaid-central-america-regional-climate-change-program-rccp-programa-regional-de&quot;&gt;Central America&lt;/a&gt;, for example, as well as on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-expert-advisory-call-down-services-eacds-lot-b-strengthening-resilience-and-response-to-crises&quot;&gt;global basis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Enable local-to-global access to climate and weather data that informs decision making and thereby reduces risk.&lt;/strong&gt; Climate change science backed by data from satellites and other sources continues to enhance our understanding of changes in precipitation, temperature, droughts, and other environmental phenomena. With this increase in data comes an equally crucial need for timely and reliable transfer of knowledge on climate and weather to inform decision making around issues such as flood evacuations, hydropower operations, and agriculture planting windows. DAI is a leader in translating and communicating climate data, and packaging it for high-level and grassroots decision makers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-servir-program-demand-activity&quot;&gt;SERVIR Demand Activity&lt;/a&gt;, for example, DAI inventoried climate decision support products, identified gaps in services and market demand, and worked with USAID and NASA to design products to “link space to village.” On the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/usaid-central-america-regional-climate-change-program-rccp-programa-regional-de&quot;&gt;Regional Climate Change Program&lt;/a&gt; in Central America, DAI created a climate information platform—&lt;a href=&quot;http://centroclima.org/&quot;&gt;CentroClima&lt;/a&gt;—where regional leaders and other stakeholders access climate change data and decision support tools to make more informed adaptation decisions. Through CentroClima, DAI also helped develop the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.centroclima.org/coffee-cloud/&quot;&gt;Coffee Cloud app&lt;/a&gt;, which connects decision makers around daily and seasonal forecasting for coffee crops, and reports outbreaks of diseases such as rust that affect coffee beans. In Indonesia, the APIK program (Adaptasi Perubahan Iklim dan Ketangguhan, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/indonesia-apik-adaptasi-perubahan-iklim-dan-ketangguhan-or-climate-change-adaption&quot;&gt;Climate Change Adaption and Resilience&lt;/a&gt;) is also collaborating with Indonesia’s Agency for Meteorology, Climatology, and Geophysics to improve public understanding and dissemination of weather data, including flood alerts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Securing Our Future Together.&lt;/strong&gt; Significant progress has been made over the past decade to raise global awareness, shift mindsets, and begin to tackle in a pragmatic way the complex problems—environmental, economic, agricultural, health- and security-related—that together constitute the global climate challenge. DAI’s practical experience supporting government, private sector, civil society, and community partners in reducing greenhouse gas emissions and increasing resilience has contributed to a broader understanding of the complexities of climate change and its impact on people and their environment. If we are to rise to the threat of climate change, we will need to make continued progress on multiple fronts—from science and policy to mitigation and adaptation actions—and we will have to do so on a global and collective basis, from national and international government bodies to individual citizens. The stakes are too high for anything less.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
