<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DAI Online Publications</title>
    <link>http://dai-global-developments.com</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2018 14:33:10 -0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Can Nigeria Fulfill its Broad Economic Potential?</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/how-can-nigeria-fulfill-its-broad-economic-potential</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 15:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/how-can-nigeria-fulfill-its-broad-economic-potential</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nigeria is the economic heavyweight of West Africa, but it faces challenges. Approximately &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.today.ng/news/nigeria/67-percent-nigerians-live-poverty-presidency-62856&quot;&gt;two-thirds&lt;/a&gt; of its people live in poverty and its economy suffers from low productivity and an uneven climate for trade and investment. Until recently, oil-rich Nigeria has not been a good place to make products or grow crops because it didn’t have to be—the country simply imported what it needed. But times are changing for Africa’s most populous nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a 70-percent devaluation of its currency—the naira—Nigeria stands on the doorstep of opportunity. Investing in productive Nigerian businesses is now relatively affordable. These businesses are better able to compete domestically against imports, while exporting goods from Nigeria is more profitable due to lower costs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_5d8fba7d-b296-4a81-92c8-c59d7d258845&quot; title=&quot;Copy: Nigeria Competitiveness &quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?PkD&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitherto underperforming, Nigeria’s economy is still the largest in Africa, with a GDP expected to exceed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2015/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?pr.x=38&amp;amp;pr.y=9&amp;amp;sy=2015&amp;amp;ey=2019&amp;amp;scsm=1&amp;amp;ssd=1&amp;amp;sort=country&amp;amp;ds=.&amp;amp;br=1&amp;amp;c=694&amp;amp;s=NGDPD,NGDPDPC,PPPGDP,PPPPC&amp;amp;grp=0&amp;amp;a=&quot;&gt;$530 billion&lt;/a&gt; in 2018,  and it is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2015/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?pr.x=38&amp;amp;pr.y=9&amp;amp;sy=2015&amp;amp;ey=2019&amp;amp;scsm=1&amp;amp;ssd=1&amp;amp;sort=country&amp;amp;ds=.&amp;amp;br=1&amp;amp;c=694&amp;amp;s=NGDPD,NGDPDPC,PPPGDP,PPPPC&amp;amp;grp=0&amp;amp;a=&quot;&gt;positioning&lt;/a&gt; to fulfill higher expectations. This year, Nigeria &lt;a href=&quot;http://pebec.gov.ng/2017/11/01/nigeria-moves-24-places-world-banks-business-rankings/&quot;&gt;jumped 24 places&lt;/a&gt; in the World Bank’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doingbusiness.org/reports/global-reports/doing-business-2018&quot;&gt;Doing Business 2018&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ease of Doing Business&lt;/em&gt; rankings, becoming one of the world’s top-10 improving countries (of the top 10, only India is larger in terms of population). The World Bank cited Nigeria’s reforms in the areas of starting businesses, issuing construction permits, registering property, obtaining credit, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-state-partnership-accountability-responsiveness-and-capability-sparc&quot;&gt;paying taxes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors are beginning to recognize Nigeria’s more competitive climate. For example, big agribusinesses such as Dangote, Top Feeds, and Olam have increased their domestic investments, as have opportunistic personal investors from Nigeria’s moneyed class. But there is more room in Nigeria for broad-based economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the continent, Ethiopia, Ghana, and other countries—Africa represents six of the world’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-state-partnership-accountability-responsiveness-and-capability-sparc&quot;&gt;10 fastest-growing economies&lt;/a&gt;—are providing examples of demand-driven investment, mutually beneficial trade, increased productivity, and job creation. Similar results can be achieved in Nigeria. Here we offer a few examples of demand-driven ingenuity and donor-facilitated programs that have opened doors for lenders and investors in Africa and unleashed the inherent energy of Africa’s businesspeople.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Developing an Investment Pipeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors are cautious about entering new countries and assuming risk. Increasingly, though, international donors are supporting efforts to bring down that risk, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/blended-finance-in-actionhow-usaid-leveraged-100-million-in-east-africa/?utm_source=daidotcom&quot;&gt;leveraging small amounts of capital&lt;/a&gt; and helping to convene the right partners, develop solid business plans, structure investment deals, address policy constraints, and realistically project and deliver positive outcomes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Headquartered in Nairobi, Kenya, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) East Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt;, for example, has created and is delivering on an investment-ready pipeline of business opportunities. Through May 2018, the Hub has helped close more than $118 million of investment transactions for 24 firms in sectors such as agribusiness, information and communication technology, financial services, logistics, textile and apparel, and health care. An additional $68.5 million in transactions is pending closure, with $124.4 million more in the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/215195467&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With assistance from the Hub’s investment transaction team—mostly East Africans—these deals have been closing in six to 10 months on average, more quickly than in the past due to reduced risks and transaction costs. The team helps nurture the pipeline from beginning to end: mapping capital, targeting geographies and sectors, validating opportunities, conducting due diligence, modeling financials, raising funds, structuring transactions, ensuring neutral intermediation, and planning the post-investment phase. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capital that the Hub is helping to raise has been transformative for East African businesses, allowing them to innovate, grow, and ultimately sell their products locally, regionally, and internationally. The Hub’s investment and trade work—including its support for the African Growth and Opportunity Act (AGOA)—created 43,000 new jobs and assisted firms to export $350 million in AGOA-eligible product to the United States over three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A country of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premiumtimesng.com/news/top-news/264781-nigerias-population-now-198-million-npc.html&quot;&gt;more than 190 million people&lt;/a&gt;, Nigeria has strong markets ripe for investment—including in palm oil, rice, wheat, starch, poultry, and aquaculture—especially with imported foodstuffs now more expensive. Investment initiatives similar to that in East Africa can succeed in Nigeria, given supportive economic policies. In this regard, the July 2016 launch of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://pebec.gov.ng/&quot;&gt;Presidential Enabling Business Environment Council&lt;/a&gt;—which works to remove bureaucratic constraints and make Nigeria a progressively easier place to start and grow a business—was certainly a welcome step. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Unlocking Capital&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the enabling factors Nigeria must nurture is affordable financing for smallholder farmers and small and medium-sized businesses. Nigeria’s existing de-risking mechanisms, essential to whet the appetite and ease the way for investments—including the Central Bank of Nigeria’s Agricultural Credit Guarantee Scheme, the Nigerian Incentive-Based Risk Sharing System for Agricultural Lending, and the Anchor Borrower’s programme—are underutilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When investment risk is appropriately mitigated, African businesses and financial institutions will certainly step up to mobilize capital. This was demonstrated at scale by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-financial-inclusion-rural-microenterprises-firm&quot;&gt;Kenya Financial Inclusion for Rural Microenterprises&lt;/a&gt; project, which facilitated more than $1 billion in financing through a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/unlocking-capital-across-kenya-how-usaid-firm-pushed-the-frontier-of-financial-services-and-built-a-foundation-for-economic-growth/?utm_source=daidotcom&quot;&gt;myriad of programs&lt;/a&gt;, jump-starting businesses and benefitting 2.5 million local and mostly farm-based households. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere in Africa, national governments and donors are working creatively to leverage capital  in ways that deliver inclusive growth. In Malawi, for example, food warehouse operators are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/36-million-investment-facility-finances-warehouses-in-malawi-to-improve-food-security/&quot;&gt;snapping up&lt;/a&gt; €30 million of new financing to build additional storage, which will help potentially thousands of smallholder farmers reduce post-harvest losses and more effectively aggregate their crops for sale. And in Somaliland, where USAID and DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/somalia-partnership-economic-growth&quot;&gt;conducted the territory’s first business-plan competition&lt;/a&gt;, entrepreneurs wowed judges with their entries, the winners earning more than $2 million in matching grants to co-fund growth in agriculture, livestock, fisheries, and renewable energy; this enabled the businesses to attract an additional $12 million in local, diaspora, and foreign investor capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-grain-trade.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-grain-trade&quot; title=&quot;The first multilateral grain trade facilitation forum in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, saw 58 contracts executed, representing US$93.1 million in sales.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Becoming a Regional Trading Partner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigerian imports—including rice, coconuts, palm oil, starch, and fish feed—are substantial. Now that these imports are more expensive and exports correspondingly more competitive, Nigeria is highly motivated to explore regional trade opportunities. This is easier said than done; to move food legally from country to country, traders need to navigate formal and informal trade barriers, inadequate storage and transportation options, differences in regional grain and other food standards, and corrupt participants, to name a few of the challenges. But these challenges can be overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, under the auspices of the East Africa Trade and Investment Hub, food traders from six East African countries met in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/a-trade-solution-to-the-food-security-challenge-surplus-grains-worth-83-dollars-million-now-available-to-countries-in-need&quot;&gt;signed $93 million in contracts&lt;/a&gt;. The resulting sale of 279,000 metric tons of food grains represented enough to feed 1.3 million households for six months in the recipient countries. Featured transactions included mass sales of maize from Ethiopia to Kenya, for instance, helping Ethiopian farmers make ends meet and Kenyan consumers put food on their tables. A second trade forum in Zambia &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/another-big-win-for-food-security-zambia-signs-100-dollars-million-in-contracts-to-sell-surplus-grain-to-african-countries-in-need&quot;&gt;produced similar results&lt;/a&gt; for its grain exporters and neighbors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of Nigeria’s regional trade is informal because traders circumvent rules such the country’s 2015 ban on 41 different imports. The government made this restrictive move to conserve its increasingly valuable hard currency, but as a consequence 1.5 to 2 million tons of rice is now smuggled into Nigeria each year through neighboring Benin, which has no import bans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our view, Nigeria needs to step up its engagement with the 15-member &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecowas.int/&quot;&gt;Economic Community of West African States&lt;/a&gt;. Increased formal trade in West Africa could stabilize the regional supply of various commodities and bring down prices. Given its size and wealth, Nigeria is favorably positioned to lead a movement for freer trade, which would be good in the long term for Nigeria and its smaller neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-Hawassa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-Hawassa&quot; title=&quot;The Hawassa Industrial Park in Ethiopia has attracted investment by clothing manufacturers around the world and already employs 15,000 local people.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Infrastructure for Business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia has established itself as a destination for foreign investors by becoming what investors want—a good place to do business. In the past two decades, as part of a national plan, Ethiopia has paved rural roads and intercity expressways, built rail lines, and invested in developing clean energy. It has also founded more than 30 universities and hundreds of other learning institutions to support the industrial labor force needed to compete in the international economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ethiopia-stands-poised-to-lead-an-african-industrial-revolution/&quot;&gt;new industrial parks&lt;/a&gt; and the incentives surrounding them are an integral part of this strategy, and they are now attracting garment and other manufacturers from around the world. Tens of thousands of permanent jobs have been created at its first such park, two more parks recently opened, and another nine are on the way, projected to employ more than 200,000 workers in the garment industry alone. The Ethiopian government anticipates that garment exports will reach $30 billion annually by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria, too, has established major industrial parks—in Aba in Abia State, Nnewi in Anambra State, and Agbara in Ogun State. However, these parks have suffered from a lack of consistent electric power. In October 2017, the Nigerian government &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.premiumtimesng.com/business/business-news/245664-nigerias-power-generation-capacity-7000-mw-osinbajo.html&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that national power generation has increased to an all-time high of 7,000 megawatts. While transmitting that power widely remains a challenge, Nigeria is addressing this need and working toward the other conditions needed for industrial growth, including workforce development and education programs, and an effective transportation infrastructure. Again, the time is right for investing in these needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tapping Nigeria&amp;rsquo;s Deep Talent Pool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria is rich in human resources. With 37 million people ages 15–24 and another 80 million &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldpopulationreview.com/countries/nigeria-population/&quot;&gt;younger still&lt;/a&gt;, the time has never been more urgent to invest in Nigeria’s talent and ensure that the upcoming generation has suitable employment opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USAID’s current global &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/what-we-do/agriculture-and-food-security/increasing-food-security-through-feed-future/fall-armyworm&quot;&gt;prize competition&lt;/a&gt; to solicit digital solutions for combatting fall armyworm—a scourge destroying crops across Africa—offers just one small example of the kind of talent latent in Nigeria. The competition attracted more than 220 entries from 34 countries, but two of the 20 finalists hail from Nigeria. The country is increasingly recognizing and acting on the need to tap this homegrown talent, as it is doing through initiatives such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scholarships.myschoolgist.com/student-innovation-challenge/&quot;&gt;Student Innovation Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cleanenergy.ng/&quot;&gt;Clean Energy Innovation Challenge&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-KIC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-KIC&quot; title=&quot;AgroCenta, a startup company which was part of the Kosmos Innovation Center programme in Ghana, was crowned 2018 Global Winner of Seedstars World in Lausanne, Switzerland. Photo: Kosmos Innovation Center.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar models elsewhere in Africa show real promise in terms of engaging young people in economic sectors key to inclusive growth and employment. In Ghana, for example, DAI helped Kosmos Energy design and implement the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kosmosinnovationcenter.com/&quot;&gt;Kosmos Innovation Center (KIC)&lt;/a&gt; to identify and assist promising entrepreneurs in the country’s agriculture sector. In three years, more than 1,000 youth innovators from across Ghana have applied to KIC’s “AgriTech Challenge,” which provides would-be entrepreneurs with training and seed funding to establish tech-driven agribusinesses. One winner developed tractor-plowing services that can be summoned by mobile phone; another developed software to manage livestock and track the health status of individual animals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, in 2018 more than 100 established small and medium-sized agribusinesses submitted their business plans to join KIC’s “Business Booster” program; KIC provided nine local ventures with technical assistance to develop and scale their ideas and operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are to succeed and grow, business owners and investors need motivated local workforces with the right skills. In Ethiopia, the Hawassa Industrial Park &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/development-secretary-priti-patel-stresses-economic-growth-in-visit-to-ethiopia-industrial-park&quot;&gt;opened for business&lt;/a&gt; in July 2016 in collaborarion with a local operation set up to hire and train the thousands of people needed to work at the park. The Ethiopian government and park employers established this recruitment platform in conjunction with training companies and facilitated by a local firm, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-private-enterprise-programme-ethiopia-pepe&quot;&gt;Enterprise Partners&lt;/a&gt;. The Hawassa park is projected to support 60,000 jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USAID’s Hub in East Africa is connecting global businesses with the Hawassa opportunity, facilitating linkages with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/us-apparel-retailers-east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-join-forces-to-improve-competitiveness-and-social-responsibility&quot;&gt;major U.S. brands&lt;/a&gt; and enabling apparel companies to participate in major trade shows. This is generating demand for finished goods, thereby contributing to the success of the firms that invested in the industrial park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such public-private cooperation is part of Ethiopia’s &lt;a href=&quot;file:///C:/Users/ccoon/Downloads/gtpii_english_translation_final_june_21_2016.pdf&quot;&gt;Growth and Transformation Plan&lt;/a&gt;, which is expected to spin off thousands of small businesses and offer the farming community access to new markets, potentially transforming the country’s economic base into a more globally connected industry. Nigeria’s development plans should address the same &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2016/03/15/nigerias-booming-population-requires-more-and-better-jobs&quot;&gt;need&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Time to Step Up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nigeria has made progress in driving investment and improving competitiveness, these reforms are likely not felt broadly by the man and woman on the street, because investment in areas such as power has been low for decades, multiple taxation and other barriers to doing business have constrained success, and only a few state governments—notably Kaduna and Lagos—have wholeheartedly embraced the &lt;em&gt;Ease of Doing Business&lt;/em&gt; initiatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibilities abound for Nigeria to step up its economic performance by improving its business fundamentals. That means opening doors for the private sector in ways that benefit the entire country—promoting trade that is accountable but not overregulated, policies that promote monetary stability and enable investors to easily enter and exit Nigerian markets, finance regimes that facilitate responsible and inclusive lending, and long-range economic development plans with aggressive stewards, including plans for infrastructure development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting now, Nigeria enjoys improved competitiveness due to its devalued currency and opportune circumstances. As the economic heavyweight of West Africa, it should—and could—be a champion of economic growth, investment, and trade.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blended Finance in Action—How USAID Leveraged $100 Million in East Africa</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/blended-finance-in-actionhow-usaid-leveraged-100-million-in-east-africa</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 17:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/blended-finance-in-actionhow-usaid-leveraged-100-million-in-east-africa</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier this spring, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; achieved a major milestone by surpassing the $100-million mark in commercial investment catalyzed into the region. This investment would not have found its way to these markets without the approximately $4 million nudge offered by the Hub, a U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) initiative implemented by DAI. Given the potential impact of the investee companies, this project shows how a donor like USAID can leverage its relatively scarce capital to crowd in more plentiful commercial funds—a process known as blended finance. The leverage factor is almost 25x.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $100 million funded 17 investments in sectors as diverse as agribusiness, mobile technology, and apparel. A great example of a high-impact company is &lt;a href=&quot;http://twigafoods.com/&quot;&gt;Twiga Foods&lt;/a&gt;, a Kenya-based mobile platform that provides seamless logistics support for fresh produce from farm to fork—removing intermediaries, reducing costs, cutting post-harvest losses, and getting food where it needs to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/twiga.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;twiga&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these funds have been invested in Kenya and Ethiopia. Both are considered “frontier” markets by most investors, who perceive high levels of risk. Typically, investors would require higher rates of return to make up for the extra risk incurred in these markets. But the Hub takes a different approach: we ask, what can we do to “de-risk” the project, bringing the odds of success more in line with markets that investors already understand?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how it works: our transaction team offers support to local firms on the investment process and guidance on investment sourcing, due diligence, and markets to potential investors (private equity funds, corporates, banks, development finance institutions, impact investors, and so forth). In some cases, we might need to employ additional instruments such as matching funds, credit guarantees, or political risk insurance. Each transaction calls for a tailored package of support, depending on the circumstances. We find the right ingredients for each case and see it through until the deal is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blending%20blog%20visual%20v2.png&quot; alt=&quot;blending blog visual v2&quot; title=&quot;Twiga trucks&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors have a herd mentality. In many cases, multiple investors will follow each other into a particular company, sometimes using different instruments. The key is to get one of them to move first so that the others follow. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://unctad.org/en/Pages/Home.aspx&quot;&gt;United Nations Conference on Trade and Development&lt;/a&gt;, the biggest source of foreign direct investment is follow-on investment either from existing investors or new investors mimicking their peers (the herd effect). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But blending is not magic; on the contrary, it can be really hard work! 
And not everyone loves blending. We frequently hear concerns about “overblending” or distorting the market with too much concessional donor funding. The value of the blended capital market is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.weforum.org/docs/WEF_Blended_Finance_Insights_Investments_Vehicles_Facilities_report_2016.pdf&quot;&gt;estimated at $25.4 billion&lt;/a&gt;, which is a big number but small in the scope of global capital markets measured in the trillions. Should we really be using taxpayer money to subsidize private companies when the transactions should happen on a market basis? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that the invisible hand of the market does not always channel investments to their best use from a social or environmental perspective. If we believe that the best poverty reduction tool is a job and that dynamic private enterprise should create that job, then driving investment to opportunities that are just beyond the reach of the current market is a potent solution. We make transactions happen where they otherwise wouldn’t, benefiting the investors, investee companies, and workers. As a bonus, the products or services of these investee companies often benefit society as well—by filling an access gap for poor or low-income people, for instance, or creating jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hub’s leverage factor of 25 is excellent value for money. But we need to figure out how to become even more efficient, maximizing the impact of every single donor dollar spent. The three main challenges we see include the lack of capacity within transaction advisory firms, the significant costs of setting up and executing a high-impact transaction facilitation service, and the difficulty of identifying high-potential deal flow with a high probability of closure over the short-to-medium term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/kanini%20in%20action.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;kanini in action&quot; title=&quot;Kanini Mutooni speaks at the 4th Angel Fair Africa in 2016 about backing Africa’s leading entrepreneurs to build great companies.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hub experiment and others like it reflect a fundamental shift in mindset and practice in the development space. Increasingly, donors, philanthropists, and investors recognize that the only way to reach lofty development objectives such as the Sustainable Development Goals is to capture private investment. All the government and donor capital in the world cannot possibly fill the &lt;a href=&quot;http://unctad.org/en/pages/PressRelease.aspx?OriginalVersionID=194&quot;&gt;$2.5 trillion gap&lt;/a&gt; identified by the United Nations as necessary to meet the SDGs. Blending concessional money to crowd in private investment is not just a trendy approach, but absolutely necessary to address the social and environmental challenges of our time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Generation of EC Framework Contracts Offers Agile Programming for European Development Aid</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-generation-of-ec-framework-contracts-offers-agile-programming-for-european-development-aid</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-generation-of-ec-framework-contracts-offers-agile-programming-for-european-development-aid</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that DAI has once again been named one of the main implementing partners for the European Commission (EC) 2018–2022 Frameworks contracts for international development assistance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Frameworks represent an agile development programming tool that enables the EC to quickly source and execute short-term research and pilot projects around the world. Unlike typical multiyear, donor-funded projects that work in a particular country or region—and can take more than a year to plan, bid, and launch—EC Frameworks contracts are capable of being designed, awarded, and deployed in a matter of weeks and can dispatch project teams to any country receiving development aid from the Commission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI has a long history of supporting this unique contracting mechanism, dating back more than 20 years. Indeed, the challenging assignments and diverse technical work entailed under the Frameworks have accelerated our own learning and enriched our capabilities as a global development company. As we look forward to the next round of Framework assignments, we reflect back on our experiences and learning from this important facet of the EC’s external aid program. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A New and Flexible Development Tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EC Framework contracts have their origins in the early 1990s, when the Commission began helping Central and Eastern European countries prepare for accession to full membership in the European Union (EU). This pre-accession period demanded what was pioneering development work at the time: never before had so much support been needed for countries transitioning from highly centralized governments and economic regimes to open democracies and free market systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central administrations of 10 countries seeking EU accession had to be overhauled and modernised, with some ministries disbanded and others created. In many cases, Soviet-style state-owned companies needed support to adopt new ways of thinking as they were privatised and shifted overnight from five-year, state-run production plans to dynamic, demand-driven markets. There was also a massive effort to re-draft laws and regulations in pre-accession countries to harmonize with EU regulations across a range of sectors and concerns, from agriculture and the environment to energy efficiency and consumer protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the volume of this specialized work ballooned, the EC was almost overwhelmed by the administrative burden—at one point attempting to manage 10,000 contracts with individual consultants. Recognizing this approach as unsustainable, the Commission developed over-arching agreements called Framework contracts. Under the early agreements, each lot or sector was awarded to just one company, which was eventually expanded to three or four pre-approved Framework contractors bidding on assignments in a mini-tender. This allowed the EC to source experts for assignments in a matter of weeks rather than months and to more efficiently contract assignments by pre-qualifying bidding organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s experience with Framework contracts began when predecessor company PE was selected for early assignments that included developing an energy strategy in Lithuania and analyzing the impact of coal privatization in Poland—projects indicative of the early Frameworks’ focus on public administration reform, privatization, and restructuring in neighboring countries applying to join the EU. However, the EC’s use of Framework contracts would soon expand to new frontiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Estonia-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Estonia-1&quot; title=&quot;Tallinn, the capital of Estonia, which was one of the countries targeted by early EC Framework assignments focusing on decentralisation and democracy.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Global Expansion and Diversification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, 10 countries—Cyprus, the Czech Republic, Estonia, Hungary, Latvia, Lithuania, Malta, Poland, Slovakia, and Slovenia—completed the formal EU accession process and in doing so became ineligible for external development aid. As a result, the Commission shifted the focus of its external aid from Europe to other parts of the world, with Framework assignments now emphasizing technical areas such as agricultural development and economic growth rather than post-Soviet restructuring. Over the years, DAI’s Frameworks Unit has adapted to meet these changing needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Frameworks allowed DAI to build new expertise in areas such as education and social development. Over the past 15 years, DAI has led assignments including curriculum development, financial planning for school systems, and evaluations of national education systems. The host countries for these assignments have ranged from the Middle East (Jordan and Iraq) to Africa (Ghana, Morocco, Sierra Leone, and Zimbabwe) and even Greenland. The diversity of the Frameworks projects also enabled DAI to develop a growing pool of trusted technical experts with a wide assortment of specializations, from veterinary doctors and meteorologists to criminal justice and cyber security professionals.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2005, we have implemented more than 800 Framework assignments for the EC, valued at around €100 million, engaging 2,000 technical experts. Framework assignments continue to span the gamut of technical disciplines, from food security, economic growth, and governance to recent engagements related to human rights, migration, and climate change. Thanks in part to this breadth of expertise—complemented by our extensive work for the U.S. Agency for International Development, the U.K. Department for International Development, the World Bank, and other donors—DAI was awarded a presence on all six lots of the new EC Framework contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_86feb80e-d767-484d-82a9-01774d1c755a&quot; title=&quot;EC Frameworks&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?tyb&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Amplifying Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our EC Frameworks portfolio has positioned DAI to serve both country-level EU Delegations and, at a  global level, the EC’s Directorate-General for International Development Cooperation. In turn, other European bilateral donors have entrusted us with important work: a multiyear monitoring and evaluation project for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Denmark on its Business Sector Programme Support in Tanzania, for example; a smaller project for its Global Green Growth Forum; a study on public pension reform in South Sudan funded by a consortium of donors including Canada, Denmark, the Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Spain, and the United Kingdom. A Framework assignment we conducted to compare the EC’s external aid operations with those of four other bilateral donors led us to work with Germany’s development Bank, KfW, to carry out a similar comparative analysis of its and other donors’ best practices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global development company, DAI is committed to capturing synergies and sharing knowledge across our projects. We are excited to leverage our cross-donor experience to better support the EC’s global development work, and we look forward to incorporating the lessons learned and best practices gained through our Framework assignments to benefit all of the organizations—and all of the communities—for which we work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Jordan’s Youth Unemployment Bubble: USAID Program Aligns Workforce with Emerging Opportunities</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/addressing-jordans-youth-unemployment-bubble-usaid-program-aligns-workforce-with-emerging-opportunities</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/addressing-jordans-youth-unemployment-bubble-usaid-program-aligns-workforce-with-emerging-opportunities</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jordan is a relative bastion of stability in the Middle East but is struggling with an unemployment problem. More than 700,000 of its young people—&lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/%20SL.UEM.1524.ZS&quot;&gt;36 percent&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://databank.worldbank.org/data/Views/Metadata/MetadataWidget.aspx?Name=Labor%20force%20participation%20rate,%20total%20(%25%20of%20total%20population%20ages%2015+)%20(national%20estimate)&amp;amp;Code=SL.TLF.CACT.NE.ZS&amp;amp;Type=S&amp;amp;ReqType=Metadata&amp;amp;ddlSelecte&quot;&gt;available labor force&lt;/a&gt; ages 15–24—are without a job. This percentage is double that of Afghanistan and triple that of Bangladesh, even though those countries register poverty levels far worse than Jordan’s. The problem has intensified since 2011 with the influx of hundreds of thousands of refugees following the Syrian crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan is also a country surrounded by lingering conflicts in Syria, Iraq, and Palestine, and officials understandably &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/content/documents/16289Jordan.pdf&quot;&gt;view&lt;/a&gt; youth unemployment as a significant threat to stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of a wide-ranging effort to transition its out-of-work youth into the formal economy, Jordan’s government partnered with the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-workforce-development-wfd-project&quot;&gt;Jordan Workforce Development (WFD)&lt;/a&gt; project, which recently concluded a 3½-year implementation. Among WFD’s many accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Producing and submitting policy papers and briefs for the government that address fair pay, flexible working hours, and incentives to “hire Jordanian.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating national standards for and training 40 career guidance counselors, and establishing career guidance offices in six vocational training institutes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Placing 5,100 Jordanians and Syrian refugees into new jobs in the food production, clean energy, and garment sectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing and launching three Employment Promotion Units, which facilitated the job placements and today enjoy good prospects for growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-WFD-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-WFD-1&quot; title=&quot;Akhtaboot job fair in Amman supported by a USAID Jordan Workforce Development Project Employment Promotion Unit.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Modernizing Jordan’s Workforce Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When WFD began in September 2014, Jordan’s vocational training system was churning out high numbers of potential workers for sectors with decreasing demand, such as tourism and hospitality. This was because supply-driven training programs had been failing to forecast workforce needs or even reach out to potential employers for input. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, many Jordanians harbored a cultural inclination to view vocational jobs—such as in carpentry, hospitality, and hairdressing—as less desirable than more prestigious “office jobs.” Combined with the country’s unfocused workforce development efforts, it was little wonder that young Jordanians trying to enter the workforce found scarce opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dynamic needed to change if Jordan was to meet the needs of job seekers and would-be employers. By creating Employment Promotion Units (EPUs) with the Zarqa and Irbid Chambers of Industry and Eastern Amman Investors Industrial Association, the country now has a better way to prepare employees and employers for workforce challenges.
The EPUs’ career counselors and marketing officers connect with clients in public, including by working at mall kiosks emblazoned with the Employment Promotion Unit brand and by networking at public gatherings such as Friday prayers. The WFD team produced movies shown by the EPUs that highlight career paths for vocations such as heating, ventilation and air-conditioning, die cutting, and electrical maintenance. The EPUs also keep updated websites with career opportunities with help lines for inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This outreach has succeeded in attracting a large pool of candidates—more than 15,000 registrants and counting—who have been vetted based on their qualifications and, when appropriate, referred to an employer. These efforts also seem to have improved the “cultural status” of vocational jobs among Jordan’s youth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Jordan-WFD1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jordan-WFD1&quot; title=&quot;Eastern Amman Investors Industrial Association job fair promoting Al-Quds University scholarships.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Making People Employable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with young people entering workforces all over the world, many young Jordanians come unequipped with the “soft skills” that employers need in their workplace—such as the ability to be on time, communicate effectively, work as part of a team, and solve problems independently. While these and other soft skills differ from job to job, by speaking directly with employers, EPU staff ascertained where otherwise qualified job candidates have fallen short of being employable. They designed eight modules of “Work Ready Now” training to build soft skills that bridge the gap between classroom and workplace. 
This effort by the WFD was so well-received by employers—mostly small or medium-sized enterprises—that many further committed to rewards programs designed to create career paths for workers and reduce turnover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Crafting Policies That Support Job Creation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its 2015 economic outlook, the International Monetary Fund outlined key challenges facing Jordan, including designing and implementing “broad-based policies in the labor market.” The IMF also cited the need to create more jobs for women, who held only &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordantimes.com/news/local/women-unemployment-increases-33-q1&quot;&gt;one in seven jobs&lt;/a&gt; in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WFD team crafted policy reforms that will support workforce development, preparing and submitting policy papers to the Jordanian government that address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible workplace hours for established employees, employees with family responsibilities, university students, and the disabled, to promote employment among women, young people, and the marginalized; the policy was endorsed in a Royal Decree by HM King Abdullah II.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incentives for employers to prioritize hiring Jordanians for labor-intensive occupations, which have a disproportionate number of lower-wage foreign workers; the brief is before the Ministry of Labor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum wage and benefits guidelines for compensating entry-level workers, with the goal of avoiding potential exploitation in the labor market, also before the Ministry of Labor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Germany Signs On for the Road Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By addressing the supply, demand, and policy sides of workforce development, the WFD team delivered measurable results while building a foundation for job growth in Jordan. Thanks in large part to the EPU model, the WFD has placed more than 5,100 workers in sustainable jobs, exceeding USAID’s target by 20 percent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the value and effectiveness of the EPU model, the German development agency &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giz.de/en/worldwide/360.html&quot;&gt;GIZ&lt;/a&gt; has committed to further assistance. These funds aim to help the EPUs become self-sustaining units that would eventually operate using higher quality, fee-based services for employees, employers, and the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand-driven EPU model has potential to be adopted by countries throughout the Middle East and North Africa, as does the WFD’s holistic approach, which offers an alternative to outdated, supply-driven workforce development. By offering flexible and targeted employment services that address emerging workforce supply and demand, countries can more effectively address the needs of their private sectors and underemployed youth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can We Keep the Promise?
Mobilizing Business on the Refugee Frontline in Jordan</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-we-keep-the-promisemobilizing-business-on-the-refugee-frontline-in-jordan</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 13:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-we-keep-the-promisemobilizing-business-on-the-refugee-frontline-in-jordan</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, lower- and middle-income countries have borne the brunt of the global refugee crisis, currently hosting more than 80 percent of the world’s refugees. But some host countries, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/calculating-syrian-refugee-crisis-fiscal-crisis/&quot;&gt;Jordan&lt;/a&gt;, are taking important steps to seize what opportunities they can in this situation, supporting refugee self-reliance and at the same time boosting their own economy by issuing work permits to refugees and connecting multinational companies to business opportunities with local firms and displaced people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blessed with a supportive government, preferential access to U.S. and E.U. markets, and strong investment incentives, Jordan provides opportunities for businesses to make investments or improve their sourcing, while at the same time creating jobs for refugees. But this model has not been without its challenges. What can we learn from Jordan’s experience, and where can we go from here?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Scale of the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of Jordan’s challenge is the sheer scale and rapidity of the human influx: more than 1.5 million refugees and displaced persons—both registered and unregistered—in roughly the past seven years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report by Jordan’s Ministry of Planning and International Cooperation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://jordan.gov.jo/wps/portal/Home/GovernmentEntities/Ministries/Ministry/Ministry%20of%20Planning%20and%20International%20Cooperation?nameEntity=Ministry%20of%20Planning%20and%20International%20Cooperation&amp;amp;entityType=ministry&quot;&gt;MOPIC&lt;/a&gt;) estimates that the country has borne an additional $6.6 billion in direct costs—for health care, education, transport, and municipal services—since the beginning of the Syrian refugee crisis in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take health care, for example: MOPIC documented a 30 percent increase in hospital and health center occupancy nationwide, resulting in a 24 percent shortfall in the availability of hospital beds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As His Majesty King Abdallah II has noted, even those people who might one day return are expected to remain, on average, 17 years in the country, which means Jordan’s response to this crisis is not a stop-gap measure; today’s policy choices are, for all intents and purposes, setting Jordan’s development agenda for the foreseeable future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jordan_refugees.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of children at a clinic in Ramtha, northern Jordan.&quot; title=&quot;Children from Syria at a clinic in Ramatha, northern Jordan. (Photo: Russell Watkins, U.K. Department for International Development.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Finding Opportunity in Adversity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan has worked to transform the Syrian refugee crisis into an economic opportunity for all residents of Jordan—an effort that, many observers agree, has had mixed success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what we define as the Syria response in Jordan, particularly insofar as it has been supported by the international donor community, has been driven by the so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://reliefweb.int/report/jordan/jordan-compact-new-holistic-approach-between-hashemite-kingdom-jordan-and&quot;&gt;Jordan Compact&lt;/a&gt;. The Compact details specific macroeconomic interventions meant to stimulate growth in the Jordanian economy, creating jobs for Jordanian communities and for the hundreds of thousands of displaced Syrians they host. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key among these macroeconomic interventions is a 10-year trade regime that relaxes so-called “rules of origin” requirements for Jordanian exporters to the European Union. To take advantage of the scheme, though, Jordanian exporters must prove that 15 percent of their workforce is Syrian—a number which was originally planned to increase to 25 percent after the first two years of the Compact’s implementation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we get to the mixed results. Although the Jordanian government has issued tens of thousands of work permits to Syrians, fulfilling the World Bank’s Disbursement-Linked Indicators, far fewer of these workers have actually been hired by Jordanian companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this disparity should be obvious: Even if we assume they are eager to join the formal economy, Syrian workers—although known for their prowess as tradespeople and craftsmen—seldom have the skills in demand by Jordanian factories. The costs of up-skilling them have outweighed the potential cost savings on offer through the E.U. trade deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to the point, Syrian refugees have proven reluctant to register with the Ministry of Labor, preferring instead to keep earning wages in the informal economy, where they can also collect aid from relief agencies and maintain their claim to restitution or repatriation when the Syrian conflict ends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.odi.org/publications/11045-jordan-compact-lessons-learnt-and-implications-future-refugee-compacts&quot;&gt;recent report&lt;/a&gt; by the London-based Overseas Development Institute (ODI) makes clear, these demand-side issues could have been anticipated. The report’s authors note, for example, that the Compact’s design “did not integrate refugee perspectives at the outset.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the Compact has yielded significant gains in human welfare, especially for the most vulnerable. ODI cites the Jordanian Ministry of Education, which reported that, in the 2016-17 academic year, some 126,000 Syrian refugee children were enrolled in public education or certified to attend private or nongovernmental organization-run schools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a considerable achievement, with demonstrable results in the lives of children and their families. But these are what one might call “traditional” relief efforts—absolutely necessary but, in the context of a country with a 96 percent debt-to-GDP ratio, not nearly enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Doing Better&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the gap between our ambitions for the Jordan Compact and the often lackluster economic results, what would guide a more successful development program—one that takes our country from resilience to growth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it will require an agreed-upon framework grounded in the government’s own vision. That vision is contained in the Jordan Economic Growth Plan, a five-year roadmap published most recently in 2018 by Jordan’s Economic Policy Council and closely tied to the requirements of the International Monetary Fund’s Extended Fund Facility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closely tied to the Economic Growth Plan and adding further rigor to the analysis is the World Bank’s recent Jump-Starting Growth and Job Creation in Jordan, a framework presented in October 2017—laying out “elements of a responsive adjustment program that will lead to higher GDP growth and better jobs outcomes”—that serves as a useful mechanism for organizing upcoming donor-supported efforts in Jordan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the donor community, too, has begun to realign its programs, taking its cues from the ODI report and others. The development firm for which I serve as a board member, DAI, recently published a wide-ranging &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/white-paper-offers-development-ideas-for-jordan-in-light-of-refugee-surge&quot;&gt;white paper&lt;/a&gt; outlining a path forward designed to generate economic development in the context of the Syrian refugee crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s recommendations cover everything from the natural environment, including developing new energy sources and managing scarce water resources; to the policy environment, including measures to promote e-government initiatives such as online resident services; to workforce development and entrepreneurship, including employment services and business incubators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jordan_refugees2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of children at a clinic in Ramtha, northern Jordan&quot; title=&quot;A woman from Homs, Syria, now a refugee in neighboring Lebanon. (Photo: Russell Watkins, U.K. Department for International Development).&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Prospects for Progress&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still room to make good on the promise of the Compact. A DAI-run project, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-competitiveness-program-jcp&quot;&gt;USAID Jordan Competitiveness Program&lt;/a&gt;, has completed two rounds of a hands-on, firm-level assistance program aimed at finding those Jordanian manufacturers with the greatest likelihood of exporting to the European Union—assisting them with packaging and marketing their products, and helping them identify buyers in the European market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through a partnership between that DAI-run program and the Jordan Investment Commission, the American Chamber of Commerce in Amman, and the Ministry of Industry and Trade, the U.S. Agency for International Development is helping build the capacity of the Commission’s newly established Investment Promotion Directorate. Through that program, more than $140 million in promising leads have been identified, and the most eager of these international investors will be hosted in Jordan next month for field visits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also actively marketing Jordan in the United States, where my colleagues in Jordan have organized two impact investment fora in June. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.connect.jo/jordan-impact-investment-forum-nyc/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;, in New York, will feature Jordan’s Minister of Planning, who oversees implementation of the Jordan Compact on behalf of the government; a second event in San Francisco will feature our Minister of Industry and Trade, who has long been a leading advocate for Jordan’s exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the long term, we need continued engagement from the donor community to make the most of the development assistance it has extended to the communities and countries that host millions of people forced from their homes. In Jordan, we are yet to realize the full potential of the Compact, but we would be doing the Jordanian people and the refugees among them a disservice if we fail to explore every avenue to deliver on that promise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Health and Tech Thinkers Come Together at SwitchPoint</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/global-health-and-tech-thinkers-come-together-at-switchpoint</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 15:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/global-health-and-tech-thinkers-come-together-at-switchpoint</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/&quot;&gt;SwitchPoint&lt;/a&gt;, a two-day conference organized by Intrahealth International—a DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-and-intrahealth-join-forces-to-amplify-global-health-impact&quot;&gt;strategic affiliate&lt;/a&gt;—400 global health and technology devotees came together in the North Carolina countryside to share ideas and seed partnerships for solving global health challenges, especially by using technology. The seventh annual event, held April 26–27, featured 30-plus stage speakers and 20-plus microlabs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These talks and microlabs covered a host of topics, from pandemic preparedness and the value of community health workers to how health innovators can best engage with investors—and much more. Here are just a few of the stand-out moments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-13&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving Sex a Good Name:&lt;/strong&gt; Youth in India—&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2017-09-08/india-s-youth-are-the-world-s-future&quot;&gt;home&lt;/a&gt; to 229 million people between ages 15–24—are interested in sex, and the internet is their top source of information, notes &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/vithika-yadav&quot;&gt;Vithika Yadav&lt;/a&gt;, co-founder and head of &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.in/en&quot;&gt;Love Matters India&lt;/a&gt;. Of India’s youth with internet access, she said, 83 percent of those surveyed have watched pornography, which paints an unreal and irresponsible picture of sex. “We have to invest in young people’s health; we need to use technology to give sex a good name,” Yadav said, adding that it is difficult for India’s young to find information on relationships, abstinence, and contraception. “Young people are looking for information about sex online,” she said. “We need to know what is youth-friendly information on sex, and how to help young people find material that resonates with them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start-Ups—Get Funding, Win Prize Money:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/bobby-jefferson&quot;&gt;Bobby Jefferson&lt;/a&gt;, pictured above, Chief Technology Officer for DAI Global Health, broke down the many avenues available for people with ideas to pursue financing. Jefferson told the audience that even well-known brands—brands not normally associated with social investment—are investing in people who show promise for delivering breakthrough ideas and thinking. He warned, though, that social investing to date has been heavily skewed and we need more women, people of color, and underserved communities to be recipients of investment funding. “Large companies and other investors increasingly realize they do not have all the answers,” Jefferson said. “Many organizations and individuals are now investing money to unearth new ideas and new energy by sponsoring contests, prizes, and innovation investment funds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow (Attract?) the Money:&lt;/strong&gt;  This microlab, photo above, featured investors, including DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/leadership/christopher-legrand&quot;&gt;Chris LeGrand&lt;/a&gt;, taking questions from people with business concepts and proposals. “Nonprofits are getting less funding—we need to learn how to raise funding differently, and this is not a bad thing,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/kafui-prebbie&quot;&gt;Kafui Prebbie&lt;/a&gt;, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://techaide.global/&quot;&gt;TechAide&lt;/a&gt; in Ghana. TechAide is seeking funding for its latest project, called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.myasanka.com/&quot;&gt;ASANKA&lt;/a&gt;, a device that collects and distributes digital content communally between wireless devices without internet access. “Investors want to see traction—impact and business results to date,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/diana-ayton-shenker&quot;&gt;Diana Ayton-Shenker&lt;/a&gt; of The New School. Added &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medtronic.com/us-en/about/foundation.html&quot;&gt;Anne Katharine Wales&lt;/a&gt; of Medtronic Foundation, “How are you going to build a shared vision so it is not just your thing?” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-5&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The One-Dollar, Bacteria-Discovering Microscope:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/jim-cybulski&quot;&gt;Jim Cybulski&lt;/a&gt; and Foldscope Instruments “want communities everywhere in the world to experience science.” The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foldscope.com/&quot;&gt;foldable microscope&lt;/a&gt; made mostly from paper and $1 in parts zooms to 140X, plus 10X digital zoom with a smart phone. More than 300,000 are deployed throughout the world, enabling schoolchildren to see micro-organisms and serving social purposes such as identifying fake drugs and currency, detecting bacteria in milk and water, and finding the microscopic eggs of agricultural pests. By bringing scientific capabilities to everyday life in remote locales, the foldscope creates openings for mentoring, opportunities for community networking, and platforms for local research and development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-7&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching Next-Gen:&lt;/strong&gt; “Teachers are force multipliers, impacting every student they teach,” said Julie Keane of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.participate.com/&quot;&gt;Participate&lt;/a&gt;, which works to add global views into U.S. curriculum and proposes educating teachers on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/sdgs&quot;&gt;Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;. “When teachers fight for what’s right, kids fight for what’s right. Let’s find a way to make teachers comfortable with [these goals], with education skills that makes sense.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-11&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowing What People Will Do:&lt;/strong&gt; It is not true that “the future belongs to crowds,” as author Don DeLillo wrote in 1991—instead, “it belongs to those who can predict and know what crowds will do,” and is used for both development and destruction, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://hhi.harvard.edu/people/nathaniel-raymond&quot;&gt;Nathaniel Raymond&lt;/a&gt; of the Harvard Humanitarian Initiative. “We are interested in when and where you do things,” he said, but in light of the recent scrutiny of Facebook, we have to remember the privacy dimension. “Data is about how we establish trust,” he said. “Data is people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-6&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitors Unite for Community Health:&lt;/strong&gt; “Community health worker programs … remain a good investment, since the alternative in reality is no care at all for the poor living in geographically peripheral areas.” The finding comes from a heralded 1998 World Health Organization &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/hrh/documents/community_health_workers.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, “and we are writing the same sentence today,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/madeleine-ballard&quot;&gt;Madeleine Ballard&lt;/a&gt; of the Community Health Impact Coalition. “[Yet] about 1 billion people in the world have never seen a health worker.” Ballard and a team of six organizations that frequently compete against each other recently collaborated to produce a report &lt;a href=&quot;https://chwimpact.org/&quot;&gt;distilling the secret sauce&lt;/a&gt; to optimizing community-led health systems. To summarize, successful community-led systems are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accredited.&lt;/strong&gt; Local health workers need that are tested and certified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessible.&lt;/strong&gt; Avoid point-of-care user fees. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proactive.&lt;/strong&gt; Workers go door to door seeking out the ill and surveilling for outbreaks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuously trained.&lt;/strong&gt; Medical education, not one-shot training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dedicated supervisor.&lt;/strong&gt; To assess work and coach one on one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data feedback loops.&lt;/strong&gt; Integrate info into public data systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paid.&lt;/strong&gt; Poor health workers should not be forced to work for free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part of a strong system.&lt;/strong&gt; Not operating in a vacuum but joined to a primary care facility and pharmacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring the Invisible:&lt;/strong&gt; A rural mother who cooks, cleans, raises children, cares for elders, collects firewood, and more stands a good chance of going unseen and uncounted even if we’re looking for her, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/nina-rabinovitch-blecker&quot;&gt;Nina Rabinovich Blecker&lt;/a&gt; of the United Nations Foundation’s Data2X project. Instead, fathers speak for daughters and husbands for wives. “We have a significant gap in data about women and girls,” Blecker told SwitchPoint. “We cannot improve something we are not measuring,” she said, which makes it harder to assist victims of violence, people with special needs, and those who do unpaid work, for example. But high-quality data collection and national debate can drive change, she said, citing the case of Uruguay, which in 2016 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.data2x.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/UruguayCaseStudy_OECDDCR2017.pdf&quot;&gt;launched&lt;/a&gt; its National Care Plan. “Unbiased data collection is the goal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-12&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ugh–Development Selfies:&lt;/strong&gt; Photojournalist &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/trevor-snapp&quot;&gt;Trevor Snapp&lt;/a&gt; thinks selfies send the wrong message. “We all do these selfies with people from across the tracks,” Snapp said. “It is not accurate. It is becoming, honestly, a kind of embarrassment.” Instead, he suggests supporting local storytellers and learning from them. Supporting events such as the April 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://nairobitechweek.com/&quot;&gt;Nairobi Tech Week&lt;/a&gt; and hackathon, for example, gives Africans an opportunity to be creative and embrace communication technology. “There needs to be collaboration all the time—there is no room for just one person telling the story,” Snapp said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-10&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Softer Collaboration That Points Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only thing being sold at SwitchPoint were T-shirts, healthy food and beverages, ideas, and partnering. Event organizer and lead sponsor IntraHealth displayed no signage. Attendees in casual dress enjoyed intergenerational collaboration and intellectual stimulation against a backdrop of performance art and live music. Packed comfortably into an old cotton mill-turned-concert-hall attached to a general store and microbrewery along the Haw River—SwitchPoint attendees and presenters shared ideas freely between activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SwitchPoint effect can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-digital.com/a-do-no-harm-framework-for-ict4d-inspiration-from-switchpoint-2018.html&quot;&gt;inspiring&lt;/a&gt;. The ultimate results, let’s hope, will be inspiration turned into action.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>With U.K. Aid, Lebanon’s Social Enterprises Pilot a New Model of Development</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-uk-aid-lebanon-social-enterprise-pilot-new-model-of-development</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2018 17:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-uk-aid-lebanon-social-enterprise-pilot-new-model-of-development</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The influx of refugees from across the Syrian border is straining Lebanon’s economy and host communities. Since 2011, Lebanon’s population has &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.TOTL?locations=LB&quot;&gt;increased&lt;/a&gt; 30 percent to around 6 million as a result of this influx, and its young people are increasingly anxious to enter the workforce. Many even wish to start or join social enterprises to help address the country’s challenges, including problems stemming from the refugee crisis. But until recently there were few avenues for pursuing this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funded by the U.K. Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/lebanon-social-enterprise-pilot-project&quot;&gt;Lebanon Social Enterprise Pilot Project&lt;/a&gt;—known locally as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.souklb.co/&quot;&gt;SoUK.LB&lt;/a&gt; Social Enterprise Hub—has assisted 19 such enterprises in the past year. Among these is the SE Factory code school, an initiative of The Nawaya Network, a local nongovernmental organization. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sefactory.io/&quot;&gt;SE Factory&lt;/a&gt; offers introductory and boot camp courses to train working-class young people on the technical and soft skills needed to get jobs in the tech industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-1&quot; title=&quot;SE Factory founders Zeina Saab and Fadi Bizri. Photo: SE Factory.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In less than three years, SE Factory graduated 59 students through its boot camp, and nearly all received job offers within six weeks. Their new employers include local tech startups, such as those participating in the FCO’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uklebhub.com/&quot;&gt;UK-Lebanon Tech Hub&lt;/a&gt; accelerator programmes, and regional tech companies. Early indications show SE Factory graduates earn higher salaries on average than they would have earned coming straight out of university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Grant Opens Door to Coding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, SE Factory was awarded a £30,000 cash grant from SoUK.LB, plus training and one-on-one mentorship to develop an introductory online course to supplement its in-person coding boot camps. SE Factory developed a pilot one-month pre-boot camp course—Foundation of Computer Science. Ten students new to coding graduated from the pre-boot camp and are now prepared for the full-time, three-month coding boot camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 20, visitors from the British Embassy of Beirut and the FCO Conflict, Stability and Security Fund (CSSF) attended the first Foundation of Computer Science graduation event. There, the visitors learned about SoUK.LB’s 18 other social enterprise grantees—including enterprises in health, agriculture, women’s economic empowerment, transportation, and other sectors. These grantees—competitively selected from 147 applicants—comprise idea and early-stage startups and established, growth-stage cross-sector organisations. Their missions are to create transformational social or environmental change whilst becoming financially sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early-Stage Grantee Wins First Place at Global Social Venture Competition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of SoUK.LB’s early-stage social enterprises won first place at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gsvc.org/&quot;&gt;Global Social Venture Competition&lt;/a&gt;, a premier business competition organized by the University of California at Berkeley. The winning team, FabricAID, competed with 550 applicants from 60 countries, with teams first passing through rounds of national and regional competitions. FabricAID created a new industry in Lebanon by more easily connecting buyers and sellers in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/richardkestenbaum/2017/04/11/fashion-retailers-have-to-adapt-to-deal-with-secondhand-clothes-sold-online/#4a468cbd1a7f&quot;&gt;multibillion-dollar&lt;/a&gt; second-hand clothing market. In the 10-year history of the competition, this is the first time a team from Lebanon reached the international finals.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-2&quot; title=&quot;FabricAID CEO Omar Itani accepting first prize at the Global Social Venture Competition finals in Milan, Italy.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Entrepreneur-Driven Social Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoUK.LB is demonstrating the viability of the small-enterprise model in Lebanon to achieve social and economic impact and potential scalability. This FCO flagship project addresses the challenges to both the supply of and demand for transformational and sustainable social and economic change in Lebanon. The investment harnesses the potential of the private sector to develop, incubate, and scale ideas that can catalyze positive change and shape the creation of a distinct social enterprise sector in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Select Results from the Lebanon Social Enterprise Pilot Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed recruitment campaign for social enterprises/innovators, resulting in 183 applicants for support in training, mentoring, and funding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of 147 eligible applicants, 48 percent were led by women, and 50 percent were ages 18–30.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awarded 19 grants to start-up and growth-stage organisations and provided training sessions to 52 of these grantees. Twelve of the grantees have begun generating sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disbursed £405,000 in grants. Grantees increased the number of beneficiaries they serve by 154 percent, and created 225 jobs covering full time, part time, and contractor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed market study on the social enterprises&amp;#39; operating environment, challenges, and opportunities and an overview of international best practices that can be adopted in Lebanon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaged policy makers in policy development discussions—including officials from the Ministry of Economy and Trade, Ministry of Finance, Banque du Liban, and Office of the President of the Council of Ministers.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By identifying, enabling, and sustaining Lebanon&amp;rsquo;s innovators and small social enterprises, SoUK.LB is transcending the traditional role of the grants-based challenge fund by enabling social enterprises too small for traditional financing to operate like businesses rather than development projects. It has also served to spotlight the unmet demand for such assistance, including in untapped markets outside of Beirut, where we are confident that similar assistance can succeed and ultimately benefit Lebanese communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New DFID Guidance Aims to Improve Emergency Schooling for Millions of Displaced Children</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-dfid-guidance-aims-to-improve-emergency-schooling-for-millions-of-displaced-children</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 14:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-dfid-guidance-aims-to-improve-emergency-schooling-for-millions-of-displaced-children</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An estimated 75 million children cannot go to school because they have been driven from their homes by war, crisis, and natural disaster. This deprivation in turn destabilizes vulnerable regions because uneducated children grow into at-risk teenagers and young adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To strengthen its education in emergencies (EiE) programming, the U.K. Department of International Development (DFID) drew on the DAI-led Expert Advisory Call Down service on resilience programming to research evidence on which interventions work to support high-quality schooling for displaced children—and where the evidence falls short. DAI consortium partner Cambridge Education led the research and produced six &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-expert-advisory-call-down-services-eacds-lot-b-strengthening-resilience-and-response-to-crises&quot;&gt;Evidence Briefs&lt;/a&gt; about EiE, focusing on quality and learning; protection and inclusion; cost-effective delivery; data, monitoring, and evaluation; political settlements; and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE1&quot; title=&quot;Syrian refugee children attend class at a makeshift school near the Syrian border on the outskirts of Mafraq, Jordan. Photo by AP/Muhammed Muheisen and Freedom House.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these briefs, the team compiled the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/EiE_Guidance_Note-8fc7f4.pdf&quot;&gt;Education in Emergencies Guidance Note&lt;/a&gt;. DFID encourages policy makers and development practitioners worldwide to consider this guidance and researchers to fill in the many knowledge gaps in this field. Here we share select observations from the briefs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Growing Need for Emergency Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violent conflicts tend to last longer today than in previous decades—26 years on average versus fewer than 10 years in 1970. These conflicts often involve non-state, regional, and global actors and are increasingly linked to complex global challenges such as climate change, natural disasters, and transnational organized crime. These protracted crises mean we are seeing more migrants, both within countries and across borders. Among those migrants, children and young adults are among the most affected.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protection and Inclusion—Ensuring Schools are Safe and Inclusive.&lt;/strong&gt; The team sought evidence on how to ensure formal and informal schools are safe spaces that protect children and welcome the vulnerable, particularly girls and the disabled. Distance to school is a major barrier for young children, girls, and children with disabilities. Strategies found to make schools safer and more accessible include chaperoned walking to school (Jordan) and recruiting village and female volunteers (Afghanistan). Tackling the effects of trauma emerged as another important theme—in Gaza, the Norwegian Refugee Council’s Better Learning Programme combined psychosocial and trauma-focused training for teachers and school counsellors. The programme significantly reduced nightmares for 70 percent of students and moderately reduced nightmares for 30 percent, with the improved wellbeing attributed to students’ improved enjoyment of school and increased level of effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data, Monitoring, and Evaluation—Understanding Change and Challenges.&lt;/strong&gt; There is consensus that better data is critical to understand the challenge of intervening at scale, to inform programming, monitor responses, and assess children’s access, attainment, and education pathways as their locations or circumstances change. For example, while an estimated 60 percent of the world&amp;rsquo;s 19.5 million refugees and 80 percent of its 34 million internally displaced persons (IDPs) live in urban environments, data on them is scarce. Many are not formally registered as refugees or IDPs, which limits the effectiveness of EiE because donors and United Nations projects typically do not fund programmes to educate unregistered refugees. The authors suggest revising assessment tools to better inform urban programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE6&quot; title=&quot;Teachers at a refugee camp in Rojava, Syria, lead students in exercise. Photo: Alberto Hugo Rojas.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality and Learning—Hurdles to Effective Emergency Teaching.&lt;/strong&gt; Both local and foreign teachers in emergency settings face unique challenges. While teacher quality is critical to learning quality, teachers who are refugees themselves—whether professional or recruited to fill gaps—often suffer from the same traumatic experiences, economic hardships, and unstable circumstances afflicting their students. Local-national teachers may have personal views on the conflict or crisis. On the other hand, well-meaning expatriates may have little or no experience in teaching or in crises. As a result, host-country teachers often take on increased class loads but are often not prepared to handle the psychosocial support needs of refugee students (or their expatriate colleagues). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effective Delivery—Creating Synergy of Efforts.&lt;/strong&gt; When it comes to delivering value for money, the team found that efforts to coordinate the separate funding streams of “first response” humanitarian relief and long-term development assistance have been ineffective. While humanitarian organizations can respond to crises in weeks or even days, their program funding typically lasts six months to one year and can vary year to year depending on priorities. In contrast, development programs tend to have consistent budgets over three to five years to achieve their goals, but can take more than one year to conceive, plan, and launch. Greater attention is required to finance, plan, and implement EiE assistance throughout education crises, which typically last for years and—for the children—multiple grade and learning levels. UNICEF’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.educationcannotwait.org/&quot;&gt;Education Cannot Wait&lt;/a&gt; fund, launched in 2016, was cited as a potential model for merging humanitarian and development activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE5&quot; title=&quot;Children of the Sheikh Misri refugee camp just south of Jalalabad, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Settlements—Knowing What is Feasible.&lt;/strong&gt; The research aimed to summarise what is known about establishing political consensus and coordinating government response to education emergencies (in various political contexts). There are few examples of “what works” in this area. One ongoing example comes from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-competitiveness-program-jcp&quot;&gt;Jordan Compact&lt;/a&gt; of 2016. Faced with an unprecedented influx of Syrian refugees, the Government of Jordan committed to schooling all Syrian refugee children in exchange for donor assistance to build more schools and address public service delivery and economic development. The Jordanian Ministry of Education reports that more than 126,000 Syrian refugee children had enrolled in school in host communities and camps for the 2016–2017 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE3&quot; title=&quot;Young students in Takegon, Aceh, Indonesia, following the 2004 Tsunami. Photo by Daniel Ziv.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability—Leveraging Local Commitment.&lt;/strong&gt; Providing EiE “should ideally be led by a national government, or aligned to national government policies or systems,” the authors write, because a locally led response is more sustainable and can also contribute to peacebuilding and national unity in the longer term. For example, in response to Typhoon Haiyan in 2013, the central Philippines government co-chaired the United Nations’ Education Cluster relief effort. The government-led approach was embedded within local Philippine government systems, where local actors employed their acute understanding of local needs and ways to organise. For example, they quickly identified alternative school spaces amid the destruction and inspected them for safety and suitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Systemic Solutions for Displaced Children&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, providing more stability for displaced children requires a long-term development approach, focused on inclusive economic growth and effective, legitimate institutions conducive to stability in fragile and conflict-affected states. This approach must include multi-year assistance in building systems for essential services such as education. If humanitarian, development, and peacebuilding actors can work in a more joined-up way to achieve education outcomes and ensure that EiE interventions are aligned as far as possible with national systems, the &lt;em&gt;Guidance Note&lt;/em&gt; suggests, they have a better chance of building resilient schools, supporting teachers, and providing a good education for displaced and refugee children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethiopia Stands Poised to Lead an African Industrial Revolution</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ethiopia-stands-poised-to-lead-an-african-industrial-revolution</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 17:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ethiopia-stands-poised-to-lead-an-african-industrial-revolution</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just over 100 years ago, Henry Ford and other industrialists revolutionised manufacturing by introducing the assembly line. They built consumer goods at unprecedented scale and cost, creating millions of jobs and bringing down the price of goods to levels that workers could afford. It was so productive that Ford could double the minimum wage and shorten the working day for his workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assembly line now spans the globe. Global brands manage hundreds of suppliers that manufacture their products in dozens of countries, particularly in Asia, which has served as the &amp;ldquo;world&amp;rsquo;s factory&amp;rdquo; for the past 30 years. However, as Asian wages rise and populations age, their workers have become more costly and choosy. This is prompting brands and manufacturers to turn to youthful and resource-rich Africa. Ethiopia has begun taking advantage, thanks in part to assistance from the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-private-enterprise-programme-ethiopia-pepe&quot;&gt;Enterprise Partners&lt;/a&gt; programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nebil-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nebil-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These multinationals are bringing to Africa knowledge and technologies, which African countries must be prepared to absorb. National governments need to reform as necessary to make their economies welcoming places to do business. Countries need to invest in industrial parks, transport hubs, and infrastructure to connect and support them, as well as in future workers. Ethiopia—which on April 2 seated a new prime minister, Abiy Ahmed—has already invested substantially and is well situated to reap the benefits. If Africa can create ecosystems where global value chains can thrive, the continent can gain ground on Asia in producing higher value goods and grow its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wto.org/english/res_e/statis_e/wts2016_e/wts2016_e.pdf&quot;&gt;share of global trade&lt;/a&gt;, currently at 2 percent compared with Asia&amp;rsquo;s 34 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nebil-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nebil-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2016: Clothing Giants Stake Their Claim&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Phillips-Van Heusen Corporation, commonly known as PVH, is a company with $8 billion in annual revenues generated by brands that include Calvin Klein and Tommy Hilfiger. PVH—among other garment giants, including H&amp;amp;M and Vanity Fair—was an early mover into Ethiopia, choosing the lakeside city of Hawassa as its production base due to the area&amp;rsquo;s abundant labour force. PVH moved fast, bringing in some of its top Asian manufacturers to invest. At the same time, the Ethiopian government financed and built a world-class industrial park focusing on garments manufacturing and completing it within nine months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;We have started up in Bangladesh. We have started up in China. We really have been ahead of the curve. Ethiopia, or East Africa in general, is significantly ahead of where those other countries were at their respective time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; —Manny Chirico, Chairman and CEO of Phillips-Van Heusen Corporation &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nebil-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nebil-4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hawassa Industrial Park &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/development-secretary-priti-patel-stresses-economic-growth-in-visit-to-ethiopia-industrial-park&quot;&gt;opened for business&lt;/a&gt; in July 2016. Production and exports have since commenced with 15,000 people hired and trained to work. Employers are hiring 100 young people per day to join the lines through a central recruitment and training platform, which was established through a joint effort by the federal and regional governments, PVH, the factories, and Enterprise Partners. The park is projected to create 60,000 jobs mostly for youth and women in coming years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To absorb the influx of workers from the surrounding countryside, the city of Hawassa is helping its property owners build affordable rooms and facilities on their plots through an innovative housing-microfinance scheme. More than 500 rooms—enough for 2,000 workers—have been built so far, enabling the mostly female migrant workforce to integrate into the existing community. The new arrivals are adjusting and settling into their new urban and industrial environments with help from special training in soft skills—such as work ethic, teamwork, and women&amp;rsquo;s empowerment—facilitated by Enterprise Partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawassa&amp;rsquo;s business community is reaping rewards with noticeable increases already in retail sales and new investment. A virtuous circle is in motion—the success of the Hawassa Industrial Park has emboldened Ethiopian officials to ramp up construction of more parks with Hawassa as their model. Two more multimillion-dollar parks, in Mekelle and Kombolcha, recently opened and 10 more are in development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nebil-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nebil-5&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ethiopia&amp;rsquo;s Investment Paying Off&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investment promises to herald a new era for Ethiopia, creating jobs and building skills for young people, 2 million of whom will need employment to achieve the Government&amp;rsquo;s ambitious Growth and Transformation Plan. The garments sector alone is targeting $30 billion in annual exports by 2030. This kind of growth would lead to the creation of thousands of small businesses and offer the farming community access to new markets, potentially triggering a much-needed transformation of the economic base away from rain-dependent agriculture toward a globally connected industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this juncture though, Africans should ask one critical question: &lt;em&gt;How will industry make our lives better?&lt;/em&gt; This is where learning from Asia&amp;rsquo;s experiences is critical to ensure that any industry is socially and environmentally sustainable. The vision is to create an industrial revolution that Africa will want to keep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nebil-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nebil-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Ethiopia has invested heavily in education, going from three universities and three technical colleges 25 years ago to 35 universities and 600 colleges today—thereby ensuring a labour force commensurate with its industrializing society and competitive in the international economy. The country is also making good progress toward developing its 40 gigawatts of clean energy potential—mostly hydropower, but also wind and geothermal power—to supply its factories with affordable and stable energy as well as help power its East African neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goods also need to be moved quickly and cost-effectively by plane, train, or truck. Ethiopia has progressed tremendously in paving rural roads and intercity expressways, which will help link the agricultural and industrial sectors. Multiple rail lines to Djibouti are being completed, halving existing times to port. And as speed to market becomes ever more critical in the age of e-commerce, Ethiopian Airlines will become a strategic asset for the garment industry as it already is for cut-flower exports. As Africa&amp;rsquo;s largest carrier, the airline already connects 56 African cities with more than 100 cities across the globe with nearly 2,000 takeoffs and touchdowns per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;Enterprise Partners is the major component of the Private Enterprise Programme Ethiopia (PEPE), a seven-year programme under the U.K. Department for International Development. PEPE has three components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://enterprisepartners.org/&quot;&gt;Enterprise Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which implements DAI’s market systems development approach in three priority sectors of the Government of Ethiopia—garments, leather, and horticulture. The team has launched more than 50 interventions to address constraints in the agro-industrial and finance sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://the-ecf.com/&quot;&gt;Ethiopian Competitiveness Facility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a challenge fund managed by the Government of Ethiopia aimed at improving the competitiveness of the private sector by providing matched grants to enable firms to access business development services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;iati.dfid.gov.uk/iati_documents/5619008.odt&quot;&gt;Multi-Donor Initiative (MDI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, implemented by the International Finance Corporation (IFC), which implements the Ethiopia Investment Climate Programme (EICP) to improve the business environment. IFC’s approach combines analysis-led diagnostics with in-country local expertise and global expertise, working closely with government.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nebil-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nebil-6&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;An Opportunity at Hand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The International Monetary Fund &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imf.org/external/datamapper/NGDP_RPCH@WEO/OEMDC/ADVEC/WEOWORLD/ETH&quot;&gt;predicts&lt;/a&gt; that Ethiopia will continue as East Africa’s fastest-growing economy, with East Africa the continent’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.un.org/en/development/desa/population/theme/urbanization/index.shtml&quot;&gt;fastest-urbanizing region&lt;/a&gt;. As Africa&amp;rsquo;s marketplace grows, improved regional relationships will become increasingly necessary to ensure neighboring countries can trade and create wealth with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Africa’s economy offers room to grow in many sectors, including finance, infrastructure/logistics, and information and communication technology, to name a few. Growth in these sectors will enhance the continent’s global role in the new, increasingly automated industrial revolution. As the nature of workforces evolves, Ethiopia stands poised to address emerging needs and fill the demand for manufactured goods. More broadly, an opportunity is at hand for Africa to become the go-to source for advanced and sustainable manufacturing in the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Young Rural Women are Crucial to Advancing Universal Health Coverage in Northern Nigeria</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/young-rural-women-are-crucial-to-advancing-universal-health-coverage-in-northern-nigeria</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 17:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/young-rural-women-are-crucial-to-advancing-universal-health-coverage-in-northern-nigeria</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/campaigns/world-health-day/2018/en/&quot;&gt;World Health Day&lt;/a&gt; theme is Universal Health Coverage. It’s an apt rallying cry, particularly for those working in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-women-for-health-w4h&quot;&gt;Women for Health (W4H) programme&lt;/a&gt; in Northern Nigeria, where a &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0069569&quot;&gt;2013 study&lt;/a&gt; showed that 94 percent of live births lacked any medical personnel presence, resulting in one of the highest maternal mortality rates in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, when the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID) launched W4H, we found a chronic shortage of female health workers converged with social, cultural, and religious norms, that severely limited women’s access to health care and produced some of the poorest maternal and newborn health indicators in sub-Saharan Africa. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr293/fr293.pdf&quot;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; Nigerian health workforce density is 1.95 per 1,000 people, far below the African average of 2.9 per 1,000. The situation was most severe in rural areas where deliveries were three times less likely than those in urban areas to be attended by a skilled birth attendant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various government strategies undertaken to deploy midwives from urban areas or from the south of the country to rural areas had &lt;a href=&quot;https://bmchealthservres.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12913-016-1688-8&quot;&gt;limited success&lt;/a&gt;, often because of the religious and socio-cultural differences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this context, a one-size-fits-all solution rarely works. The specific situation and needs of the women and their families must be taken into account and the health service designed around them. This was particularly important in Yobe state where conflict and insurgency created unique challenges for health training and women’s access to services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/training-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;training-1&quot; title=&quot;W4H trains women who live in the communities where they provide health services.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Tailored Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and social care is labour intensive and must be tailored to people’s needs if it is to be effective. It is now &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/hrh/resources/WHO-HLC-Report_web.pdf&quot;&gt;widely recognized&lt;/a&gt; that human resources for health is a key enabler for the attainment of universal health coverage. In response to the challenge, the W4H team recruited women already residing in the rural North for training so they would return to their communities to provide culturally appropriate health services for girls and women. We worked with 20 health training institutions in five northern states. We created Foundation Year Programmes in each state, where young women from rural areas with a foundation in basic science subjects and life skills upgraded their academic skills so that they could successfully enter professional midwifery, nursing, and community health careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the existing health training institutions, the environment was predominantly male with few female tutors and very few, if any, in decision-making positions. Most of the facilities were unsuitable for female students, especially married females. The W4H team improved the gender responsiveness of the institutions by providing gender training for staff, constructing female-friendly accommodations, improving security, providing academic and psycho-social counseling, providing child care facilities, and increasing the proportion of female tutors and managers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Improved Access&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve women’s access to health care services in rural areas, it became clear that we must support the training of health workers who would understand, appreciate, and respect women in rural communities. The need to support communities to produce their own health workers was imperative considering that 39 percent of women in the northwest stated they had serious problems accessing care due to a lack of female providers. This was particularly important where social norms prohibited women from receiving care from male health workers, a common situation in rural areas of northern Nigeria. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one W4H study, a community leader in Katsina was quoted saying: “I visited a health facility in this community where a male health worker was attending to a woman after delivery. There was a lot of intimacy in the process, which is not acceptable in our culture and in our religion. That was when I decided my wife will never give birth in these facilities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, 110 young rural women have now graduated to become midwives, nurses and community health workers from the health training institutions and are now not only providing health care services to their communities during working hours, but their services are accessible for their communities 24 hours a day and seven days a week. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/At%20graduation%20Devs.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At graduation Devs&quot; title=&quot;Graduates are now actively providing care in their communities and in some cases, becoming role models for others.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One graduate from Kano state said, “I was inspired into this profession because of difficulties my people are facing over the years when it comes to child delivery…Since I joined the programme I have become a local champion with many young girls looking up to me as their role model, they always see me as their saviour, meeting me at home, morning and night, for advices and services.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The availability of health workers working in their own communities ensures better communication between service providers and health service seekers. It also ensures that rural women receive services with dignity and will not have to travel distance to access such services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Transforming Norms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the programme has begun a gradual process of attitudinal change in rural communities about girls’ education and women as professionals. Some men in Zamfara state have changed their minds about antenatal issues. “With women health workers around, we feel at ease to send our wives for antenatal care,” said Ibrahim Tanimu. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issues relating to women’s roles and relationships can be extremely sensitive, particularly in the complex, religious, political, and social structures of northern Nigeria. Effective engagement in this context is not simple, and entry points and strategies had to be sensitively honed to local situations. Extensive consultations and meetings were held at national and state levels with opinion leaders, gatekeepers, and policy makers, to promote the rationale for, and benefits of, the programme and the role each stakeholder could play in resolving the human resource and maternal mortality challenges. Without this buy-in and ownership, the programme would have been extremely difficult to implement and there would be very little chance of embedding it within the existing system and sustaining the initiative in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also engaged with religious leaders and identified key messages from religious texts that emphasised the importance of women working to save lives, and together we formulated messages to reach rural communities. They also advised us on the best ways to reach the communities and helped the programme to do this through religious institutions such as the Hisbah board, the State Ministry of Religious Affairs, and the Council of Ulammas, using platforms such as the Ramadan Tafsir sermons and seminars and conferences organised to celebrate the Islamic calendar. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Crafting Policy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W4H also worked to establish gender-equality-enabling legal and regulatory frameworks, policy, and protocols by engaging with state legislators to secure financing for the Foundation Year Programme and to establish policies and laws to ensure its sustainable implementation in the states.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Legislators.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Legislators&quot; title=&quot;Yobe and Katsina legislators in an interactive session.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 2017, 6,750 women had received training as health workers and the first group of Foundation Year Programme students who studied midwifery, nursing, and community health finished their training. Some have already gained employment in rural communities; others are volunteering in their own communities and local health centres and hospitals while awaiting deployment. Their commitment to providing health services in underserved areas and their determination to improve the health outcomes for women and children is very apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$36 Million Investment Partnership Finances Warehouses in Malawi to Improve Food Security</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/36-million-investment-facility-finances-warehouses-in-malawi-to-improve-food-security</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2018 15:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/36-million-investment-facility-finances-warehouses-in-malawi-to-improve-food-security</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Malawi has suffered from poor food production for decades—its 17 million people are mostly smallholder or subsistence farmers who have struggled to overcome drought, pests, and outdated farming practices. Even successful harvests are diminished because they have few options to process and store their crops for sale, resulting in post-harvest losses that cut deeply into already small profits. But development assistance from the United States and European Union is helping Malawi address its shortage of warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Agency for International Development&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; (the Hub) brought together the European Investment Bank, National Bank of Malawi, and the Agricultural Commodities Exchange for Africa to develop a first-of-its-kind Agricultural Storage Investment Facility (ASIF). Through ASIF, the European Investment Bank is channeling a credit line of €30 million (approximately $36 million) through National Bank for on-lending to seven Malawian agribusinesses to build more than 200,000 metric tons of new storage capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, National Bank has loaned $12 million to four warehouse operators to build 100,000 metric tons of new storage, benefiting agribusinesses and—notably—potentially thousands of farmers. The Hub and its partners expect the remaining $24 million to be utilized over the next 18 months. The Hub will also support integrating these facilities into Malawi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/SATIH%20Infographic.pdf&quot;&gt;Warehouse Receipt System&lt;/a&gt;, which enables farmers to borrow money against their stock of warehoused crops to buy seed, fertilizer, and household necessities. Warehouse and grain silo operators such as Rab Processors and CP Feeds have already added more than 200 jobs after receiving financing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Hub played an integral role in supporting National Bank to bring the ASIF to market,” said Harold Jiya, National Bank’s Director of Wholesale Banking. “By bringing these new sources of ﬁnance into Malawi, we are now able to ﬁnance important long-term investments that our clients highly value.&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/gS1JZtUhQtFajjLKHzZa&quot; title=&quot;Malawi Agricultural Storage Investment Facility &quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?Pyq&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Developing the Finance Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To develop the ASIF, the Hub team convened international ﬁnanciers, agribusiness and farmer organizations, and other stakeholders. The Hub assisted in developing the instrument, building the financing pipeline, bringing in investors, coordinating investment appraisals by both the European Investment Bank and National Bank, and supporting transactions as they progressed through the approval process. The Hub is also supporting the Agricultural Commodities Exchange to integrate the new warehouses into its system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Storage bottlenecks have hindered Malawian smallholder producers from realizing returns on their activities,” said Kristian Schach Moller, CEO of the Exchange. “The Hub&amp;rsquo;s [ASIF] initiative is helping to overcome those bottlenecks.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malawi and other countries in southern and eastern Africa have increasingly endured drought conditions and crop-devastating infestation of pests such as Fall Armyworms. While these countries have historically turned to food relief programs to survive, they aspire to solve their food issues through trade, investment, and agricultural technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Storage facilities such as the ones receiving ASIF financing reduce post-harvest losses by controlling the temperature, shade, and humidity so harvested crops last longer and farmers can sell more of their harvests in the off-season, often for a better price than when they are desperate to sell expiring goods to opportunistic traders. In addition to staple crops such as maize, other grains, pulses, and legumes, high-value crops such as tomatoes, peppers, and fruit can also be stored in these warehouses for short periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SATIH-EIB-Malawi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SATIH-EIB-Malawi&quot; title=&quot;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub officials meet at Rab Processors in Lilongwe.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mobilizing Local Investment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To borrow money from ASIF, warehouse entrepreneurs must put up their own capital as well as present well-articulated business plans. The four facilities built or expanded so far under ASIF are in and around Lilongwe and Blantyre, locations chosen to best serve farmers, cooperatives, traders, and transporters. Other warehouses are planned for locations such as Kasungu and Mchinji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASIF is part of a trend of financing facilities that use European Union financing to generate local investment in areas such as energy efficiency in Eastern Europe and private sector engagement in at-risk countries. In Malawi, there is confidence that the ASIF will help farmers and others in Malawian agricultural value chains to earn more income—as well as serve as a model for agricultural storage investment facilities in other countries that rely on smallholder farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LTA Program Shows Benefit of Truly Participatory Approach</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lta-program-shows-benefit-of-truly-participatory-approach</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 14:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lta-program-shows-benefit-of-truly-participatory-approach</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/tanzania-feed-future-tanzania-land-tenure-assistance-lta&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Land Tenure Assistance&lt;/a&gt; (LTA) activity—which has completed mapping of more than 36,000 land parcels in 26 villages with more than 27,000 Certificates of Customary Rights of Occupancy printed and registered—is a powerful example of how digital technology applied in a participatory process can enable rural people to strengthen their land rights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demarcation and mapping facilitated by the Mobile Application for Secure Tenure (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MASTUSAID&quot;&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt;) has increased the speed of registration and certificate issuance, reduced costs, and engaged young people in a way that has led to wide acceptance of the program and prompted calls by government, donors, and other development agencies to implement the program nationally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Agency for International Development’s LTA program is moving the needle on land registration and security in a country where less than 10 percent of individually owned land is registered. And there are encouraging signs that this expansion of formal land titling is beginning to translate into income gains. Both women and men, for example, have been able to use their new CCROs to secure loans enabling them to invest in their land holdings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Residents Included—From Start to Finish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the moment the program is introduced to a village council to the issuing of the last CCRO, residents of each village are fully and directly involved in the registration process. Residents, for example, serve on Village Land and Adjudication Committees and the Village Land Use Planning Committees. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mpl.ird.fr/crea/taller-colombia/FAO/AGLL/pdfdocs/tanzania.pdf&quot;&gt;participatory rural appraisal approach&lt;/a&gt; is used to draft and approve &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/templates/nr/kagera/Documents/PES_workshop_August2011/Day1/LAND_USE_PLANNING_AND_LAND_TENURE_IN_TANZANIA.pdf&quot;&gt;Village Land Use Plans&lt;/a&gt;, which ensure that land parcels are not allocated and registered across village boundaries or in wetlands, and that corridors are set aside for pastoralists to move their cattle. These issues sometimes require negotiation and agreement between parties with competing interests but have to date been amicably resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DSCN8551.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;DSCN8551&quot; title=&quot;A representative of a Masai pastoralist community participating in the Village Land Use Planning process in Makuka Village, Tanzania&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents also participate directly in the digital capture of land parcel data. They are invited to volunteer for one-week adjudicator and para-surveyor training in the use of MAST for land demarcation. Those who pass the course accompany the Adjudication Committee members, LTA staff, and District Land Office representatives to demarcate the boundaries of every land claim in the presence of neighboring claimants. They capture the GPS coordinates of the parcel boundaries using MAST on a smartphone or tablet, together with a GPS enhancer for greater accuracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents are trained in  the registration process, as well as educated on their &lt;a href=&quot;http://extwprlegs1.fao.org/docs/pdf/tan23795.pdf&quot;&gt;land rights&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://extwprlegs1.fao.org/docs/pdf/tan53306.pdf&quot;&gt;legislation&lt;/a&gt; governing land tenure. These learning sessions take place at the Village Assembly, at hamlet-level meetings, at special meetings for women, and at schools. Participants are educated about the type of occupation which may be most suitable to protect their interests and informed about the right of women to have CCROs registered in their names as single occupants, as joint tenants, or as tenants in common with their husbands. Tanzanian law enshrines women’s right to occupy land. The number of claimants to date is close to equal between men (52 percent) and women (48 percent). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After claimants have been identified and parcel boundaries recorded, maps are produced for public display for two weeks at the Village Council office. During this period, residents inspect the maps and confirm their claims or raise objections and corrections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_ae8ab2f6-e786-4a83-b8ba-db686285a1bc&quot; title=&quot;LTA Results To Date&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?05u&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Increased Efficiencies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTA has greatly streamlined and automated the printing and processing of CCROs to increase speed and reduce costs. Up to 500 CCROs can be printed each day by a small team of District Land Office staff. Registered CCROs are returned to the Village Council, which retains hard copies in Village Registry Offices refurbished with LTA assistance to provide secure storage. Issuance &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/more-than-500-rural-tanzanians-now-have-land-titles&quot;&gt;ceremonies&lt;/a&gt; celebrate the claimants receiving their CCROs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high level of participation by residents and village leaders has proved to be invaluable in reducing disputes over boundaries, resolving intra-family disputes, and resolving land use planning conflicts. Disputes referred to the dispute resolution process make up less than 0.02 percent of all land parcels demarcated to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involvement by district-level government officials at all stages of the program has resulted in District Land Office staff being fully engaged with the program and capable of conducting public outreach meetings, capturing and correcting the data, printing and registering the CCROs, and leading issuance ceremonies with ever-decreasing supervision by LTA. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, the program has been well received by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://landportal.org/organization/ministry-lands-housing-and-human-settlements-development-tanzania&quot;&gt;Ministry of Land Housing and Human Settlements Development&lt;/a&gt;, which recently moved to implement MAST and the processes used by LTA on other donor- and government-funded land registration programs. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aru.ac.tz/&quot;&gt;Ardhi University&lt;/a&gt; is collaborating with LTA to use its processes and MAST for its practical training of students and has asked DAI to provide technical assistance and set up an internship program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mozambique: Even a Progressive Land Law Needs Revision After a Generation of Experience</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/mozambique-even-a-progressive-land-law-needs-revision-after-a-generation-of-experience</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/mozambique-even-a-progressive-land-law-needs-revision-after-a-generation-of-experience</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mozambique is widely regarded as having a modern and progressive land tenure framework, following the enactment of the 1997 Land Law. However, in its implementation, the law has not always lived up to its promise. Twenty years of experience reveals a number of areas in which the legal framework would benefit from revision and better serve its primary aims of promoting productive land use while protecting legitimate customary and smallholder land rights.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As demand for access to agricultural land increases—whether from national investors, international conglomerates, or just a local smallholder wishing to increase the size of his or her farm—the pressure for clarity and transparency in land administration has grown accordingly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full privatization of land remains politically unacceptable, but other topics once off-limits—for example, loosening the restrictions on land rights transfers in rural areas—are now openly discussed in the press and at the government-led Land Consultative Forum. The time is right to address this and other weaknesses in the legal framework and thereby catalyze investment, increase productivity, and enhance transparency in land administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues were also openly discussed and debated more recently at the private sector-sponsored 15th Conferência Anual do Sector Privado (CASP) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dais-ian-rose-on-legal-reform-in-the-land-sector&quot;&gt;held on March 12&lt;/a&gt;, during which the DAI presented in front of an audience including Prime Minister Carlos Agostinho do Rosário, Minister of Land and Rural Development Celso Correia, and Minister of Industry and Commerce Ragendra Berta de Sousa. The conference was widely covered in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/SAVANA%201262.pdf&quot;&gt;Mozambican press&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The donor community is poised to provide technical assistance based on best practices from relevant contexts, and the Mozambican government has indicated its willingness to engage in a multistakeholder participatory reform process. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-support-program-economic-and-enterprise-development-speed&quot;&gt;Supporting the Policy Environment for Economic Development (SPEED+)&lt;/a&gt; project, implemented by DAI and funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development, is in discussions with the Mozambican government on how best to support reforms, with the National Land Directorate (DINAT) signaling its preliminary agreement with several recommendations already being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Keep It Simple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informed by extensive stakeholder discussions and economic analysis, SPEED+ is working on the premise that increasing transparency and simplifying the procedures for acquiring and transferring secure leasehold access to land via DUATs (&lt;em&gt;Direito de Uso e Aproveimento de Terra&lt;/em&gt;, or Land Use and Benefit Right) will lead to a higher volume of transactions, with more of these transactions brought into the formal registration process. A more fluid environment for transactions will eventually lead to a more market-oriented allocation of land rights, with the legal framework—engaged rather than skirted—protecting the rights of the most vulnerable. In turn, a more efficient allocation of land rights means that land will flow to those people and enterprises with the capacity and capital to put the land to more productive use. Increased investment will lead to greater productivity and economic growth, primarily in agriculture but also in sectors—such as housing or light industry—that require secure access to land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the government in February 2018 launched a National Land Audit Campaign to revoke DUATs from people or enterprises that were not putting their land to productive use. We believe that a more market-oriented legal framework could accomplish similar goals more efficiently and cheaply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking, all land in Mozambique is owned by the state, held in trust for the people to be managed for their benefit. Citizens, foreigners, and corporate entities may acquire DUAT rights in various ways. Essentially leaseholds granted or recognized by the state, DUATs run for varying periods of time (the length of a DUAT&amp;rsquo;s validity depends on a number of factors and can even be of indefinite duration under certain circumstances). Technical ownership of the land by the state is not a constraint to secure tenure or a more fluid land market (or its functional land rental equivalent). Rather, constraints arise due to partial restrictions on DUAT transferability and to inefficiencies in land administration that lead to actual and perceived weak title or insecure tenure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mozambique can therefore make significant strides toward promoting increased investment in land by revising the current legal framework but leaving the fundamental premise of the 1997 Land Law—the state&amp;rsquo;s unequivocal ownership of all land—untouched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/moz%20ag%20land%202.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;moz ag land 2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Change for the Better&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In analyzing the policy environment for land-based investments, SPEED+ has organized its recommendations around four investor-driven criteria for secure access to land:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certainty and Transparency &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protection of Investment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community Consent and Participation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sustainable Land Administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If concerns in these areas can be adequately addressed, then the investor can appropriately focus on its core business: determining market demand, putting the land into production, and supplying product to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Certainty and Transparency&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investor strives to reduce unknown risk to the extent possible: the &amp;ldquo;rules of the game&amp;rdquo; should be known to all players and should be enforced in a consistent manner. Our recommendations to increase certainty and transparency can be summarized as follows: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue official technical norms for DUAT acquisition, addressing both government-sponsored mass title regularization as well as privately initiated DUAT applications. The most recent official norms date back to 1989 and are obsolete in many aspects. This has led inevitably to inconsistency in the way cadaster services are implemented across the country, posing risk for the investor. Proposed norms cover both urban and rural contexts and clarify such issues as accuracy requirements for surveys, eligibility for free registration under state-initiated regularization programs, appropriate use of spatial technology, and when the need for physical &amp;ldquo;marcos&amp;rdquo; (expensive concrete boundary markers) may be waived. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant the public online access to land use planning instruments and to cadastral data. Privacy concerns have complicated the public dissemination of cadastral data online. One approach would be to authorize online secured read-only access via the digital registry of the geographic borders of all DUATs with the names of the holders, but without any further personal information. A more cautious approach might be to withhold names (but not the geographic information) of private individuals, but not of corporate holdings. Transparency of land rights data should reduce multiple sales (or attempted sales) of the same property.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish accurate Land Use Plans. The current inventory should be analyzed to determine which plans are not outdated. Plans deemed useful and relevant should be geo-referenced accurately and published online. This step should presumably be uncontroversial, given the absence of privacy concerns and the state&amp;rsquo;s clear interest in widespread dissemination of such plans. Better access to the plans should reduce unwelcome surprises when a purchaser learns it cannot implement the project it had in mind. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Protection of Investment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are to invest in the land, potential investors need confidence about the following issues: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability, if necessary, to recoup their investment by selling improvements on the land (in buildings, irrigation infrastructure, planted crops, and so on). In practical terms, their ability to sell such improvements—that is, the attractiveness of the transaction to a buyer—depends on the seller&amp;rsquo;s ability to transfer the underlying DUAT to the buyer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility to transfer use rights over part of their granted DUAT (that is, their ability to subdivide the DUAT).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility to change development plans (wholly or partially), within reason and without excessive fear of DUAT revocation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protection against expropriation without just compensation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarity on compensation and resettlement guidelines for occupants of land earmarked for development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to challenge arbitrary or arguably &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;illegal&amp;rdquo; acts in a timely fashion (in court or via alternative dispute mechanisms).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key constraint affecting all these issues is the current restriction on the transferability of land use rights in rural areas. In rural settings, transfer is possible but subject to a high degree of local government discretion. By contrast, transferability of land use rights of developed urban land is less problematic, since the legal framework provides for what amounts to a nearly automatic transfer of a DUAT—that is, with minimal government discretion—when an improvement on that land is sold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors need to know that if they are running short on capital mid-way through a project, the improvements and DUATs can be sold and transferred to another interested party. There are many examples in Mozambique of &amp;ldquo;abandoned&amp;rdquo; improvements (which ultimately revert to the state if the DUAT is revoked), but it is not clear if they would have been abandoned if the DUAT transfer procedures (or DUAT partition procedures) in rural areas were automatic or at least less discretionary. SPEED+ will draft proposals to make the transfer of rural land rights more similar to urban land rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state&amp;rsquo;s ability to revoke DUATs is another area that would benefit from revision. DUAT-holders are at risk of losing their leasehold rights if they are in violation of their development plan. Once again, the standards for when a DUAT-holder is in violation vary among the provinces, with opportunities for rent-seeking resulting from the discretionary power of government officials. While the state surely has a legitimate interest in how land is used, these interests can be served in many instances by greater attention to, and enforcement of, district land use plans. SPEED+ seeks to clarify the criteria for DUAT revocation as well as make development regulations more flexible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Community Consent and Participation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most critical issues for investor confidence and security, as well as for the protection of community members&amp;#39; land rights, remains the mechanism for community consent. The Land Law anticipated that the mechanisms of representation of local communities with respect to land rights would be defined by the enactment of future legal instruments to regulate such procedures. However, no such law has ever been enacted. There has been some guidance as to the procedures for conducting a community consultation within the context of awarding a DUAT to a third party on land that may affect or involve community land, and there is guidance on the process by which a community delimits its land. Strictly speaking, these are two different processes, though in reality they may often occur at the same time, and the differing guidelines may create confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The procedures for community consultation and community land delimitation should be harmonized, and procedures should also be clarified for the community to become a legal entity capable, for example, of opening a bank account and receiving funds to which it is entitled (either because of contracts with outside investors, or via the percentage of mining, forestry, and tourism-related fees it is entitled to under those corresponding laws). Banks have been known to refuse to open accounts for communities, insisting the legal framework is not sufficiently explicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that consultations must be genuinely participatory and foster informed consent. Informed and effective consent by the local community to a proposed project is not only a protection for members of the local communities—it&amp;rsquo;s also a protection for the investor who does not want to see an initial investment of time, money, and effort wasted if, at a later time, disaffected members of the community object to the project and successfully pressure community leaders or the state to cancel the contract, citing insufficient consultation. In short, hasty and incomplete &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/to-realize-the-promise-of-renewables-address-the-concerns-of-local-people/&quot;&gt;community consent&lt;/a&gt;, as well as one-sided negotiations, may backfire later in the form of community opposition. SPEED+ is reviewing the relevant legislation to ensure the protection of community rights with an approach that will not deter investors but rather attract investors who wish to conduct business in a more defined, predictable, and transparent environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4. Sustainable Land Administration&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Mozambique is to provide an attractive venue for increased land-based investment, then it must perform its land administration functions in a sustainable fashion. This includes maintaining its digital cadaster database, as well as staffing district, provincial, and national positions with sufficient numbers of well-trained staff. Unfortunately, these government offices have not been given sufficient human and physical resources to run the land administration services at the optimum level, and the demands will only increase—for example, as greater numbers of parcels enter the formal system via the government&amp;rsquo;s massive &amp;ldquo;Terra Segura&amp;rdquo; titling program, and as foreign investors continue to look to Mozambique for opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, increased formalization of land rights does hold out the promise of greater revenue opportunities. Increased land-based taxes and fees are a natural source of funds to help sustain Mozambique&amp;rsquo;s land administration services while also discouraging idle land. We recommend efforts to: (a) increase collection rates; and (b) increase tax rates, with an assessment base tailored more proportionately to &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; or market-oriented values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mozambique legal framework already exempts the great majority of parcels from the DUAT tax because they fall under the category of &amp;ldquo;family use&amp;rdquo; or because the DUAT-holders are local communities or members of local communities. As a first step, Mozambique would benefit from more clearly defining the exemption categories with an eye toward limiting the exemption to subsistence farming households and the urban poor. Although the philosophy of generous tax exemptions may originally have been conceived to guarantee universal access to land for productive use, the impact of the generous exemptions appears to have the contrary result—namely, the lack of a disincentive to leave the land unproductive. Of course, due attention must be given to avoiding the other extreme, in which overly burdensome taxes push transactions back into the informal sphere and pose undue hardships on vulnerable households and populations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Moz%20image%20copy.png&quot; alt=&quot;Moz image copy&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When is the Right Time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current administration, soon after the 2014 general elections, emphasized secure land tenure as one of its priorities. In April 2015, President Nyusi himself launched the Terra Segura program, which promised to issue 5 million DUAT titles in five years. Although it does not demonstrate political will for legal reform per se, the program provides a window of opportunity to push forward a land sector reform agenda that can assist in streamlining the legal framework to facilitate more fluid acquisitions and transfers of rural land DUATs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the goals of Terra Segura lend critical weight to the argument that a stable and reliable digital cadaster must be maintained. The registration of 5 million DUATs will mean little unless the cadaster is maintained with up-to-date information, such as changes in DUAT titleholders due to death, marriage, divorce, transfers, expiration, revocation, and other modifications. The advent of Terra Segura underscores the need to adopt measures to maintain the integrity of the digital cadaster database, as well as the recommendations related to reforming the land tax revenue base, given that the enormous influx of formal titles into the cadaster system will require a much higher volume and level of services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more explicit expression of the political will for reform was made by the Land and Rural Development Minister Celso Correia at the national land forum in November 2017, which closed with a formal commitment to make a targeted revision of the Land Law (albeit one that leaves some issues—such as full privatization of real property—unequivocally off the table for the time being). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the level of DINAT, the openness to reform is a mix of outward cautiousness regarding donors while, at the same time, internal preparations are underway to consider a vast range of reforms, including not only changes to regulatory instruments but also amendments to the 1997 Land Law itself. In fact, DINAT has prepared a list of approximately 40 legal instruments in need of revision (or in some cases creation). Although the list may be ambitious, it certainly reflects the realization within DINAT of the need for reform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the lower levels of bureaucracy, there is a predictable mix of openness and resistance to change. In project visits to local cadaster offices, we encountered some directors committed to the integrity of the new digital database and others who retain paper-based procedures, perhaps intentionally opting for opacity over transparency. However, previously taboo subjects—such as the sale (not just &amp;ldquo;transfer&amp;rdquo;) of DUATs—are now openly advocated by some university faculty. The existence of an informal rural land market is now widely acknowledged, and there is a growing understanding that bringing these informal transactions into the formal sector can increase tax and fee revenues to the state, as well as provide more security to smallholders wishing to consolidate and grow their businesses. The demand for formal title among communities and smallholders is also growing as external investors insist on formal title (or at least some assurance of land rights) in out-grower schemes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite what appears to be a gathering consensus for reform, some pockets of resistance should be expected. For example, the reduction of procedural discretion (and corresponding process simplification) will reduce rent-seeking opportunities enjoyed by some cadastral officials. In addition, it is still widely mentioned that an element of the political elite prefers a lack of transparency in land transactions such that deals favorable to these elites, that might not survive public scrutiny, can be cut in relative secrecy. Nevertheless, the bulk of investors, and particularly foreign investors, welcome more transparency as a precondition for expanding opportunities throughout the provinces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Nigeria, Governance Champions Can Transform Resource Wealth into Development Results</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/in-nigeria-governance-champions-can-transform-resource-wealth-into-development-results</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/in-nigeria-governance-champions-can-transform-resource-wealth-into-development-results</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nigeria is well known for its glaring inequalities, particularly the disparity between the impoverished northern states and its oil-rich south. This disparity covers more than just wealth and economic growth, as large segments of the country’s 185 million people want for simple stability and basic public services. But just as Nigeria’s economy is powered by more than oil, so the country’s inequities stem from more than just the so-called “resource curse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nigeria’s oil industry is the largest in Africa, in 2016 it represented only 8.4 percent of the country’s overall gross domestic product (GDP). Non-oil exports have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailytrust.com.ng/nigeria-records-rise-in-non-oil-export.html&quot;&gt;continued to rise&lt;/a&gt;, with total exports increasing by 73.5 percent in the second quarter of 2017 year-over-year, according to Nigeria’s National Bureau of Statistics, driven largely by economic diversification efforts focusing on agricultural goods. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/willem-buiter-3g-countries-2011-2?slop=1#nigeria-8&quot;&gt;2011 Citigroup report&lt;/a&gt; suggests Nigeria will achieve the highest average growth in GDP in the world between 2010 and 2050, and Nigeria already has the largest economy in Africa—surpassing South Africa in 2014. We would do Nigeria a disservice to pigeonhole it as resource-cursed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, economic growth alone is not working for most Nigerians. In 2016, the National Bureau of Statistics reported that Nigeria’s poverty rate was 67.1 percent, making it one of the poorest—and economically unequal—countries in the world. But this can be fixed, not by natural resources alone but by human resources in the service of good government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transforming Nigeria’s economic growth into countrywide development results rests on improving three elements of governance: strategic planning, financial management, and—critically—institution-focused capacity development at the state and national levels. These elements form a stable three-legged stool of governance required to steer economic growth toward inclusive growth, and to optimize Nigeria’s capacity in public service sectors such as education, health, and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Abah-Nigeria-top.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Abah-Nigeria-top&quot; title=&quot;Market in Ibadan, Oyo State. Photo: Mary Gillham Archive Project&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Strategic Planning: Knowing Nigeria’s Public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the development space, Nigerians are often faulted for poor implementation of good plans. In truth, many of those plans are written with lofty ambitions but little consideration for the country’s prevailing institutional, political economy, and human resource constraints. This factor renders many plans virtually undeliverable before they leave the consultant’s desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigerians are no more incapable of project implementation than any other nationality. They effectively implement communal self-help and religious projects on time, at the agreed cost, and with the requisite quality, often without issues of corruption, embezzlement, or diversion of funds. However, when it comes to implementing &lt;em&gt;government&lt;/em&gt; projects, the same commitment, transparency, and unity of purpose are too often absent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should that be the case? As far back as the 1970s, Nigerian academic Peter Ekeh described what he calls &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/178372?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;two publics&lt;/a&gt; in the minds of the post-colonial African citizen, even among the more privileged classes: a “primordial public,” which exists at the communal level and to which Africans are generally loyal; and a “civic public” representing Western-style government, to which most Africans have no such intuitive loyalty, and from which they will accordingly seek to extract whatever might support themselves. Whatever its merits, this framework certainly accords with Nigeria’s record of unfulfilled government projects, public sector corruption, and high degree of nepotism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressing this point of view in the development lexicon of the 21st century, we would probably say that development plans failing to take account of the local political economy are dead on arrival—they have virtually no chance of being implemented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As development professionals working in Nigeria, we must improve the quality of planning between Nigeria’s public and private sectors. But to do that we must acknowledge that a realistic plan—whether for tax reform, domestic resource mobilization, transparency and accountability, or other areas—needs to understand local political economies and work to optimize the capacity of local institutions and their staffs. Plans for public-sector reforms should identify ways to quickly gain stakeholder buy-in and account for risks to successful implementation at the communal level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Abah-Nigeria-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Abah-Nigeria-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Financial Management: Marrying Rules to Reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria has made good progress in putting into place rules-based public financial management systems that accord with international standards. The country’s Public Procurement Act of 2007 follows a template of the International Monetary Fund, the National Chart of Accounts meets international requirements, and the national accounting system is designed to conform with International Public Sector Accounting Standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, budgeting across the country remains uneven, despite the 2016 adoption by the federal government of a zero-based budgeting system. Auditing and financial reporting throughout Nigeria also leave much room for improvement. Notable here is the interplay between rules-based financial management systems and institutional factors that are often informal and not rules-based. Failure to understand this conflict—another manifestation of the friction between Nigeria’s primordial and civic publics—will lead only to more rules-based efforts that deliver little discernible change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, we know that reform is possible: for example, a number of African countries—including Nigeria at the state level—have improved their public financial management and domestic resource mobilization performance, thanks in part to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/governance-solutions/public-financial-management&quot;&gt;effective development assistance&lt;/a&gt;. In January 2018, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-joins-forces-with-nigerias-grid-consulting&quot;&gt;acquired&lt;/a&gt; Lagos-based GRID Consulting, a longtime partner of DAI’s that specializes in financial advisory services, human resource management, and development program implementation. GRID’s combination of local acumen, demonstrated integrity, and financial expertise will be an essential ingredient of our commitment to provide effective assistance in public finance and other aspects of Nigeria’s development challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-Abah-hospital.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-Abah-hospital&quot; title=&quot;Hospital in Katsina in northwest Nigeria. Photo: Eugene Kim&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Building Institutions: Unleashing the Capacity of Capable Nigerians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Nigeria, it is critical to differentiate between individual capability and institutional capacity. In virtually every sector or industry in Nigeria—both public and private—one finds capable Nigerians. Yet, too often, donor-supported development efforts focus on developing the capabilities of Nigerians as opposed to unleashing their collective capacity. The distinction is subtle but important. Capable Nigerians are individuals, while capable Nigerians acting in concert can dramatically improve an institution’s ability to deliver results. In other words, capacity development may involve developing the skills of individuals, but should do so in the context of improving institutional capacity. In practice, this means we should complement formal education with skills such as negotiating and managing contracts, developing public-private partnerships, optimizing organizational performance, and managing programs. In this way, we can unleash the institutional capacity of capable Nigerians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most effective way to unlock institutional capacity is through on-the-job training: providing coaching, mentoring, and skills development &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; institutions, as opposed to within classrooms—with a focus on the skills people need for their &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; job in the institution, not the one they currently hold. Too often, individuals are mired in positions where they are unable to increase their contribution to the capacity of the institution over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know this approach works in Nigeria. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-state-partnership-accountability-responsiveness-and-capability-sparc&quot;&gt;State Partnership for Accountability, Responsiveness, and Capability (SPARC)&lt;/a&gt;, funded by the U.K. Department for International Development, carefully and progressively aligned Nigerian capability to institutional capacity needs. SPARC itself was able to move from a composition of approximately 70 percent foreign consultants and 30 percent Nigerian consultants in 2008 to the reverse composition by program’s end in 2016. “SPARC has strengthened core State Government business processes,” according to the project’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opml.co.uk/sites/default/files/SLP-Final-Evaluation-Volume-1.pdf&quot;&gt;final evaluation&lt;/a&gt;. By 2016, the Nigerian-led SPARC team supported 10 State Development Plans and had helped state governments collect an additional GBP600 million (equivalent) to support public services by improving domestic revenue mobilization—reclaiming funds from dormant bank accounts, reducing procurement costs, and recovering outstanding debts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there were capable Nigerians available, but those capabilities needed to be developed, tailored, and aggregated to unlock the full capacity of SPARC and its government partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-Abah-bottom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-Abah-bottom&quot; title=&quot;Nigerian volunteers mobilized against the Ebola crisis. Photo: CDC Global&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mobilizing Nigeria’s Potential Champions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s oil industry and related wealth might be concentrated in the south, but its entrepreneurial and business energy is more widespread. Likewise, public servants throughout the country have shown they possess the collective capacity and potential to reform public finance, plan strategically, and raise and mobilize revenues for the public good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under SPARC, the northern state of Kano mobilized GBP14 million more revenue from 2012 to 2014, an 11 percent increase; the resulting expenditures benefited health, education, and other services. In the northwest state of Niger, budget variance for expenditures decreased from 50 percent in 2011 (budget vs. actual) to 15 percent in 2013, enabling improved planning. As noted above, these and other gains were achieved largely thanks to Nigerian consultants and their local counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To strengthen the three legs of the governance stool—strategic planning, institutional capacity, and financial management—we must identify, support, and empower those Nigerian champions in both the public and private sectors who seek to align traditional loyalties with civic reforms in ways that broaden and deepen the country’s economic successes to benefit all Nigerians. These champions are there—in business, government, schools, and communities. They are many.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Helps Position the Southern Africa Development Community for 21st Century Success</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ec-helps-position-the-southern-africa-development-community-for-21st-century-success</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ec-helps-position-the-southern-africa-development-community-for-21st-century-success</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Launched in 1992, the Southern Africa Development Community (SADC) was based more on ideals than economics. Born of the anti-Apartheid movement, the SADC aimed to help Southern Africa countries build economic ties and reduce dependence on the Republic of South Africa. As the region changed, the SADC’s membership grew and the organization adopted lofty goals. But the SADC’s outmoded inner workings did not meet the needs of its escalating staff and ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the SADC’s Secretariat—based in Gaborone, Botswana—asked the European Commission (EC) to help modernise the SADC’s processes and recalibrate the organisation for success. After four years of sustained collaboration, the SADC now operates with new systems and a renewed focus on rigorously planning and managing its projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/lfYchLjWLYbcc7p8s6a4&quot; title=&quot;SADC Map&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?lYq&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This accomplishment was assisted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/botswana-technical-assistance-sadc-secretariat-institutional-capacity-development&quot;&gt;Technical Assistance to the SADC Secretariat Institutional Capacity Development Programme&lt;/a&gt;, which worked closely with the Secretariat’s executive team, supporting them through the setbacks and successes of organisational transformation. Over the past four years, the team:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trained the Secretariat on revised procurement policies, supply chain management, and contract administration;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepared the SADC to work directly with international donors to manage projects;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teamed with SADC directorates to improve evaluation guidelines and build capacity among personnel responsible for monitoring and planning;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed program dashboards to track projects and created statistical yearbooks to support data-driven planning;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enabled the SADC to better manage members’ obligations;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aligned human resources policies—including job descriptions, hiring standards, and performance reviews—to support the SADC vision and values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme, managed by DAI, also helped the SADC to develop a comprehensive plan for how it will utilise the current round of European Development Fund (EDF) funding for its programmes, which address agriculture, water, trade, and other regional needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Regional Communities Matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The African Union recognizes eight regional economic communities on the continent. The SADC member states— Angola, Botswana, Democratic Republic of Congo, Lesotho, Madagascar, Malawi, Mauritius, Mozambique, Namibia, Seychelles, South Africa, Swaziland, Tanzania, Zambia, and Zimbabwe—have long depended on regional cooperation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regional economic communities play increasingly important roles, from improving intra-region trade to preventing conflicts between member states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harmonized financial regulations can facilitate commerce and create jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong regional cooperation can attract donor agencies and private investors to support cross-border infrastructure projects, such as highways and electrical grids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six SADC member states are landlocked and rely on neighbours to import and export products by sea.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;SADC Commits to Intensive Reform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with a complex and diverse regional body prompted DAI to apply an adaptable, demand-driven approach. The programme focused on improving SADC staff attitudes about their work over publishing documents. The SADC Secretariat staff proved to be receptive partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Initially, the programme was run like a framework contract, but this didn’t allow enough flexibility—the typical 20-day timeframes for consultants didn’t provide time for knowledge transfer,” said David Ablett, Team Leader for DAI. “We didn’t want to just drop off documents and then leave. We wanted to nurture people and test things.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the Secretariat was struggling with the key processes it needed to plan, implement, and monitor projects, but its leadership knew what the organization needed and committed to bringing about sustainable change. In turn, DAI’s team formed a close working relationship with the SADC’s executive team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fixing the Procurement Struggle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the procurement difficulties of the Secretariat, for example, the DAI team and SADC leadership developed and implemented procedures and created an internal audit manual. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff from across the Secretariat were trained on the revised policies. The cross-trained staff can now effectively manage an annual procurement budget, allowing the Secretariat to hire directly and manage technical consultants or upgrade its own information technology (IT). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes had an immediate effect on efficiency and staff morale. Several large tenders that had been blocked in the SADC’s system for years have been executed as a result, and staff are now working on projects directly with international donors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;Among SADC’s offerings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service centres&lt;/strong&gt; addressing areas such as agriculture standards, climate resilience, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sadc.int/sadc-secretariat/services-centres/rptc/&quot;&gt;security&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financing facilities&lt;/strong&gt; for jumpstarting project planning, water projects, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sadc.int/sadc-secretariat/directorates/office-deputy-executive-secretary-regional-integration/trade-industry-finance-investment/sadc-trade-related-facility-trf/&quot;&gt;trade&lt;/a&gt; technical assistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consultancies&lt;/strong&gt; including for health, infrastructure, defence, and agriculture.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Promoting Merit-Based Human Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SADC Secretariat’s annual budget of $71.9 million is made up of contributions from member states. While revamped administrative processes were essential, addressing the SADC’s human factors was equally important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat worked with DAI’s team to revise HR policies. Incomplete job descriptions were updated and performance reviews adjusted to connect employee’s objectives to larger organizational goals. Improving hiring standards and rewarding top performers helped rejuvenate the organization and boost morale, while enabling the Secretariat to hold underperforming and corrupt employees accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Dusting Off Manuals, Putting Policy into Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat worked with DAI’s team to strengthen financial management and upgrade IT systems. While previous consulting projects had developed valuable technical manuals and plans for the Secretariat, the EC and DAI’s team recognised that different approaches would be needed to ensure that what was put down on paper during previous programmes was also put into practice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EC Delegation in Botswana supported DAI’s team in taking a long-term, iterative approach, with a focus on attitudinal change, and allowed the programme to hire consultants for extended periods. “We took a more in-depth, hands-on project approach to a typical technical assistance framework contract,” said Ablett. “It was a frustrating process at times to design and test, but the EC saw benefit in it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SADC-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SADC-1&quot; title=&quot;SADC Executive Secretary Ms. Stergomena Lawrence Tax Gaborone, right, meets in November 2017 with United Nations Special Representative Maman Sidikou in her office in Gaborone, Botswana. Photo: MONUSCO.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New Confidence Attracts New Partners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The positive changes were noticed outside of the Secretariat. With new confidence in the SADC’s administrative capabilities, donor agencies from France, Italy, the United Kingdom, and other countries began approaching the organisation about leading regional development projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those working on U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)-funded projects in the region, the SADC’s improved capacity was noticeable. USAID’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-feed-future-southern-africa-seed-trade-project&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Seed Trade Project&lt;/a&gt;, both led by DAI, have partnered with the SADC Secretariat on activities, including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.satradehub.org/food-safety-and-production/537-sadc-convenes-to-improve-seed-trade?highlight=WyJzYWRjIiwic2FkYydzIiwiJ3NhZGMnIl0=&quot;&gt;SADC Seed Technical Meeting&lt;/a&gt; in November 2017 to discuss agricultural issues affecting the region. With its newly streamlined procurement process, the Secretariat directly paid its contribution of $20,000 rather than having to pass funds through an intermediary member state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its new policies and procedures, the Secretariat can confidently address operational challenges. Most importantly, this regional economic community—accounting for 300 million people and gross domestic product of $600 billion—has the potential to play a positive role in transforming the economy of Southern Africa and the wider continent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Zealand Aid Helps Rwandan Smallholders Enter Fortified Foods Supply Chain</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-zealand-aid-helps-rwandan-farmers-reduce-losses-sell-more-maize-to-producer-of-maternal-infant-foods</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-zealand-aid-helps-rwandan-farmers-reduce-losses-sell-more-maize-to-producer-of-maternal-infant-foods</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Small-scale farmers in Rwanda struggle to capture the full value of their maize harvests. Farmers typically process their maize manually or using basic tools. With limited infrastructure available for threshing, cleaning, and drying, the full harvest and post-harvest process takes six weeks, on average. Apart from being burdensome for farm families, the lengthy process exposes their maize to rotting, pest infestation, and mould. As a result, the farmers lose an estimated 30 percent of their yields, and traders capture much of the profit generated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Rwandan farmers seek to earn more from their maize, an emerging food producer in Rwanda is seeking locally grown maize for its nutrient-fortified products, presenting a clear market opportunity. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.africaimprovedfoods.com/&quot;&gt;Africa Improved Foods Limited (AIF)&lt;/a&gt;—a social enterprise with a mission to create jobs, produce and sell food, and support local farming—launched its state-of-the-art food processing facility in 2015 in Rwanda’s capital of Kigali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running at full capacity, AIF needs up to 30,000 metric tons of maize and 11,000 metric tons of soybeans per year. Currently, though, AIF can procure only a small fraction of that volume locally; it buys the rest from commercial maize producers and commodity traders in neighboring countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Wallis-pic-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Wallis-pic-2&quot; title=&quot;Rwandan farmers bring their maize to a collection point for processing. Photo: Kumwe Logistics.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With financial support from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mfat.govt.nz/en/aid-and-development/&quot;&gt;New Zealand Aid Programme&lt;/a&gt;, DAI is assisting a pilot process that has nearly eliminated post-harvest losses for targeted Rwandan farmers and helped them enter the AIF supply chain. Initial results suggest that post-harvest losses are being reduced to approximately &lt;em&gt;2 percent&lt;/em&gt; with no adverse effect on crop quality. The difference maker: a cob-to-factory concept supported by the Clinton Health Access Initiative (CHAI) that shortened the farmers’ maize processing time from weeks to days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Moving Maize Directly From Cob to Factory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, AIF, which makes fortified porridge flours, has been challenged to source grain of sufficient quality at targeted prices. The difficult growing season across East Africa—the 2016 El Niño phenomenon led to the worst drought in 60 years—diminished maize yields regionally and pushed prices upward. CHAI had been arranging forward contracts between farmers and AIF to transact maize at an agreed price and date, but conditions rendered the contracts unenforceable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new sourcing approach, advocated by DAI Team Leader James Allen from AgFirst in New Zealand, was piloted during the 2017 maize harvest. The idea was to streamline post-harvest handling and sales, moving maize as quickly as possible from the farm to the AIF factory. CHAI partnered with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kumwelogistics.com/&quot;&gt;Kumwe Logistics&lt;/a&gt;, a local transport company, to set up mobile maize processing centres with threshing and cleaning equipment. These centres were hosted by partner cooperatives with drying infrastructure on site and access to a network of farmers. The mobile centres had cash on hand to buy maize cobs directly from farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The participating cooperatives were [also] empowered, being able to offer a full post-harvest service to all farmers—something not previously possible given limited infrastructure.”&lt;/em&gt; —Kumwe CEO Cyril Khamsi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Wallis-pic-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Wallis-pic-1&quot; title=&quot;Touring the Africa Improved Foods processing facility in Kigali. Photo: Africa Improved Foods.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial calculations by Kumwe indicate that although farmers pay for some additional costs in this process, they earned 35 percent more net income due to the significant reduction in wastage. Additionally, the streamlined handling process helped maintain high-quality maize grains—no aflatoxins were detected in the 80 metric tons of threshed maize output sold to AIF—and farmers gained more time to sow the next crop. The concept is still under development, but initial results are encouraging, as the pilot proved that targeted sourcing of maize cobs could align the market incentives of farmers with those of AIF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits include farmers being paid six to 10 weeks &lt;em&gt;earlier&lt;/em&gt; and having the cash flow to invest in the subsequent season, which begins shortly after harvest, as well as ancillary impacts such as improved education for children not pulled from school to harvest and process maize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Scaling Up the Fresh Maize Purchasing Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the pilot, Kumwe worked in Rwanda’s Nyagatare (East) and Kamonyi (South) districts, engaging approximately 680 farmers and four cooperatives. Farmers each earned approximately 35 percent more income, or RWF 88,000 (US$100) on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----MFAT-Wallis-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----MFAT-Wallis-3&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Africa Improved Foods.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fresh maize purchasing model will be scaled up during the 2018 growing season. For the next phase, Kumwe established a processing centre adjacent to the AIF processing factory. After harvest, Kumwe will deliver the maize cobs from collection sites directly to the processing site, where there will be a centralized set of machines for shelling and winnowing. This fixed site enables far greater utilization of the machines, reduced breakdowns due to less wear and tear from transporting them, and easier repair given their location in Kigali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI has a contract through 2019 with the New Zealand Aid Programme to assist CHAI, and we look forward to supporting the “cob-to-factory” program as it scales up to provide more income for farmers and more maize for the AIF social enterprise as they produce affordable nutritional porridge flours for mothers, newborns, and infants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afghan Cities Assisted by USAID Project Achieve Highest Ratings in Citizen Survey</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-cities-assisted-by-usaid-project-achieve-highest-ratings-in-citizen-survey</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 17:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-cities-assisted-by-usaid-project-achieve-highest-ratings-in-citizen-survey</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a citizen assessment of government services in nine Afghan municipalities, the four that ranked the highest—Chaharikar, Hirat, Mazar-e-Sharif, and Jalalabad—are all partners with a U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) project working to improve the capacity of Afghan municipal officials to meet citizen priorities and service delivery needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/map-of-afghan-cities-in-survey%20Green.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;map-of-afghan-cities-in-survey Green&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-strong-hubs-afghan-hope-and-resilience-shahar&quot;&gt;Strong Hubs for Afghan Hope and Resilience (SHAHAR)&lt;/a&gt;, offers targeted support to municipal governments—as well as to the Deputy Ministry of Municipalities and Municipal Advisory Boards—to improve municipal financial management, urban service delivery, and citizen consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent that such improved governance confers legitimacy on government institutions and weakens the hand of anti-government elements, SHAHAR&amp;rsquo;s success offers an encouraging example of how technical assistance can be an effective tool in countering violent extremism in fragile environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conducted by the independent Integrity Watch Afghanistan (IWA), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://iwaweb.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/CITIZEN-REPORT-CARD-ON-MUNICIPAL-SERVICES-IN-AFGHANISTAN-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; used the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pria-academy.org/pdf/2.m4-2-Citizen-Report-Cards-Civicus.pdf&quot;&gt;citizen report card&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; approach, seeking to prompt reform by imitating the type of consumer pressure that drives private companies to do better. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fifth SHAHAR partner municipality included in the study is Gardez, which was without SHAHAR embedded advisors from mid-November 2016 until June 2017, due to a funding reduction that was subsequently partially restored. Consequently, the citizen service center, a number of community outreach activities, and public awareness campaigns were not completed in Gardez until after IWA conducted its survey in April 2017. Additionally, the increasing insecurity in and around Gardez in 2017 also caused several project activities to be cancelled. These issues may have contributed to its lower score. In compiling its scorecards, IWA conducted a total of 4,444 surveys, spread evenly across the nine municipalities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_50a861c4-dff4-44a4-bcfb-8b1092b82ad4&quot; title=&quot;Afghanistan Survey&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?vki&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IWA concluded that, overall, &amp;ldquo;Afghan municipalities must do more to improve the quality of services delivered to citizens, the level of overall governance, and the extent to which they communicate effectively with citizens.&amp;rdquo; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cities that scored relatively well are those where SHAHAR has led targeted activities around improving the services offered by local governments. These activities include establishing Citizen Service Centers (CSCs) equipped with systems that track business licensing, parcel registration, tax billing, and collection, and holding community meetings to spread awareness around municipal services such as waste collection. To reduce corruption, SHAHAR introduced a practice whereby citizens pay their taxes or fees at a bank or the CSC—instead of paying a government employee directly—and receive a receipt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since SHAHAR started in 2014:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partner communities have raised &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-municipalities-raise-more-revenues-deliver-better-services-enhance-stability/&quot;&gt;legitimate municipal revenues&lt;/a&gt; by as much as 38 percent year over year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its partner municipalities improved their governance scores by an average of 239 percent between July 2015 and August 2016 in the areas of revenue and finances, planning, service delivery, administrative reform, and community outreach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its partner municipalities have successfully bid out and completed 14 small infrastructure projects (such as new bus terminals, markets, renovated parks and sports fields, and improved drainage).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about what SHAHAR is doing to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-municipalities-raise-more-revenues-deliver-better-services-enhance-stability/&quot;&gt;improve local governance&lt;/a&gt; and service delivery, watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/204593033&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philippines’ New Tax Bill Promises More Revenue for Social Programs, Infrastructure</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-new-tax-bill-promises-more-revenue-for-social-programs-infrastructure</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 20:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Bryan Schuetz</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-new-tax-bill-promises-more-revenue-for-social-programs-infrastructure</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been more than 15 years since the Government of the Philippines undertook its last comprehensive tax policy reform. Over that period, tax revenues have seen a steady decline, from a high of nearly 17 percent of GDP in 1997 to only &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/GC.TAX.TOTL.GD.ZS?locations=PH&quot;&gt;13.6 percent in 2016&lt;/a&gt;. This decline can be attributed to both domestic and external factors. On the international front, the Asian financial crisis of 1997–1998 and the global recession of 2008–2009 certainly contributed to sharp drop-offs. But the Government of the Philippines’ limited ability to enforce fiscal discipline also was a factor, allowing special interests to introduce loopholes, weaken tax laws, and chip away at previous reforms. These factors were compounded by lower import duties (motivated by the prospect of improving trade) and flaws in the 1997 excise tax reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/SBkjBbLfUQ7SFLOAP4Vz&quot; title=&quot;Philippines Infographic&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?dmj&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recent years have seen an uptick in the tax revenue-to-GDP ratio since the low of 12.1 percent reached in the post-recession year of 2010, helped by adjustments to corporate, excise, and value added tax rates in the early 2000s and &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GNP.PCAP.CD?locations=PH&quot;&gt;steadily increasing incomes&lt;/a&gt;. These recent increases were also in no small part due to the efforts of the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/philippines-facilitating-public-investment-fpi&quot;&gt;Facilitating Public Investment&lt;/a&gt; (FPI) program in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates/&quot;&gt;modernizing and expanding the electronic tax-filing system&lt;/a&gt;, which among other achievements increased the e-filing rate to 76.23 percent by October 2017, compared to 8 percent in 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/philippines.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;philippines&quot; title=&quot;Participants at one of the roadshows for the Tax Reform for Acceleration and Inclusion bill (TRAIN). FPI Chief of Party Roberto Toso is third from left.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not content with capturing significantly more tax revenue through expanded e-filing, FPI has also been working to push sweeping tax reform legislation. Building on comprehensive technical support to the Department of Finance (DOF) and the Bureau of Internal Revenue (BIR), FPI facilitated passage of the Tax Reform for Acceleration and Inclusion bill (TRAIN), culminating with President Rodrigo Duterte signing it into law on December 19, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;The TRAIN Bill: A Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Reduces income taxes on 99 percent of taxpayers while increasing them for the wealthiest&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Raises taxes on certain goods and services (cars, fuel, tobacco, cosmetic surgery, tobacco, and sweetened beverages)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Removes 54 lines of exemption in the value added tax (VAT), while increasing the threshold from P1.9 million to P3 million (small business with annual sales of P3 million and below would now be exempt from paying VAT)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Levies new 6 percent estate and donor tax&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Increases rates for the documentary stamp tax (a tax on documents, instruments, loan agreements, and papers evidencing the acceptance, assignment, sale, or transfer of an obligation, right, or property) and imposes a tax on currency deposit units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major overhaul of the tax code, the TRAIN bill is expected to raise P130 billion (roughly US$2.5 billion) in new revenue, 70 percent of which will go toward funding the government’s “Build, Build, Build” infrastructure program and 30 percent toward social programs, such as the Unconditional Cash Transfer structure that provides P200 per month to the 10 million poorest Filipino families who will be affected by the higher prices of goods and services resulting from the bill. A major feature of the bill is the reduction of income taxes for most wage earners while increasing them for the very wealthy. This change in itself represents a net reduction in revenue, but is made up for by the introduction of new excise taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FPI drove outreach and consensus building for the legislation through nationwide tax reform roadshows in collaboration with the Philippine Chamber of Commerce and Industry. The resulting tax reform coalition—composed of private and business sector associations, the Open Government Regional Dialogues with the Philippine Open Government Partnership Secretariat, and civil society organizations—proved to be an effective advocate for bringing tax reform into the public discourse and garnering public support for the legislation. FPI also worked with the DOF’s Strategy, Economics, and Results Group and led meticulous assessments of the TRAIN bill’s Lower and Upper House versions, proposing detailed amendments and sharing them with DOF stakeholders to arrive at the final bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;TRAIN 2: Proposed Reforms&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Reduces the corporate income tax rate from 30 percent to 25 percent by 2022, while expanding the tax base by 0.75 percent of GDP&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Enforces the minimum corporate income tax&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Allows BIR to prosecute tax cases&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Targets corporate incentives to activities with significant positive externalities, as specified in the strategic investments priority plan&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Eliminates VAT incentives: all firms to pay VAT and prove they export to be able to get a refund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAIN’s passage begins to address some of the Government of the Philippines’ signature priorities, namely to invest heavily in infrastructure and to simplify the tax code. However, TRAIN is just the first of five planned reform bills. One major intended component of TRAIN 1 that was not finalized in time for the bill was the Tax Administration Reform Act (TARA). TARA was meant to complement TRAIN by providing a modernized tax environment that is conducive to the proper implementation of the Philippines tax law.  However, tax reform pragmatists in both Houses and the DOF decided to prioritize the passage of TRAIN 1 and leave TARA for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As FPI enters its fifth and final year of implementation, it will continue to support the tax reform agenda, including pursuing TARA in subsequent TRAIN packages. FPI will continue to provide technical studies, advice, training, outreach strategy, messaging, and other support to DOF, and we are already working with the BIR’s new Implementing Rules and Regulations to help roll out changes enacted in the bill. We will continue to advance the tax reform agenda as we look ahead to TRAIN 2 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>With Elections Looming, Can Pakistan Fulfill Its Education Promise to Unschooled Children?</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More than 23 million children in Pakistan do not attend school. More than half of children who start at government schools drop out before completing primary school. These stark facts are harming a rising generation of Pakistanis already vulnerable to unemployment, instability, and extremism. And while upper-class Pakistanis enjoy excellent private schools and universities, much of the rest of the country has become resigned to derelict classrooms and substandard government-provided education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2013 and funded by the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID), the Alif Ailaan campaign is moving education to the front and center of the 2018 general election, in which 342 seats in parliament are at stake. In vying to make 2018 the “education election,” Alif Ailaan has inspired groups throughout Pakistani society—rural and urban, rich and poor, traditional and progressive—to mobilise in demand of improved public education. The campaign’s “ask” is succinct:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better budgets&lt;/strong&gt;—more government funds on education, better spent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better data&lt;/strong&gt;—led by Alif Ailaan’s annual &lt;a href=&quot;http://rankings.alifailaan.pk/&quot;&gt;Pakistan District Education Rankings&lt;/a&gt; that call out where government education is failing and why;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better teaching&lt;/strong&gt;—with a focus on mathematics and science; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better government schools&lt;/strong&gt;—with an emphasis on the poorest and most vulnerable 40 percent of the population who use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximately 1.5 million supporters have signed up for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/&quot;&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/a&gt; campaign, including politicians from all major parties, educators, parents, and civil society organisations. The campaign’s Facebook account has amassed more than 2 million followers. The question now is whether this groundswell will translate into more and smarter funding for public education, more prestige for teachers, and higher-quality schools for millions of marginalized kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/pakistan-transforming-education-pakistan-tep&quot;&gt;Transforming Education in Pakistan&lt;/a&gt; (TEP) project, Alif Ailaan is implemented by DAI and London-based subcontractor Accadian Ltd. TEP’s assistance is not designed to pay for books or desks or rehabilitated schools. Instead, given that the Constitution of Pakistan guarantees government-funded education to every Pakistani child between the ages of 5 and 16, TEP’s job is to make parents aware of this right and help them demand high-quality schooling for their children. At the same time, TEP encourages politicians to deliver on the right to education and work with education providers to improve the quality of that education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan is a high-priority country for U.K. assistance. In designing the TEP programme, DFID concluded that a crucial long-term intervention—in terms of stabilisation, economic development, countering violent extremism, and meeting the needs of a fast-growing, younger population—would be to help tackle Pakistan’s education emergency. Alif Ailaan is on track to get more Pakistani children into school, stay there, and achieve literacy, numeracy, and other skills so they can contribute to a more stable and prosperous Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-graphic-1-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-graphic-1-new&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Galvanising Political Will, Mobilising Demand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In making education politically relevant, DAI and Accadian have drawn on political campaigning techniques to influence political will and mobilise demand. TEP identified and analysed every interest group involved in providing education and constructively engaged those group members willing to be part of positive change while marginalising any blockers. This outreach required creating a strong, independent, authoritative campaign that would become the leading voice for education reform in Pakistan, which is what we have built with Alif Ailaan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TEP team, led by DAI&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/mosharraf-zaidi&quot;&gt;Mosharraf Zaidi&lt;/a&gt;,  emphasizes smart political engagement to support reformers across all the main political parties and groupings, and to empower other stakeholders in the education system to understand what needs to be done and start doing it. As we come to the second set of elections to have taken place during the campaign (the first was in 2013), we will be refocusing attention explicitly on voters—especially parents—and helping them to make education a salient issue for politicians seeking their votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----TEP-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----TEP-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of Smart Startup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In setting up Alif Ailaan, the most important first steps we made were recruiting the best Pakistani campaign team we could find. Our Islamabad-based team of more than 25 people were personally selected and have spent a good deal of time developing their skills as campaigners, first and foremost, and as professionals working to DAI’s high standards. We invested the rest of our inception period in testing our strategies and systems. TEP is not a typical development project—it involves generating political will and pushing for change—so we have been fortunate to have the active support of our colleagues at DFID Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the outset, TEP had to establish Alif Ailaan as a voice in the public political discourse but first and foremost to make people acknowledge the “education emergency” they face. Key to this was our lobbying the government to research, calculate, and publish a nationally accepted number for out-of-school children. Achieving consensus in 2013 that there were 25 million Pakistani children out of school was a critical initial achievement. Through sustained advocacy and communications efforts, TEP has since developed a layered understanding and buy-in around the four themes central to fixing Pakistan’s education system: budgets, data, quality of teaching, and the focus on government schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-graphic-2-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-graphic-2-new&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Is Your School Passing or Failing? Click Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TEP made education more pressing and locally relevant to politicians by building and launching a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/district_rankings&quot;&gt;nationwide data platform&lt;/a&gt; that uses the government’s own statistics to rate school districts in areas such as grades, security, water and toilets, enrollment, and gender equity. This data is open to parents and politicians alike and has spurred social and political discourse and competition between districts to move up in education rankings. We have also partnered with MIT media labs to track the frequency of media coverage on education stories, which is important to measure the impact of the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-5&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2018 election will mark the end of the current Alif Ailaan campaign and present TEP with two challenges: first, achieving the “education election,” where education gets due prominence and the parties compete in their commitments to improve it; and second, achieving sustainability—embedding practices and ownership so the urgent work of transforming Pakistan’s education system can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TEP has already embedded education issues into the political and social discourse, set a precedent of data-informed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/bulletin&quot;&gt;journalism and reporting&lt;/a&gt; on education, pioneered &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/publications&quot;&gt;ground-breaking publications&lt;/a&gt;, and lobbied for the government to research, calculate, and publish a nationally accepted number for out-of-school children. During and following the 2018 election, we believe the government provision of high-quality education for all Pakistani children will remain a top agenda item in manifestos and political party campaigns. Whoever wins the election will have much work to do. We and our partners will play our part in holding them to their commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liberia Moves to Reduce Donor Dependence by Improving its Ability to Invest in Itself</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/liberia-moves-to-reduce-donor-dependence-by-improving-its-ability-to-invest-in-itself</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 19:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/liberia-moves-to-reduce-donor-dependence-by-improving-its-ability-to-invest-in-itself</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Liberia has endured much turmoil in recent decades. Civil wars in the 1990s and 2000s saw the mass destruction of dams, bridges, power lines, and other infrastructure. Many of Liberia&amp;rsquo;s best and brightest citizens emigrated. Suffering from a large budget deficit, its government developed a deeper dependence on foreign aid. Furthermore, the Ebola virus epidemic of 2014–2015 killed more than 4,800 Liberians and terrified the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, after all this, people today in Liberia generally look forward with hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they have reason to do so. Liberia’s donor dependence could increasingly turn to self-reliance—if a second-year program by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) continues its recent success. The program’s goal—improve Liberia&amp;rsquo;s ability to pay for its own development—coincides with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/long-term-fiscal-reform-takes-root-in-el-salvador-and-elsewhere/&quot;&gt;broader movement&lt;/a&gt; by developing countries to mobilize domestic resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its outset in May 2016, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/liberia-revenue-generation-governance-and-growth-rg3&quot;&gt;Revenue Generation for Governance and Growth (RG3)&lt;/a&gt; project engaged the Liberia Revenue Authority (LRA) to jointly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/BENCHMARKING%20THE%20TAX%20SYSTEM%20IN%20LIBERIA.pdf&quot;&gt;benchmark Liberia tax policy and administration&lt;/a&gt; against international good practices. As a result, RG3 identified critical gaps and set the stage for tax reform in Liberia. Just one year in, the LRA has already achieved some impressive results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaps in Liberia&amp;rsquo;s tax practices identified by RG3’s benchmarking activity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low goods and services, excise, corporate income, and property taxes compared with those of peers (see table below);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No electronic filing or payment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No mobile payments;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No tax payments through commercial banks;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No excise stamps for enforcement;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No tax-return processing center and low data availability as a result;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inability to introduce risk-based audit selection due to the limited data availability;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No automated compliance monitoring;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No risk-based arrears management;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No taxpayer advocate office at LRA;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited role of the LRA call center in promoting taxpayer education; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No regular taxpayer surveys.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Great Progress So Far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand for improved domestic resource mobilization and accountability is arising from both the government and taxpayers. Early on, the LRA and RG3 team ramped up taxpayer engagement by increasing the number of taxpayer inquiries to the LRA call center &lt;em&gt;tenfold&lt;/em&gt; through aggressive mobile text-messaging outreach. LRA and RG3 conducted an innovative text-based taxpayer perception survey as well as a cost-of-compliance survey using computer-assisted telephone interviewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LRA established a centralized data processing center that has already processed information from thousands of tax returns into LRA databases, improving transparency for taxpayers encompassing some 70 percent of revenues and generating crucial information—on topics such as wages, employment, and property ownership—to inform audit selection and improve revenue forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxpayers gained a strong ally in the form of a newly established Taxpayer Advocate’s Office. Already, the office has repeatedly stood up for taxpayer’s rights—in areas such as customs clearance and verification of tax compliance—thereby reducing opportunities for corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DAI&amp;rsquo;s Tax Benchmarking Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two decades, DAI has produced tax-benchmarking training and studies for partner governments to assist them in benchmarking tax policy, customs, and tax administration against international good practices. Tax benchmarking helps identify the biggest gaps in tax policy and tax administration, inform tax reform strategy, and prioritize tax reform interventions. DAI is currently implementing fiscal reform and domestic revenue mobilization projects in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/when-tax-reform-leads-to-increased-funding-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;El Salvador&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-state-partnership-accountability-responsiveness-and-capability-sparc&quot;&gt;Nigeria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates/&quot;&gt;the Philippines&lt;/a&gt;, and elsewhere.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the LRA allowed taxes to be paid for the first time through commercial banks and their branches, as much as $7.3 million in taxes was paid using this method though August 2017—leading to the first electronic tax payments wired to government coffers and the first, albeit rudimentary, email-based electronic filing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LRA and RG3 interventions have also increased compliance. The number of tax payment transactions increased by some 48 percent in March–August 2017 compared with the same period in 2016, which is expected to lead to increased revenues for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LRA and RG3 are close to launching the first mobile tax payments. And finally, in close cooperation with the Ministry of Finance and Development Planning (MFDP), RG3 has developed a revised draft excise tax legislation that should help pave the way for a significant revenue increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/QBehpEVGpci6ueSMpwHz&quot; title=&quot;Liberia&amp;amp;amp;#39;s Deficit/Revenues vs. GDP&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?ur0&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on a productive first year and the benchmarking exercise, RG3 has established the following objectives for the next phase of the program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve risk-based audit selection so that LRA auditors focus on taxpayer cases that are most likely to yield revenues;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop microsimulation models to forecast revenues and analyze potential policy outcomes;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce e-filing to further reduce cash transactions between tax officers and taxpayers;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch mobile payments;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze pros and cons of decentralizing real estate tax revenues, so local property taxes pay for local services;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate payment reconciliation so compliant taxpayers are certified as such;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate LRA management reports to improve decision making; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce excise stamps to generate revenue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Liberian government has been a positive partner in tax reform, and we are hopeful that will continue for two more years under RG3—and beyond—under the newly elected president, former international soccer star George Weah. The government has great upside in terms of revenue generation and, in turn, expenditure management. While Liberia has suffered a great deal over the past two decades, we believe 4.5 million Liberians are eager to see through the tax reforms that will make government more accountable and productive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
