<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DAI Online Publications</title>
    <link>http://dai-global-developments.com</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 18:14:17 -0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving Livestock Markets to Generate Economic Growth and Resilience in East Africa</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/improving-livestock-markets-to-generate-economic-growth-and-resilience-in-east-africa</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 12:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/improving-livestock-markets-to-generate-economic-growth-and-resilience-in-east-africa</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;East Africa&amp;rsquo;s immense livestock resources represent the largest proportion of Africa&amp;rsquo;s livestock population. Many millions of people depend on the sector for food, income, and employment, and it contributes greatly to the region&amp;rsquo;s gross domestic product and foreign currency earnings. Strategically located near the livestock markets of the Arabian Gulf, the East Africa region is Africa&amp;rsquo;s largest exporter of live animals, generating income for producers, traders, and governments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While livestock is big business—generating 42 percent of Kenya’s agricultural gross domestic product—the sector provides scant income for the pastoralists who raise most of the animals. These families graze their herds for years in search of grass and water, in the end selling the animals for an unpredictable price. But recent assistance initiatives sparked new sales and energy in Kenya&amp;rsquo;s livestock sector while moving food from areas of surplus to areas of need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----livestock-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----livestock-1&quot; title=&quot;Loading cattle at the Garissa, Kenya, forum in November 2018.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional Livestock B2B Trade Facilitation Forums recently convened in Marsabit, Wajir, Isiolo, and Garissa attracted hundreds of traders from northern Kenya and neighboring Ethiopia, Somalia, and Uganda. Many in these business-to-business events were meeting in person for the first time. Together, they reached trade agreements to sell nearly 28,000 cattle, camels, sheep, and goats for $7.1 million. But just as importantly they began laying a foundation for transformational business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facilitated by the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; (the Hub), our key partner the International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI), and the Partnership for Resilience and Economic Growth, these forums represent the first livestock trading platforms of their kind in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I buy livestock from Wajir and Garissa regions and sell in Nazaret market in Ethiopia, and I export some of the meat outside the country. This forum has helped a lot. Sitting down with these traders has enabled me to learn from their experiences. I have made several beneficial trading agreements.”—Abduba Halake, livestock trader from Ethiopia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Scalable Market Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand for beef and milk alone in Africa is projected to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/3/a-i7222e.pdf&quot;&gt;triple and quadruple&lt;/a&gt;, respectively, between 2030 and 2050 due to rising populations, increasing incomes, and changes in eating habits. Northern Kenya’s pastoralist families and others in the sector are well placed to capitalize on this demand. Failing to meet demand, however, would lead to a critical shortfall for many African households in high-quality animal-based proteins and nutritional health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 70 percent of Kenya’s livestock is raised in the country’s arid and semi-arid lands, &lt;a href=&quot;https://clippings.ilri.org/2018/06/14/northern-kenya-southern-ethiopia-dryland-livestock-traders-gathered-in-marsabit-for-better-livestock-trade-and-market-links/?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+ilriclippings+%28ILRI+clippings%29&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to the ILRI. In addition to supporting nine out of 10 livelihoods, the sector provides 95 percent of the area’s total income. In short, livestock is a critical component of East Africa’s economy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More than 50 percent of Africa&amp;rsquo;s livestock is located in the East Africa Region.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The region is home to 107.2 million head of cattle, 178.8 million goats and sheep, 1.3 million camels, and 4.4 million pigs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sector accounts for approximately 40 percent of the agricultural gross domestic product in Ethiopia and Kenya and nearly 20 percent in Uganda.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sixty to 80 percent of rural households keep livestock to supplement their food needs and incomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Livestock-8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Livestock-8&quot; title=&quot;Grazing camels south of Marsabit, Kenya.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of Pastoralists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hub’s livestock forums focused on the market system and demand but were equally designed to improve food security and livelihoods for East Africans by moving food from surplus to deficit regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While livestock is produced commercially in East Africa, the sector’s success hinges on pastoralists and agropastoralists, the region’s main producers. They and their families mostly live in the vast areas that suffer from recurrent drought, human conflict, and marginalization, and their livelihoods and productivity are prone to shocks. Pastoralists live symbiotically with their livestock and their rhythm of life is dominated by the needs of the animals. Anything that affects the life of flocks and herds affects their caretakers just as acutely. The Hub works to help build resilience among these communities and pastoral areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pastoralists and others in East Africa’s livestock sector face many challenges, among them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practices built on subsistence and not scale;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High distance and cost of animal transport;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of livestock market management;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of information such as fair pricing and buyer requirements;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inadequate linkages between buyers and sellers at both micro and macro levels;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ambiguous livestock policies and administrative actions;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Occasional border closures, restrictive trade practices, and a range of informal taxes that inflate market transaction costs; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A chain of middlemen who each takes a share of pastoralists&amp;rsquo; potential earnings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Livestock-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Livestock-2&quot; title=&quot;Attendees at the Wajir, Kenya, livestock trade forum in September 2018.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these are solvable problems. Efficiently connecting animals to markets remains key, and it presents an opportunity to transform the sector—from the rural markets to the ports. The region’s proximity to and longstanding tradition of trading with the Middle East—Ethiopia and Somalia are chief exporters—represents an opportunity to deepen those trade relations. Surplus livestock and livestock products also provide East Africa with a comparative advantage for the promotion of intra-African trade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have been a livestock trader for over 11 years. I buy livestock from Garissa and sell in Kismayo, Somalia. I am happy to be in Wajir today because this has created a new market for me. I now have connections in Moyale and even Marsabit!&amp;ldquo;
—Ebrahim Nuno, livestock trader from Somalia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hub’s livestock forums provided an accessible platform for producers and traders to improve their businesses by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating linkages between key regional traders;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the price discovery mechanism of the regional livestock market, allowing livestock farmers to earn better prices from larger and more diverse markets;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Professionalizing livestock trade and reducing trade disputes;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving food safety through shared information exchange and expedited trade; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing financial inclusion through the use of formal payment mechanisms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These business-to-business forums—not unlike previous Hub-facilitated forums that focused on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-developments.com/articles/africa-trading-five-takeaways-on-trade-based-solutions-for-food-security/&quot;&gt;grain trade&lt;/a&gt;—applied structured trade principles by using common contracts, quality standards, dispute resolution mechanisms, and payment terms. They are proving that when buyers and sellers meet face to face, food can be moved, helping the continent become more self-reliant. As importantly, they are demonstrating how when businesspeople meet to trade, share insights, and discuss market solutions, they can prepare an underdeveloped sector for economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will Feminized Parliaments Mean More Gender-Friendly Policies?</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/will-feminized-parliaments-mean-more-gender-friendly-policies</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 20:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/will-feminized-parliaments-mean-more-gender-friendly-policies</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On January 3, 2019, a new U.S. House of Representatives was sworn in with 102 women members—a record number for the United States. All told, 127 women will serve between House and Senate, a 20 percent increase in the number of women over the previous congress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This encouraging trend is not limited to the United States. Last Spring, Mexico achieved &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipu.org/news/news-in-brief/2018-07/mexican-parliament-achieves-gender-parity&quot;&gt;gender parity&lt;/a&gt; in its upper and lower houses of congress. Sri Lanka elected &lt;a href=&quot;https://borgenproject.org/female-political-representation-in-sri-lanka/&quot;&gt;thousands of new female local officials&lt;/a&gt;, up from just a handful in previous elections. In Rwanda’s lower house, the elections of September 2018 saw women take &lt;a href=&quot;https://allafrica.com/stories/201809050028.html&quot;&gt;a whopping 67 percent of seats&lt;/a&gt;. Globally, the number of women MPs has roughly doubled in 15 years (though women still hold less than one in four seats). Other countries, such as Liberia, have seen little growth in the number of women holding elected office, something I was asked to consider recently in reviewing the country’s electoral reform efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My past experience working with women parliamentarians and my recent assignment in Liberia got me thinking: what does the latest evidence show about what women do once they are in elected positions, especially in developing countries? Are the assumptions that women will pursue policies favorable for women’s rights and a more development-friendly agenda holding up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Carmen-Conley-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Carmen-Conley-1&quot; title=&quot;Bangladesh Parliament HE Dr. Shirin Sharmin Chaudhury, left, presenting an honorary plaque to Afghan MP Fawzia Koofi during Koofi&amp;#39;s visit to Bangladesh to seek council on how to design anti-harassment legislation for Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, it is said that women in parliament will promote greater support for social programs such as health and education. Women parliamentarians are believed to be more “gender sensitive” policy makers who will also be more likely to promote the rights of other women. They are also assumed to be less corrupt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ideas seem as if they ought to be true, and anecdotal evidence—including my own experience—seems to confirm the assumption. We also have individual country case studies to draw on, though the country-specific literature has been mixed. More persuasive are recent, more robust, cross-country quantitative and qualitative analyses such as a study published in 2018 by researchers from the University of Kansas: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=The+Effect+of+Women%E2%80%99s+Representation+in+Parliament+and+the+Passing+of+Gender+Sensitive+Policies&amp;rlz=1C1GCEA_enUS831US832&amp;oq=The+Effect+of+Women%E2%80%99s+Representation+in+Parliament+and+the+Passing+of+Gender+Sensitive+Policies&amp;aqs=chrome..69i57.6025790j0j4&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8&quot;&gt;The Effect of Women’s Representation in Parliament and the Passing of Gender Sensitive Policies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study analyzes 159 developing countries according to their likelihood to pass and implement gender-sensitive laws. The results indicate that the countries with a higher share of women in their national parliaments are significantly more likely to pass and implement such legislation, including measures related to equal child custody rights, divorce, and legal protections against domestic violence, rape, and sexual harassment. (The study also looks at the role of electoral “quotas” in this process, about which more below.) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2018/06/180615094850.htm&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; from last year, this time of 125 developed and developing countries, was published in the Journal of Economic Behavior &amp;amp; Organization by researchers from Virginia Tech. It finds that corruption is lower in countries where a greater share of parliamentarians are women. Building on past studies that show correlation between the presence of women MPs and lower corruption, this research goes further to posit a causal link (more women in parliament leading to less corruption) and locate that causality in women legislators’ roles as policy makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Carmen-Conley-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Carmen-Conley-2&quot; title=&quot;A woman casts a vote in Sri Lanka.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on these efforts, the Inter-Parliamentary Union—which tracks the proportion of women in parliament across the globe and has a record of developing valuable case evidence on this subject—launched in fall 2018 an extensive new research project titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipu.org/sites/default/files/documents/ipu_wip_study_2018_tor_21sept18.pdf&quot;&gt;“The Value of Women’s Participation in Parliament: Enhancing the Evidence Base.”&lt;/a&gt; Now in its early stages, this research promises empirical answers to the questions: What is the particular contribution of women in parliament? How can we better measure this contribution? How can we more effectively promote and give visibility to it? And it sets out to develop indicators we can use across country contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final note: Many of the gains in woman’s representation—including those mentioned above in Mexico, Sri Lanka, and Rwanda—were made with the help of quota systems that in various ways promote female candidates or reserve a percentage of seats for women. Much has been written about the pros and cons of gender quotas, and the different types of quota that may be effective in getting women elected under different legal and electoral systems and political and cultural environments. Indeed, one of the reform recommendations I was in Liberia to evaluate involved the current political support for reserved seats for women in the house of representatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the policy benefits of electing more women to parliament, and other elected offices, are increasingly borne out by credible analysis and data, the case for a carefully structured quota system would seem to be strengthened, along with other forms of support for female candidates, including training and financing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Afghanistan, Women Step Up to Fill Need for Frontline Healthcare Workers</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/in-afghanistan-women-step-up-to-fill-need-for-frontline-healthcare-workers</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/in-afghanistan-women-step-up-to-fill-need-for-frontline-healthcare-workers</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Communities across Afghanistan—especially the dispersed populations in rural areas—have long endured a lack of basic health services due to low numbers of trained health workers and chronic security issues. But this situation is improving. Today, a program to bolster women’s inclusion in Afghanistan’s mainstream economy is also serving to fill high-priority needs in maternal and infant care, vaccination, skilled nursing, and other health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-women-in-the-economy&quot;&gt;Promote: Women in the Economy (WIE)&lt;/a&gt; program is enjoying noteworthy acceptance in the health sector, both by local clinics and hospitals that need trained workers and young women wishing to train for and fill those jobs. Funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development and implemented by DAI, WIE has facilitated 8,000 internships and apprenticeships and assisted hundreds of women-friendly businesses across Afghanistan. Among WIE’s results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health internships and apprenticeships:&lt;/strong&gt; Implemented by 24 job placement officers and managers across Afghanistan, the WIE Internship and Apprenticeship program’s network of 1,600 vetted employers provides safe working conditions for young women who are often entering the professional workplace for the first time. WIE has facilitated more than 1,700 internships and apprenticeships in the health sector alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forward Together Scholarships:&lt;/strong&gt; Of the 4,380 women earning these cost-share scholarships, 534 have completed or are enrolled in medical technology skills development courses, with 310 attaining full-time jobs and another 35 securing internships. WIE’s pre-vetted training providers teach courses in ultrasound, emergency obstetrics, pharmacy, mammography, and more than 10 other specialties.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Traditional culture, security concerns, and social norms are factors that often bar women from entering the workplace—however, the situation is different in the healthcare industry,” said Dr. Hamid Shirzad, director of Global Innovation Consultancy Services, a WIE grantee for nursing and radiology training for women. “Female practitioners are needed to help female patients, especially in gynecology, obstetrics, and pediatric care … There is a huge demand for skilled female medical staff.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afghan-WIE-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afghan-WIE-5&quot; title=&quot;Midwife nurse intern with patient at Jowzjan Civilian Hospital, Mazar-i-Sharif, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Giving Women a Chance to Excel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan as elsewhere, culture norms require that only women may provide healthcare to other females, especially during intimate circumstances such as pregnancy and childbirth. Yet these countries often present complex and challenging environments that restrict women’s access to training, leading to low numbers of midwives, nurses, and female community health workers, especially in rural locales. Hence, women and girls go untreated. In Afghanistan, this shortage has resulted in high rates of &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.STA.MMRT?year_high_desc=true&quot;&gt;maternal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.DYN.MORT?year_high_desc=true&quot;&gt;child&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.DYN.IMRT.IN?year_high_desc=true&quot;&gt;infant&lt;/a&gt; mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can fill crucial needs in community healthcare delivery by opening up these opportunities to young women,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/leadership/christopher-legrand&quot;&gt;Chris LeGrand&lt;/a&gt;, President of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/global-health&quot;&gt;DAI Global Health&lt;/a&gt;. “In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-women-for-health-w4h&quot;&gt;northern Nigeria&lt;/a&gt;, for example, many families are willing to break with tradition and support their daughters going away to train in midwifery, nursing, and other skills, especially when they see the need for such workers in their own communities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Afghanistan, socio-religious expectations and the poor quality of rural education have in many cases rendered girls unprepared to enter the health workforce. But these conditions are addressable, as WIE is demonstrating. A few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-4&quot; title=&quot;Laila, left, a dental assistant, assists during a procedure at Ahmadi Dental Clinic in Kandahar, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Kandahar: First-Time Dental Visits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to cultural and safety concerns, women and girls in Kandahar province struggle to locate acceptable dental and healthcare. When WIE introduced a Basic Dentistry Training course, 13 women enrolled and 11 graduates found jobs, becoming among the first female dental practitioners in Kandahar.
Laila became the first woman to work as a dental assistant in the Ahmadi Dental Clinic, prompting her employer to promote dental care for female patients. Since hiring Laila, the clinic’s roster of female patients has steadily increased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Before, we had too many issues in that female patients in need of care would cancel appointments,” says Dr. Sharifullah Sharafat, the clinic’s owner. “They were not comfortable to be in an examination room with a male dentist and no female assistant. With Laila, we can offer proper care for female patients in an environment that makes them comfortable.”
Added Laila: “Now I have a job that is critical in helping women in my community get dental care, many of them for the very first time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-3&quot; title=&quot;New staff at the Loghnam Hakim Hospital in Herat, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Herat: A Thankful Hospital Chief&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loghnam Hakim Hospital was expanding from 70 to 100 beds and needed more trained health workers. The private hospital already employed 260 staff, including 140 women. Hospital manager Dr. Ejaz approached WIE and accepted 30 interns for on-the-job training positions as nurses, midwives, lab assistants, x-ray technicians, and administrative staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The inclusion of women into the national healthcare system is vital for our country,” said Dr. Ejaz. “The WIE internship program was a lifesaver for us, and it provided a platform between us as an employer and new, inexperienced female recruits. The young women who came to us were well prepared for work, they had their family’s permission to work; most of them could even work night shifts, which in a hospital is critical. We invested in quality training for our interns, and it has paid off.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loghnam Hakim Hospital has since enjoyed a 10 percent increase in revenue, which is increasing day by day as the number of female patients increase. The hospital adopted more thorough and transparent personnel practices, improved the quality and variety of care for female patients, and further improved its local reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-2&quot; title=&quot;WIE beneficiary Nooria, who manages Mazar-i-Sharif&amp;#39;s first mobile health clinic.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Mazar-i-Sharif: A New Mobile Healthcare Clinic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-nine-year-old Nooria, a resident of Mazar-i-Sharif, had medical education but no work experience. After completing a WIE-facilitated ultrasound technology course, she was soon hired to run Mazar’s first-ever mobile health clinic. Sponsored by Marie Stopes International, the clinic is equipped with an ultrasound machine, medication, and other medical machinery. Nooria now examines 20 to 30 female patients daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The WIE scholarship program helped me gain job-specific technical skills, which enabled me to get this job,” Nooria said. “I am now helping hundreds of women per week get healthcare services they need and that otherwise might not be available to them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Afghan-WIE-health-1&quot; title=&quot;Dr. Arzoo at her facility in Jalalabad, Afghanistan, with a patient.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Jalalabad: A Doctor Gets Her Chance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Arzoo’s family supported her wish to study medicine at a private university in Jalalabad, but upon graduation the 28-year-old was not qualified to operate the ultrasound machine, which is required in diagnostics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arzoo learned about a WIE-facilitated course in ultrasound technology, which she took for three months under a certified trainer. Upon completion, Arzoo struggled to find a job due to a lack of positions for women in government clinics, so she opened her own facility. She now sees female patients each day and earns as much as AFN 28,000 per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I will never forget the assistance from WIE that allowed me to earn a living doing what I love and helping other women in my community have safe pregnancies and aftercare.”—Dr. Arzoo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;

MANAGING MIDWIFE CARE: In Afghanistan, many midwife clinics offer valuable services but lack business management skills. Many have no bookkeeping systems, inventory control, or income statements, reducing their profitability and putting their sustainability at risk. WIE is collaborating with the USAID-funded HEMAYAT (Helping Mothers and Children Thrive) program and its network of 25 midwife houses in Mazar-i-Sharif, Kandahar, Jalalabad, and Herat. Skilled midwives provide standardized, fee-based family planning and maternal newborn care, and WIE delivers business skills training through four female business-degree graduates embedded within the network. These advisors work alongside clinic managers to install financial management and administrative systems so that clinic managers learn the cost control and financial skills needed to sustain their services.&lt;/aside&gt;  

&lt;h2&gt;Government Driving Health Reforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WIE is also supporting the Afghanistan Medical Council (AMC) to enact licensing and registration procedures for doctors and dentists to ensure improved diagnosis and care. Funded by the Afghan government, the AMC will mandate high standards for professional conduct and medical ethics, and improve competency across registered medical practitioners, eventually to include midwifery, nursing, and other disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This more robust registration regime will enable women to better document their credentials, in turn leveling the playing field in Afghanistan’s healthcare industry. “In the last decade and a half, thousands of female midwives, doctors, and nurses have been trained, yet many public and private health facilities still lack qualified female staff,” said Dr. Shirzad. “This situation justifies the need for more quality training, investment, and standardized certification procedures for female practitioners.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Women and girls should not have to suffer medically because social barriers are preventing their treatment or preventing other women from becoming health workers,” added DAI’s Michelle Morgan, WIE’s Chief of Party. “Fortunately, the demand for women health workers is driving good participation in our program and supporting women’s inclusion in the economy and more broadly.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Inclusivity into Inclusive Education</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/building-inclusivity-into-inclusive-education</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 15:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/building-inclusivity-into-inclusive-education</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the Millennium Development Goals were established in 2000, the number of out-of-school children in the world has dropped from nearly 100 million to 65 million, and in most countries, girls have &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.undp.org/content/undp/en/home/librarypage/mdg/the-millennium-development-goals-report-2015.html&quot;&gt;achieved&lt;/a&gt; equal attendance in primary schools through hard-fought wins. At the same time, however, we are still not reaching millions of out-of-school children, nor are we helping all of those we do reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, children with physical or learning disabilities represent half of the 65 million children not in school. Our ongoing failure to assist children with disabilities has cumulatively resulted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.worldbank.org/education/missing-piece-disability-inclusive-education&quot;&gt;only 3 percent&lt;/a&gt; literacy among the world’s disabled adults—only 1 percent among women. Today, children with disabilities are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalpartnership.org/blog/new-usaid-and-world-bank-partnership-support-inclusive-education&quot;&gt;less likely&lt;/a&gt; to complete primary school than they were two decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Inclusive-education-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Inclusive-education-1&quot; title=&quot;Taking tests in northern Nigeria as part of midwife coursework under the U.K. Department for International Development&amp;#39;s Women for Health program.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address this problem, countries and donors are emphasizing assistance that equally addresses education for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; out-of-school children. “Inclusive education” has become the buzz phrase, with the Australian government, the U.K. Department for International Development, and the U.S. Agency for International Development prioritizing inclusive education in their overall education strategies and taking actions such as the U.K. Government’s first &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/global-disability-summit-sparks-170-commitments-to-tackle-stigma-and-discrimination-against-people-with-disabilities&quot;&gt;Global Disability Summit&lt;/a&gt; in June 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the summit, International Development Secretary Penny Mordaunt called on other governments and donors to follow the U.K.’s lead and “stand alongside people with disabilities in their country, commit to ending stigma, and fully value the contribution they can make to the success of their nations.” The summit generated &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/global-disability-summit-commitments&quot;&gt;170 commitments&lt;/a&gt; from governments and other funders to take action on stigma and discrimination against people with disabilities, including through inclusive education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;“Inclusive” Defined&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to define the excluded and ways we can start bringing these young people into classrooms. Here are five principles we should appreciate and embrace as we talk about this critical topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Including the disabled.&lt;/strong&gt; This movement aims to ensure all children are learning together in one common education environment, as opposed to programs where students with special needs are segregated into different classrooms or schools. Educators and proponents argue that inclusive learning environments help improve learning for all students.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcoming the marginalized.&lt;/strong&gt; Nobel Prize-winning economist Amartya Sen described development as addressing the “various types of unfreedoms that leave people with little choice and little opportunity of exercising their reasoned agency.” This “unfreedom” in education includes any process that leads to one group being treated less fairly than others, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dais-fatima-adamu-describes-survivor-centred-approach-at-dfid-safeguarding-summit&quot;&gt;those affected&lt;/a&gt; by conflict, structural violence, and crises; girls; LGBTQ youth; ethnic and religious minorities; and others. These marginalized learners need opportunities to learn with their peers in supportive classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Appreciating differently-abled students.&lt;/strong&gt; This term is quickly replacing “disabled students” or “special needs students,” the idea being to frame all students as individuals who have assets and strengths to contribute to any learning environment. The term brings a positive and asset-based approach—not negative or deficit-based—to discussions around education.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recognizing learning vs. physical disabilities.&lt;/strong&gt; Educators talk about two large categories: learning disabilities stem from neurological brain abnormalities, while physical disabilities include visual or auditory impairments and anything that results in reduced mobility. Many students have multiple disabilities that require multiple strategies to meet their learning needs. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adopting assistive technology&lt;/strong&gt; supports children in the classroom and beyond, and includes anything from text-to-speech technology to specialized tables and chairs that accommodate all children.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-2%20(1).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-2 (1)&quot; title=&quot;Advocating for increased funding as part of the U.K. Department for International Development&amp;#39;s  Transforming Education in Pakistan program.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Steps Toward Inclusive Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are actions we can take collectively to increase inclusivity in education and build a world where many more children can have access to high-quality, relevant education:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit to training.&lt;/strong&gt; Globally, only &lt;a href=&quot;https://unstats.un.org/sdgs/files/report/2018/TheSustainableDevelopmentGoalsReport2018-EN.pdf&quot;&gt;85 percent&lt;/a&gt; of primary school teachers are adequately trained; even fewer are trained to work with children who have physical or learning disabilities, or have faced significant trauma or marginalization. Even in the United States, credentialed teachers find themselves &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/education/archive/2017/03/how-teacher-training-hinders-special-needs-students/518286/&quot;&gt;underprepared&lt;/a&gt; to manage students with specialized needs. Globally, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unicef.org/disabilities/files/IDDC_teacher_education_policy_paper_-_FINAL_-_July_2013.docx&quot;&gt;shortage of qualified teachers&lt;/a&gt; compounds the difficulty of promoting inclusive environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support advocacy.&lt;/strong&gt; For caregivers—including parents, families, and the broader community—to &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-developments.com/articles/women-and-girls-advocate-for-their-place-in-afghanistans-social-and-political-mainstream/&quot;&gt;effectively advocate&lt;/a&gt; for children’s education rights, they first have to know these rights. In most countries, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children/&quot;&gt;children have the right&lt;/a&gt; to free primary education regardless of their physical/educational ability, identity, and background. We need to better equip caregivers with information and resources so they are empowered to advocate on behalf of children’s education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Budget for early childhood education.&lt;/strong&gt; Education budget shortfalls limit resources for inclusive education, even though we know early investments pay off. Differently-abled children who receive high-quality care before kindergarten are 40 to 60 percent &lt;a href=&quot;https://edsource.org/2018/special-education-funding-is-a-morass-straightening-it-out-may-not-be-cheap-or-easy/594336&quot;&gt;less likely&lt;/a&gt; to require special education interventions when they reach school age. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enable funding flexibility.&lt;/strong&gt; Children who are differently-abled or marginalized need different kinds of support, so schools should possess enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-developments.com/articles/baseline-study-prompts-school-officials-to-counter-violence-in-honduras/&quot;&gt;flexibility and control&lt;/a&gt; to help shape their journeys to more inclusive education. Notably, per-pupil funding scenarios that do not account for “inclusive education” have &lt;a href=&quot;https://edsource.org/2018/special-education-funding-is-a-morass-straightening-it-out-may-not-be-cheap-or-easy/594336&quot;&gt;failed&lt;/a&gt; to create effective learning environments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promote relevant technology.&lt;/strong&gt; Technology provides exciting options to better support students—from script software that makes reading easier for dyslectics to text-to-speech software that helps the visually impaired consume lessons. A worldwide suite of digital resources is available to help reach learners in remote and even violence-prone areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Inclusive-Education-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Inclusive-Education-3&quot; title=&quot;The USAID/Honduras Securing Education program helps children overcome complex circumstances to attend school.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Cost of Exclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not investing in inclusive education can prove costly. The International Labour Organisation suggested the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.light-for-the-world.org/economic-case-inclusive-education&quot;&gt;cost of excluding&lt;/a&gt; children with disabilities from mainstream educational systems could represent up to 7 percent of gross domestic product in some low- and middle-income countries. In Bangladesh, the World Bank estimated a loss in employment and productivity by the disabled and their caregivers could cost the country $1.2 billion of income each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While various tools can be used to supplement and complement learning, students still need to be taught in classrooms with teachers and curriculum. Many additional well considered and intentional steps are required to expand and deepen inclusive education for the millions of children going without. As education programming becomes more inclusive—and it will—we must move beyond the buzz to build programs that bring all children into the tent of high-quality learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why the Time is Right for Access for All</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/why-the-time-is-right-for-access-for-all</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/why-the-time-is-right-for-access-for-all</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Following is DAI CEO Jim Boomgard’s Foreword to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/access-for-all-dais-brigit-helms-launches-her-new-book-on-economic-inclusion&quot;&gt;Access for All&lt;/a&gt;, Brigit Helms&amp;rsquo; new book on economic inclusion:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in my career as a development professional—a career that goes back to the early 1980s—informed observers are talking in credible terms about ending extreme poverty, not just within our lifetimes but within the foreseeable future. These aspirations are reflected, to take just one example, in the United Nations’ Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one factor accounts for this growing sense of promise. Not the rise of China and India, nor the globalization of the economy, nor the levelling and leapfrogging effects of digital technologies. But if there is one element that underlies the tectonic shift in the perceived prospects for global development, it is the pivotal role of the private sector: our realization, acceptance, and embrace of the notion that ending poverty ultimately depends on channeling the massive force of commercial actors driven by commercial incentives to create viable businesses and productive jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/304715051&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments increasingly (albeit reluctantly in some cases) accept that a vibrant and inclusive private sector is the key driver of development. Experience has taught us that public sector institutions simply do not have the incentives or capabilities to do more than facilitate the development aspirations and activities of others. Likewise, international donors are beginning to embrace their role as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-the-invest-project&quot;&gt;catalytic enablers&lt;/a&gt; rather than prime movers in the development story—if only because the funds at their disposal are so small in the grand scheme of international financial flows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the nice part of this story is that the private sector itself has a powerful incentive to play the very role that is expected of it. The SDGs alone represent a $12 trillion business opportunity, according to recent estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this story may be beguiling. While the convergence of opportunity and incentive could yield the economic growth we all want, there is no guarantee it will be the inclusive growth we all hope for. To put it in the terms of this book, there is no guarantee that the roaring engines of change in developing markets come with “access for all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Boomgard-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Boomgard-3&quot; title=&quot;Touring the Hawassa Industrial Park in Ethiopia, a country with a fast-growing sector for garment manufacture and export.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigit Helms has made a career at the intersection of inclusiveness and economic growth. As a development thinker, as a field worker, as an impact investor and an entrepreneur in her own right, she has striven to understand how markets work in developing countries, how they can work better for all citizens, and how the dizzying and evolving array of market actors are coming together to shape opportunity in frontier economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why DAI sponsored this book. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-the-invest-project&quot;&gt;DAI’s roots&lt;/a&gt; are deep in the loam of economic development, and it is clear to us that this soil has never been richer or more fertile, particularly when it comes to engaging the private sector. As I write, six of the world’s 10 fastest growing countries are in Africa. In Africa and elsewhere, DAI finds itself working in exciting new ways: running innovation centers and entrepreneurship hubs, bringing down risk and encouraging private capital toward emerging markets through “blended finance,” accelerating the adoption of transformational technology, facilitating regional and international trade, and working directly for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/sustainable-business&quot;&gt;multinational firms&lt;/a&gt; on assignments that support their investments, underpin their social license to operate, upgrade local suppliers, and generate local jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Boomgard-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Boomgard-1&quot; title=&quot;Gavin Gayadin, construction firm owner, at the Centre for Local Business Development in Georgetown, Guyana.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we are working with country governments on what is known as domestic resource mobilization—fairer and more efficient taxation and revenue generation—so they can finance their own development programs as economic growth takes flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brigit’s book asks the right questions for this propitious moment: In our quest to create more inclusive economic systems, what works and why, and how do we measure it? Who exactly are the poor and how do we open doors for them? At various levels of the economy, who are the major and emerging players, and how are they engaging? Full of examples, the book is both a snapshot of the current scene and an inventory of what we know about inclusive growth. Rather than grasping for an exhaustive summary of an inexhaustible subject, however, it curates the most telling trends, examples, and data, highlighting the most interesting and innovative developments in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Boomgard-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Boomgard-2&quot; title=&quot;Finance  matchmaking workshop in Herat, Afghanistan, for USAID Promote: Women in the Economy.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it does all this in the language not of the development economist, but of the layperson. Because “access for all” applies not only to the people who must be included in the growth picture, but also to the range of players who must play a part in making inclusive growth a reality—the people, we hope, who may be drawn to this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you are a government official, a fund manager, or a corporate executive; an academic, an impact investor, or a civil society leader; a venture capitalist, a philanthropist, or an NGO officer; an entrepreneur, an everyday citizen, or even—yes—an old development professional, you are the subject and the audience of this book, and you deserve to read it in a language we can all understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope &lt;em&gt;Access for All&lt;/em&gt; gives you a fresh look at the exciting world of inclusive economics. And I hope something in it inspires you to find your place in that world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Steps to Advocate for Government Investment in Public Health</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/four-steps-to-advocate-for-government-investment-in-public-health</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 21:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/four-steps-to-advocate-for-government-investment-in-public-health</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Nigeria, as in many countries, the government faces practical hurdles to funding health systems adequately and preventing sickness and disease among its most susceptible citizens. As Health Systems Advisor for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/global-health&quot;&gt;DAI Global Health&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-integrated-approach-to-neglected-tropical-diseases-united&quot;&gt;Integrated Approach to Neglected Tropical Diseases (UNITED)&lt;/a&gt; programme, I advocate for increased, cost-effective health funding in Nigeria so more people can benefit from health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the UNITED programme’s mass drug administration (MDA) to prevent neglected tropical diseases (NTDs) reached 39 million people, and by programme’s end will have distributed more than 110 million treatments in the five northern states of Kano, Katsina, Kaduna, Niger, and Zamfara. These drugs are donated, in whole or in part, by pharmaceutical companies and distributed by community volunteers. The MDA cost comes to $0.08 per person per year and leads to countless additional years of productive life. These are cost-effective results that funders like to see, including government budget officials in Nigeria and donors such as the U.K. Department for International Development, which supports UNITED. But we need to communicate these results in the right way if they are to support the case for continued funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----new-pic-UNITED.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----new-pic-UNITED&quot; title=&quot;Joint review of UNITED&amp;#39;s health systems strengthening strategies for client states in Nigeria.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective health advocacy depends on demonstrating measurable value for money and translating it into easy-to-grasp formats for busy policymakers, an information-overloaded public, and the headline-grabbing media. In today’s media landscape of snappy 30-second videos and tweets, advocacy must be equally attention grabbing but also strategically deployed. Four considerations stand out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understand the political and economic dimensions of the health sector.&lt;/strong&gt; Those with power often resist changes to the status quo—a good political economy analysis will inform your strategies on how to confront and positively influence recalcitrant parties. As my DAI colleagues John Yates and Darrell Freund &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/how-can-developing-countries-identify-and-allocate-resources-to-pay-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;write&lt;/a&gt;, health system stakeholders—policy makers, executives, and senior managers—should learn how public financial management works so they can use tools such as modeling and forecasting and planning and budgeting to inform and strengthen their advocacy for health funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enlist allies.&lt;/strong&gt; High-profile people with credibility can amplify a cause they care about and give it visibility, a voice, and clout. For example, physicist Stephen Hawking helped shine a media spotlight on the importance of controlling and treating NTDs, such as blinding trachoma, bilharzia, elephantiasis, river blindness, hookworm, whipworm, and roundworm. These less publicized tropical infections are prevalent in Sub-Saharan Africa and other locales and are collectively as widespread and destructive as malaria and tuberculosis. Hawking’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sightsavers.org/news/2017/12/stephen-hawking-commends-fathers-role-tackling-ntds/&quot;&gt;remarks&lt;/a&gt; at a December 2017 event hosted by Sightsavers—the UNITED programme’s prime contractor—marked the organization’s one-billionth treatment for NTDs and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-britain-science-disease/stephen-hawking-says-eliminating-neglected-tropical-diseases-within-our-grasp-idUSKBN1E71QX&quot;&gt;generated&lt;/a&gt; significant publicity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map influencers.&lt;/strong&gt; In Nigeria, certain state and non-state actors may for various reasons stand between the national allocation of funds and their expenditure at state and local levels. These persons take advantage of the lack of political commitment to ensure the non-release of, for example, health funding. Other barriers to cost-effective health expenditure include: &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-developments.com/articles/when-tax-reform-leads-to-increased-funding-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;inadequate revenues&lt;/a&gt;, misappropriation of funds, insufficient collaboration between health-related sectors, and rivalry between various interests. For example, the feud between health sector unions and the Nigerian Medical Association bedeviled the health sector in Nigeria for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing who will stand for, and against, our advocacy for health funding and expenditure often determines its success or failure. We need to identify the key relationships and specific ways that influential people—including naysayers—might come around to champion cost-effective health care programming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target messaging.&lt;/strong&gt; Successful advocacy for health expenditure requires reaching decision makers, the media, and the general public. Advocacy plans must include clear channels to effectively communicate with the right audiences. A good message delivered by the wrong messenger or to the wrong place will not be useful. Identify credible sources who can deliver &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/marshaling-the-evidence-to-better-help-developing-countries-improve-and-afford-their-health-services/&quot;&gt;evidence-based&lt;/a&gt; messages to decision makers in government. Include the voices of constituents who add authenticity to the campaign and personalize your efforts. Reach out to coalition, academic, and government partners who can lend supporting statistics and other research.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-UNITED-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-UNITED-5&quot; title=&quot;Presenting the Kaduna State, Nigeria, master plan for addressing neglected tropical diseases.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advocates need to develop a good working relationship with the media, as journalists and pundits will cover stories and give visibility to causes and information in their audiences’ interest. This collaboration between advocate and journalist helps media outlets achieve their content goals and advocates their messaging goals. Most journalists prefer facts to hyperbole, so providing evidence-based messaging and stories about effective health programming will more likely get your cause noticed. This media-advocate relationship also helps an informed public hold their government to account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-UNITED-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-UNITED-3&quot; title=&quot;Group training of local government officers for monitoring and evaluation on the use of neglected tropical diseases data tools.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To successfully advocate for adequate funding of health systems and programming requires ongoing effort with an eye toward capturing and demonstrating value for money. Groups that produce rigorous and compelling analyses, develop brilliant advocacy strategies, and execute them flawlessly may still fail to achieve their short-term objectives—unforeseen circumstances such as crises in other sectors may draw away attention from health, and funding and political shifts may occur. The key is for advocates to reflect, understand what happened, adjust their strategy, and go forth again and again, each year conveying a well-prepared case for funding that will underpin healthier and more productive communities and countries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Online Dispute Resolution Change the Way Global MSMEs Do Business?</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-online-dispute-resolution-change-the-way-global-msmes-do-business</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 19:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-online-dispute-resolution-change-the-way-global-msmes-do-business</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a grad student in London in the 1990s, I earned a bit of extra money sourcing and exporting handcrafted furniture from India to the United States for interior designers. My U.S. customers were small businesses, but I was even smaller, so if I wanted to sell to them I had to take on most of the risk. On school breaks I would travel to India, find what my customers were looking for, purchase it, accompany it to the port, and—when I could—watch as it was loaded onto a ship. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending the summer standing guard over my investment was time consuming, emotionally taxing, and expensive. The extra costs reduced my profits substantially. Why did I insist on being so “hands on” instead of relying on arm’s-length contracts in which physical control and oversight are replaced with specific terms and references? Because I was investing the next semester’s tuition, and if someone failed to pay me, going to court was not an option. Lawyers are expensive. While India was familiar to me, its courts and laws were not. If an American buyer didn’t pay, traveling to the States to sue while living abroad was out of the question. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, as a microenterprise, I lived close to the edge. One mistake and, poof, there went my tuition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As high as my risks were, for most micro and small enterprises (MSMEs) in developing countries, the risks of entering global value chains are even higher. All this risk must be accounted for in contracts because litigation isn’t an option, principally because there is no cross-border enforcement of litigated judgements and arbitration is too expensive and complex. While alternative dispute resolution (mediation, arbitration, med-arb, multi-tiered) has exploded in popularity for larger businesses and for investor-state agreements, it hasn’t found its way to the MSME community. As a friend in the arbitration business told me recently, “micro businesses couldn’t afford the coffee at most arbitration centers.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty-five years later, the risks are largely the same. But the emerging field of online dispute resolution (ODR) promises to change the landscape dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Enter ODR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recently invited by the U.S. Department of State and the governments of Japan and Hong Kong to participate in an Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) workshop on the development of a platform and procedural rules for ODR for MSMEs doing business across borders. It’s a tough problem. The Executive Director of the Hong Kong, China, APEC Business Advisory Council, David Dodwell, remarked that pushing small businesses into the unfamiliar world of global value chains without contracting skills and access to commercial justice is like “ordering soldiers out of the trenches armed with baguettes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the solution is to establish the foundations for enforceable awards at low cost, relying heavily on technology. Technology and a little creative legal thinking can reduce the cost of dispute resolution from $1,000 an hour to $1,000 a case. Or even $100 a case. ODR, accordingly, has tremendous potential to spur growth in developing countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Electronic Lawyers, Anyone?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with mobile money, ODR is a disruptive innovation driven primarily by technological advances in the way people interact, the way artificial intelligence (AI) is applied to real-world problems, and the way information is protected. ODR doesn’t replace lawyers, or any of the existing justice mechanisms, such as litigation, mediation, and arbitration. Emerging at the intersection of alternative dispute resolution and information and communications technology, it simply adds another method to the mix—one that combines many of the elements of the others, but with cost savings and other efficiencies built in.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most ODR systems (yes, they’re already out there; see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tylertech.com/products/modria&quot;&gt;Modria&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://getmatterhorn.com/&quot;&gt;Matterhorn&lt;/a&gt;, for example) rely on a multi-tiered dispute resolution approach, administered online with varying degrees of human intervention. Where liability is challenged, the first stage consists of technology-assisted negotiation in which machine learning allows the computer to prompt formulations and reformulations of the problem and of the parties’ interests so that they may achieve a consensual middle ground. Assisted negotiation and mediation aren’t about the law as much as they are about the parties’ future interests rather than their present grievances. Most disputes can end at this stage. Further stages can include AI-driven mediation and, of course, mediation or arbitration that is supported by real people but done remotely using virtual courtrooms and blockchain technology for protecting evidence and other information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Photo%201.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo 1&quot; title=&quot;Law students in Myanmar learn about dispute resolution.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting on the Same Page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the workshop, held at the Japan International Dispute Resolution Centre in Osaka, was to advance the APEC Work Plan on ODR and to establish a collaborative framework among APEC’s 21 economies—a set of rules and procedures that would apply to ODR platforms in the region—and to draft ODR language for the 2018 APEC Ministers’ and Leaders’ statements. The workshop attracted more than 90 participants, including government representatives from 17 of the 21 APEC economies. All of APEC’s developing member economies were present. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APEC’s interest in ODR stems from a recognized need to improve access to commercial justice for MSMEs, particularly those doing business across borders. The work plan consists of aspirational objectives and activities: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a pilot in conjunction with a platform host/ODR provider&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote harmonization of ODR laws using existing international instruments &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborate across APEC &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gather research and information &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design a model ODR platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop ODR procedural rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build capacity in ODR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leverage the private sector and academia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore technology for contract management or enforcement and prevention of disputes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an ODR framework can be established in APEC, it would be accessible to nearly half the world’s population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Obstacles to ODR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenges are the traditional, but arguably outdated, protections in relevant laws. An example is Indonesia, whose law on arbitration requires physical appearances by the parties and physical written submissions. Indonesia is also not party to important treaties that facilitate contracting, choice of law and forum, and dispute resolution, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uncitral.org/uncitral/en/uncitral_texts/sale_goods/1980CISG.html&quot;&gt;UN Convention on Contracts for the International Sale of Goods&lt;/a&gt;, and it has not adopted the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNCITRAL_Model_Law_on_International_Commercial_Arbitration&quot;&gt;UNCITRAL Model Arbitration Law&lt;/a&gt;. Indonesia’s law also allows arbitrators to physically inspect property in dispute if a party asks for it, and it allows a party to request physical meetings outside the place where the arbitration is held. Many other developing (and developed) countries have similar laws that would need to be amended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other important roadblocks include issues of due process (can AI provide parties with due process?), cross-border legal practice, and privacy concerns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic on which I spoke at the workshop is one of the most challenging problems. Many countries, both developed and developing, do not permit consumers to waive their rights to “traditional justice” (read courts). We can restrict ODR (and other forms of alternative dispute resolution) to business-to-business transactions, but it is often difficult to distinguish between a consumer transaction and one that is for business. Did I buy the computer I’m writing this on for business or for personal use? Even if it was purchased for both personal and business use (which it was), how would the seller know unless I told her? Does it matter? What if something is to be used only for occasional, or even rare, personal use? The rules we apply in the business-to-business ODR context may run severely afoul of national laws on the subject and need to be reconciled for the system to function properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Photo%203.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo 3&quot; title=&quot;Niche products like roasted coffee are being marketed internationally by microenterprises.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Development Community’s Role&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already seeing more donor interest in commercial and alternative dispute resolution. The U.S. Agency for International Development is building some of this programming into new projects, and the U.K. Foreign and Commonwealth Office is designing entire projects around rule of law for business, which includes alternative dispute resolution and, potentially, ODR. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For their part, implementers need to learn about their constituents’ culture of contract and dispute resolution, the challenges MSMEs face, and how they would benefit from improved skills and incentives (such as ODR) to take advantage of new dispute resolution mechanisms. Likewise, the ICT4D community has an important role to play in the development of localized, technology-assisted contracting and dispute resolution solutions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The payoff for MSMEs is a potential transformation of their prospects in global markets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Boundaries: How Secure Land Tenure is Improving Lives in Rural Tanzania</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/beyond-boundaries-how-secure-land-tenure-is-improving-lives-in-rural-tanzania</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 20:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/beyond-boundaries-how-secure-land-tenure-is-improving-lives-in-rural-tanzania</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After Monika Lalika’s husband passed away, her in-laws did not allow her to use the land he had left her and she used to worry that they would one day claim the property for themselves. For Martha Paulo Mwilongo, a land dispute with her neighbor kept her from selling or renting part of her 11 acres to pay her children’s school fees. Joti Kihongo wanted to expand his general store, but could not get a large enough loan because banks would not recognize his undocumented land as collateral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of official land documentation is not unusual in rural Tanzania, since property in most villages is handed down from generation to generation, typically through male family members. However, for Monika, Martha, and Joti, and thousands of Tanzanians like them, this historically informal system of land ownership had become an impediment to their ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that started to change after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/tanzania-feed-future-tanzania-land-tenure-assistance-lta&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Tanzania Land Tenure Assistance (LTA) project&lt;/a&gt; began holding meetings in their villages. The U.S. Agency for International Development project works with 41 communities in central Tanzania to register land and issue Certificates of Customary Right of Occupancy to individual landholders, with a focus on increasing women’s inclusion in property ownership. LTA has worked with villages to demarcate and digitally map and record almost 63,000 parcels. These previously undocumented parcels are now registered in the country’s official land registry system, providing secure property tenure to 21,000 Tanzanians. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But LTA’s work is about more than reaching target numbers—it’s about improving lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_02c9e45f-c0d8-4912-8584-952afd03626c&quot; title=&quot;Tanzania LTA 4&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?H15&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;More than Mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing secure land tenure in rural villages involves more than simply asking landowners to fill out a form. Parcels need to be accurately surveyed, ownership verified, and disputes settled before certificates can be processed. But first, village leaders and community members have to understand how land tenure can benefit them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/putting-the-value-in-land-titling/?utm_source=daidotcom&quot;&gt;secure land tenure is tied to economic development&lt;/a&gt;, Tanzania’s landmark Village Land Act of 1999 sought to formalize land rights in the country’s estimated 12,500 rural villages. While some progress has been made, village officials often lack the funding and trained personnel to survey and register land. Under the Act, land certificates can only be provided to individuals after the village council has developed a Village Land Use Plan, which only 15 percent of villages have done. Landowners—few of whom are aware of the certificate’s utility—must also pay a fee to obtain their certificates. As a result, less than 10 percent of individually held land is registered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTA begins work in each of its target communities by holding village-wide meetings to explain land rights law and how formally documented tenure can benefit and protect rural landholders. The project partners with village councils and uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lta-program-shows-benefit-of-truly-participatory-approach/&quot;&gt;participatory planning &lt;/a&gt;exercises to develop a Village Land Use Plan that determines village boundaries and demarcates public spaces, such as schools, markets, and pastoral lands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After gaining community buy-in, LTA begins digital demarcation of land parcels, also using a participatory and locally led approach. LTA trains parasurveyors from the villages to demarcate parcels by walking the boundaries of fields and residential parcels with residents and their neighbors, while marking property lines on a GPS-enabled tablet or smartphone. These mobile devices use the Mobile Application to Secure Tenure (MAST) to overlay boundary points on a satellite image of the village, which is then uploaded to a cloud server for editing back in the project office. LTA’s geographic information systems experts adjust boundaries for roads or public lands and the resulting map is posted in the village council offices for community members to review. Members of the Village Land Adjudication Committee work alongside parasurveyors to verify claims, confirm rights of occupancy, and resolve competing claims or boundary disputes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/parasurveyor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parasurveyors in the field&quot; title=&quot;A parasurveyor trained by LTA demarcating boundaries with a property owner.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project works together with the local District Land Office (DLO) to register new claims in the official registry system and to print and issue formal land certificates. Issuing land certificates is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/more-than-500-rural-tanzanians-now-have-land-titles&quot;&gt;cause for celebration in villages&lt;/a&gt;, drawing hundreds of attendees for music, dancing, and speeches from local leaders or district officials. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Benefits of Secure Tenure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Martha, receiving her official land certificate meant much more than getting a piece of paper. In her village of Mathembo, clarifying property lines ended years-long land disputes, including the one she had with neighbors. Like others in her village, she began investing in long-term crops and agricultural inputs for the previously contested fields, confident now that she will reap the benefit of her investment and not lose the land to another claimant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The certificates issued by LTA have also paved the way for rural Tanzanians to improve their farms and start small businesses by leveraging their land to access credit. The project is working with local banks to encourage the acceptance of certificates as collateral and with villages to raise awareness of the new loan opportunities. Farmers have already begun using their land-backed loans to purchase fertilizer, high-quality seeds, tractors, and other agricultural inputs to raise their productivity and their incomes. For Joti, having access to credit through the land certificate allowed him to save on costs and increase profits by buying items for his store at a bulk rate and stocking a wider variety of goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Joti_store.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joti Kihongo&quot; title=&quot;Joti Kihongo in front of his now expanded store.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to economic benefits, the project also expects the land certificates to have a social impact.  The Tanzanian constitution and the Village Land Act provide equal rights to land ownership for women. However, most people are not aware of these rights enshrined in the law and traditional inheritance practices still favor men. To address this knowledge gap, LTA led small group sessions to inform village residents of their land rights and the rights of women in particular. The project encourages husbands and wives to register their claims jointly, which protects women from losing land to male in-laws or relatives if their husbands die and can mitigate family disputes over property inheritance. LTA also works to link women’s economic empowerment to secure land tenure. The project facilitates training for village women’s groups on business skills and income-generating activities, such as raising small livestock and beekeeping, to help women make the most of their new, official land rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creating a New Market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another advantage of formalized land ownership is that it can foster an open market for land sales that contributes to further economic development. Currently, most DLOs in Tanzania use paper-based systems to track the buying and selling of registered land, which is time-consuming and cost-intensive and results in out-of-date records. Without a trusted means of verifying the current ownership of a parcel, farmers historically have been deterred from purchasing additional lands for fear of falling victim to fraud. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address this constraint, LTA worked with the Iringa DLO to build the country’s first post-registration digital transaction system for land, known as the Technical Register Under Social Tenure (TRUST). As there were no off-the-shelf land management programs that fit the unique needs of the DLO and the Ministry of Lands, LTA partnered with these organizations to co-design the TRUST system from the ground up. The project’s software engineer collaborated with end-users at the DLO and the Ministry to ensure that TRUST addresses common local registration issues and is flexible enough to adapt to future policy changes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operationalized this summer, TRUST enables DLO officials in Iringa to easily record the buying and selling of parcels and to quickly verify land ownership for banks and prospective buyers. An open-source application, it is interoperable with other land databases and—unlike off-the-shelf land management software—it does not require annual licensing fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_a29c158d-d0ac-4869-9da5-8e2930303b23&quot; title=&quot;Tanzania LTA 3&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?MFD&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Looking to the Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having demarcated nearly 63,000 parcels and registered 52,000 land certificates for more than 21,000 unique claimants in 36 villages, LTA plans to register a further 8,000 certificates for an estimated 2,500 unique claimants in 5 more villages before the project ends in 2019. Through its lean approach, combining community involvement and technological innovations, LTA has been able keep the cost of certificates to less than $10 each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TRUST post-transaction registration system also has the potential to be scaled beyond LTA. The project is already in discussions with Tanzania’s Ministry of Lands to integrate the system with the Ministry’s national land management database, and the World Bank is considering TRUST for an upcoming land tenure project that will work across 5,000 villages in Tanzania.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Matembo_Women%20copy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Martha Paulo Mwilongo&quot; title=&quot;Martha Paulo Mwilongo, on right, holding her new land certificate.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, the secure land tenure provided by the project is already helping new certificate holders to improve their lives. Joti’s store now draws more customers by virtue of its more diverse products, which he is able to purchase thanks to loans that use his land certificate as collateral. The store’s profits have grown by 30 percent.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monika was able to confirm her right to her late husband’s land. After receiving her land certificate, she planted trees on the property as a long-term investment in her children’s future.  She feels secure knowing that her former in-laws cannot lay claim to the land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martha has been able to use her now uncontested parcel to grow corn and sunflower seeds for sale. With a new sense of secure tenure, she has also rented part of her landholdings to other farmers, further increasing agricultural productivity in the community and earning income to help pay school fees. The land certificate has also given her something less tangible but perhaps more meaningful. “I’m so happy because I have freedom,” she said. “I can do anything. I can do different crops, I can sell land, I have freedom of decision.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study: Overcoming Land Tenure Issues to Stimulate Investment in Mozambique</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/case-study-overcoming-land-tenure-issues-in-mozambique</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 16:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/case-study-overcoming-land-tenure-issues-in-mozambique</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Mozambique, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-innovation-agribusiness-inovagro&quot;&gt;Innovation for Agribusiness project (InovAgro)&lt;/a&gt; uses a market systems approach to encourage investment by smallholder farmers in agricultural productivity, thereby boosting their incomes. But many of those smallholders find themselves increasingly at risk of losing their land to large investors who, with the backing of the government, are looking to start commercial farming operations encompassing thousands of hectares. This precarious state of affairs, which is in large part due to the government’s very limited formal recognition of smallholder land holdings, has made small farmers more and more reluctant to invest in their land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing the need to disrupt this cycle, InovAgro set out to improve land tenure security, then—crucially—follow up with efforts to expand access to services in those more tenure-secure regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A principal constraint in Mozambique’s market system for land is its bureaucracy. On paper, the country has a relatively progressive land law. But its land administration system is arguably less developed than, say, Ethiopia’s, and its actual capacity to deliver land certificates is severely limited. While there is a formal process for obtaining a long-term land leasehold, known as a DUAT, it is an expensive and time-consuming chore for farmers, and the actual number of DUATs the authorities can generate is small. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Mozambique has a second, albeit slightly less binding form of land recognition; namely, community land delimitation, which registers the boundaries of the community’s land and issues a certificate for the entire community that is recorded in the provincial land cadaster office. Easier, faster, and cheaper to obtain that the DUAT, this form of land registration can give the community some formal recognition of its lands and a bargaining position if the government tries to give that land away without proper consultation or authorization—and InovAgro found it can serve as a starting point for the more elaborate DUAT process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a pilot activity, InovAgro worked with local nongovernmental organizations to raise awareness around land registration in four communities—representing 17,225 people—and develop a network of land committees and paralegals. With InovAgro’s assistance, the communities and its cadre of paralegals were able to delimit their lands and register them with the provincial land cadaster office, the SPGC. In addition to improving tenure security for these pilot households, registration helped two of the communities resolve conflicts with encroaching investors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key to this success were the 57 trained paralegals, who are now recognized by the SPGC as valuable intermediaries in preparing communities and georeferencing communal land for the titling process. Moreover, the availability of what are essentially local service providers has enabled individuals to more easily start the DUAT process. By September 2018, 2,000 households had taken advantage of the paralegal services to file land demarcation applications for DUATs with the SPGC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;From Tenure Security to Economic Benefit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help farmers take advantage of their increased tenure security, InovAgro is also facilitating their access to better financial, input supply, and output marketing services. Based on the understanding that farmers more assured of tenure security will likely invest more, InovAgro has informed its private sector partners of the new opportunities in those communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leveraging its relationships with nine seed companies, for example, InovAgro has highlighted the stronger potential demand for inputs from newly land-secure households, and the input suppliers have increased their marketing and demonstration activities accordingly. In 2018, one input company opened shop in one of the districts and started organizing demonstrations for farmers. Two additional seed companies are considering opening retail outlets in those communities as well, and in general seed companies anticipate strong initial sales in the InovAgro pilot communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/seed%20store.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;seed store&quot; title=&quot;Project seed firm partners are increasing their marketing activities.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the visible interest and growing presence of these companies, 1,249 smallholders working in 44 groups have started participating in a Savings for Seed program to increase their purchasing power. Based on our experience of such programs in other communities, participation is likely to increase rapidly as the benefits are observed by other community members. InovAgro is also alerting financial institutions to the new opportunities inherent in a more land-secure market. BancABC, for instance, has already started identifying agents to offer services in these communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, an output marketing company has opened three branches to buy crops in those communities, purchasing maize, soya beans, sesame, groundnuts, and pigeon peas. Two additional output buying companies plan to open branches in those communities in 2019, stoking competition for the crops. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks very much like tenure security is working to the economic benefit of the farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Case Study: A Market Systems Approach to Deriving Value from Land Certificates in Ethiopia</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/case-study-a-market-systems-approach-to-deriving-value-from-land-certificates-in-ethiopia</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 16:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/case-study-a-market-systems-approach-to-deriving-value-from-land-certificates-in-ethiopia</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Funded by the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-land-investment-transformation-lift&quot;&gt;Land Investment for Transformation (LIFT)&lt;/a&gt; project works to raise incomes for poor and vulnerable populations in Ethiopia and to enhance economic growth through second-level land certification and improved rural land administration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second-level certification differs from first level certification by collecting and digitizing spatial data on a parcel-by-parcel basis. It provides a georeferenced land use certificate to the holder, containing a map with general boundaries that can be digitally accessed by interested parties such as lenders and insurance companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIFT &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/lift-programme-issues-second-level-land-certificates-ethiopia&quot;&gt;issued its first such certificates&lt;/a&gt; in 2015. As of September 2018, LIFT has demarcated and adjudicated approximately 9.9 million of them, approved 8.2 million, printed 7.7 million, and distributed 6.1 million to land holders, meaning that roughly 1.5 million Ethiopian farmers now have registered certificates for the land they farm (an average of almost four parcels per household). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do these certificates offer economic value to the farmers who hold them? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, the certificates provide tenure security, which should lead farmers to invest more in their land, facilitated by greater access to loans and other financial services, such as insurance. With a formal land certificate, smallholders who cannot farm all of their land (for example, elderly landholders), should feel safer renting out unused land, thereby increasing overall productivity in the economy by reducing the amount of underutilized land. LIFT has also supported the Government of Ethiopia in the development of a rural land administration system to maintain the land register through the recording and registration of subsequent land transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, however, several practical challenges inhibit landholders from turning their new certificate to productive uses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, all rural land is vested in the state and the peoples of Ethiopia, so land parcels cannot be legitimately sold from one person to another. Without a formal market for the exchange of land, parcels have limited use as direct collateral for financial institutions because lenders cannot take ownership and recoup their loan losses in case of default. Therefore, financial institutions have not been incentivized to accept land as collateral.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, while Ethiopia does have a culture of informal land rental, the lack of a formal rental market has created asymmetries in information that limit the value of the land to the owners. Having a second-level land certificate in hand certainly reduces the risk to land owners and provides assurance that they can reclaim their land after a rental. But without a formal market, owners lack an efficient price-setting mechanism to maximize rental returns. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third, the Ethiopian Government is skeptical of brokers, seeing it as the Government’s responsibility, rather than a service provider, to provide such services to land holders. Without recognized, certified land rental agents, the rental transaction process has often moved underground, compounding the opaque nature of the market.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fourth, rural landowners are simply unaware of the various economic options available to them by virtue of having a land certificate, since those formal options have never been available before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tackling Obstacles to Land Utilization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take on these challenges, LIFT established an Economic Empowerment Unit (EEU). Using a market systems approach, the EEU analyzes the nature of the land transactions occurring, the supporting services that support these transactions, and the rules and regulations (both formal and informal) that govern them. Focusing primarily on the land collateral and land rental markets, the EEU has worked to address the policy (and informal) regulatory constraints at work in Ethiopia, build up the offer of the service providers, and raise awareness of the value their services offer to holders of land certificates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding financial services, the EEU has advocated that the government recognize the second-level land certificate as providing a means of obtaining collateral based on the value of the production of the land, rather than its sale value—because rural land cannot legitimately be sold. Although comprehensive reform is still pending to legalize this approach at the federal level, certain regional governments are already enacting market-oriented reforms. The regional government of Amhara recently legalized the collateralization of land parcels, making it possible for financial institutions to lend against second-level land certificates, and the EEU is now working with six financial institutions to help them develop associated loan products and train their staff in how to process them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of September 2018‚ 18 months after initiating the services—these institutions had facilitated 7,663 loans with an aggregate value of 222 million Ethiopian birr (£6.5 million). These loans are put to a wide variety of uses. One borrower in Womberma woreda, in the northwest Amhara region, used his 50,000 birr (£1,400) loan to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/land-titles-in-ethiopia-open-doors-to-finance-and-investment/&quot;&gt;buy diesel-operated flour mills&lt;/a&gt; catering to the high demand for milling services nearby. The business is currently turning a profit of 5,000 birr per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/bare.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bare&quot; title=&quot;Alemneh Bare reinvested in his business after obtaining a loan by using his new land certificate as collateral.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to land rental services, the EEU has developed a training course for land rental service providers on how to market their services, negotiate a price between parties, and help renter and rentee register their transaction formally with the woreda (district) land administration office. While it is still not legal for rental service providers to charge for their services, many receive informal payments from the transacting parties, as well as enhanced status in the community as trusted intermediaries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of September 2018, land rental service providers have facilitated 11,901 rental transactions, in turn accelerating the adoption of transaction registration. Participating households are seeing increased income from land that previously went unrented due to the risk of loss, in addition to higher prices for land rental. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stimulate the market for land rental services and to build a commercially viable cadre of service providers, the EEU is running a public awareness campaign to change attitudes on land renting and land brokers. Given the increasing demand from woreda land administration offices for such facilitation services, the EEU is also advocating to build a positive consensus on land rental service providers with regional governments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting the Value in Land Titling</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/putting-the-value-in-land-titling</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Nov 2018 15:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/putting-the-value-in-land-titling</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is a land title worth? The prevailing assumption in development circles is that helping smallholders acquire formal title to the land they farm will help them integrate into formal economic channels, invest more in their property, and access loan financing. But in practice most land titling programs have focused on the process of delivering titles and left the assumption of economic benefits as exactly that—an assumption. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI is no exception. For more than a decade, we have been a leader in developing highly efficient, cost-effective means for registering land at scale and putting land titles in the hands of millions of smallholders, especially in Africa. And we have achieved some &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/delivering-large-scale-land-certification-programmes-lessons-from-rwanda/&quot;&gt;striking successes&lt;/a&gt;. But while there is some evidence of economic and other benefits accruing from those programs, we have found that the farmers are generally slow to put their new titles to use for their economic benefit, especially in more remote rural areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address this issue, two DAI-implemented programs are working explicitly to enable smallholders to leverage titling into tangible economic growth opportunities. These projects—&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-land-investment-transformation-lift&quot;&gt;Land Investment for Transformation (LIFT)&lt;/a&gt; in Ethiopia, a U.K. Department for International Development initiative, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-innovation-agribusiness-inovagro&quot;&gt;Innovations for Agribusiness (InovAgro)&lt;/a&gt;, a Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation project in Mozambique—are beginning to show that land reforms can translate into economic returns.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both LIFT and InovAgro are applying a market systems development approach to drive land utilization in the post-titling phase. Applying a market systems approach starts with defining the transaction—in this case, various forms of land utilization—and the participants in it. For title holders seeking to exploit their property, land utilization might include working with a bank to get a loan or with another farmer to rent out the asset. The market systems approach seeks to understand how well the transaction is proceeding—or not—identify any market failures, diagnose their underlying causes, and then design solutions to address them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As summarized generically in the figure below, these market failures occur either in the supporting functions (information, infrastructure, or supporting services) or the rules (formal and informal) that enforce the market system. Ideally, if the market failures are understood, we can craft solutions to address them and promote a more sustainable and self-driven system that functions without external support.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/m4p.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chart&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to land—especially in countries with less developed land markets—the supporting services (financial institutions, land rental agents, insurance companies, and so forth) are relatively weak, and typically do not immediately understand the sales opportunities presented by engaging with smallholder farmers newly armed with formal title. The increased land security also makes these smallholders better market opportunities for input suppliers and output marketers who typically are not present. At the same time, those farmers are not fully attuned to the economic benefits latent in their new certificates. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these circumstances, the land utilization process needs a jump-start in the form of targeted efforts to raise the awareness of both smallholders and service providers, and to facilitate the process by which these two parties can productively engage with each other. Ultimately, this process of increasing awareness and facilitating the engagement of service providers builds upon itself, spurring more service provision, more service adoption, and more benefits for landholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We invite you to review a pair of brief case studies exploring our experience working to derive value from land titling in Ethiopia and Mozambique:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/case-study-a-market-systems-approach-to-deriving-value-from-land-certificates-in-ethiopia&quot;&gt;A Market Systems Approach to Deriving Value from Land Title in Ethiopia&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;/articles/case-study-overcoming-land-tenure-issues-in-mozambique&quot;&gt;Overcoming Land Tenure Issues to Stimulate Investment in Mozambique&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Land Titles in Ethiopia Open Doors to Finance and Investment</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/land-titles-in-ethiopia-open-doors-to-finance-and-investment</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 18:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/land-titles-in-ethiopia-open-doors-to-finance-and-investment</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While still one of the poorest countries in the world, Ethiopia has made major advances in reducing poverty and increasing agricultural production in recent years. However, the pace of progress is constrained by inefficiencies in the rural land sector, including weak documentation and management of land rights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-land-investment-transformation-lift&quot;&gt;Land Investment for Transformation (LIFT)&lt;/a&gt;, a U.K. Department for International Development (DFID) programme, is tackling this issue with a unique approach—by using a market systems lens. And the benefits of this approach are beginning to bear fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIFT supports the Government of Ethiopia’s efforts in rural land certification to drive investment, increase productive land use, and boost the incomes of rural households. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/market-systems-development-a-primer-on-pro-poor-programming/&quot;&gt;market systems approach&lt;/a&gt; addresses constraints that prevent farmers from increasing their productivity. Covering 14 million parcels of land across Ethiopia’s four highland regions, LIFT is the single largest land governance project in DFID’s portfolio and one of the largest in terms of budget and scale of operation funded by any donor globally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Opening New Doors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The confidence that comes with security of tenure opens up new opportunities. For example, LIFT has developed an individual loan product linked to farmers’ land certificates and is working with microfinance institutions (MFIs) to promote it, enabling farmers to access finance that otherwise has been out of reach in rural areas. Annual interest rates for the loans linked to land certificates issued by LIFT are around 15 to 18 percent, compared to up to 21 percent for group loans from MFIs and up to 120 percent for loans from informal money lenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alemneh Bare, a resident of the Womberma district in the Amhara region, is a father of seven young children. Through LIFT, he obtained a land certificate for his 0.75 hectares of land in 2016. Unable to generate enough revenue for his family’s needs from this parcel of land, Bare got a job as a mechanic at a flour mill in the nearest town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2017, he used his land certificate to obtain a 50,000 Ethiopian birr (around £1,400) loan from the Amhara Credit and Savings Institute. Using the loan and existing savings, Bare was able to purchase two diesel-operated flour mills and establish his own milling business. “I am excited to be self-employed, owning and operating my own enterprise,” he said. “My long-term dream has become a tangible reality.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LIFT%201-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;LIFT 1-1&quot; title=&quot;“I am excited to be self-employed, owning and operating my own enterprise”, says Alemneh Bare, who used his land certificate to obtain a loan. “My long-term dream has become a tangible reality.”&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bare’s business plan is based on meeting the high demand for milling services to neighboring communities. The mill currently offers employment to both him and his spouse. The business is running well, with daily revenue of 1,000 birr (around £28) and an average net profit of 5,000 birr per month (around £140). As a result, taking care of his children and paying school tuition fees is no longer a daunting challenge for him and his wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bare is confident that he will repay his loan without much difficulty, as his investment has already started to pay off. His future plans are to increase his savings and, upon repaying the first loan, to apply for an additional loan to expand and improve his milling operation, as well as engage in dairy farming and cattle fattening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bare’s is one of more than 7,600 loans that have been disbursed through September, worth 222.5 million birr (more than £6 million). At the same time, the loans have allowed the MFIs to leverage more than 21 million birr (around £600,000) in savings, thus increasing their liquidity and allowing them to issue more loans. The MFIs have told the project team they are so happy with this loan product that they are introducing it to non-programme areas, using other land certificates as guarantees—a great example of MFIs expanding and adapting the loan product independently of LIFT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIFT’s other interventions in the rural land market include developing a standard land rental contract and establishing a network of land rental service providers that can facilitate land rental agreements, thus allowing landholders to access a formalized and secure land rental market. To date, more than 430 land rental service providers have facilitated and formally registered nearly 12,000 rental contracts. LIFT estimates that more than 40 percent of people who rent out land are women, often from female-headed households, who are unable to work all of the parcels they hold. Renting out land gives them additional income, and the standard contract and formalization of the agreement offers them security and peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Land Registration at Scale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIFT combines a systematic high-volume strategy to the registering of land parcels with the market systems approach. This combination accelerates and magnifies the impact of improved security of tenure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of September, roughly 10 million parcels of land have been demarcated by LIFT, with more than 6 million certificates issued and in the hands of farmers. The project aims to register and issue 14 million certificates by 2020, recognizing the rights of all rightful land holders, including men and women in married and unmarried households. By the end of the project, a rural land administration system will be operational in 140 of the nearly 700 districts in Ethiopia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LIFT’s high-volume approach to land certification has the added advantage of reducing the average cost per parcel certified. To date, LIFT has achieved an average cost per certificate of £3.75, compared with £4.68 in Rwanda and £20.45 in Mozambique.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women and Girls Advocate for Their Place in Afghanistan’s Social and Political Mainstream</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/women-and-girls-advocate-for-their-place-in-afghanistans-social-and-political-mainstream</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 19:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/women-and-girls-advocate-for-their-place-in-afghanistans-social-and-political-mainstream</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Girls and women in Afghanistan are transitioning away from Taliban-era oppression to attend school, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-women-re-enter-the-economy-as-workers-business-owners/&quot;&gt;get jobs&lt;/a&gt;, and fully participate in mainstream life. Afghan leaders and politicians have enacted national laws to support this movement, but the reality in Afghanistan’s 34 provinces is another matter. Girls and women in too many locales routinely endure child/forced marriage, domestic assault, and injustice, and female leaders become targeted for reprisals. In the space between the national law and local reality, various groups are working to preserve hard-earned gains and advocate for Afghan women. This is the space where the Musharikat program works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Musharikat-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Musharikat-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/afghanistan/promote&quot;&gt;Promote&lt;/a&gt; initiative, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-musharikat&quot;&gt;Musharikat&lt;/a&gt; is building an inclusive network of women’s rights groups across Afghanistan that aims to become a permanent advocate for laws, practices, and public perceptions that affect women’s lives. In the past three years, Musharikat has enlisted 330 organizations and 2,200 women and men in eight issues-based coalitions: Violence Against Women, Access to Education, Access to Economic Opportunities, Women’s Political Participation, Access to Justice, Access to Healthcare, Women in the Peace Process, and Anti-Harassment of Women and Girls. These coalitions are now building support both nationally and in communities for their respective causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among its results, Musharikat has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launched advocacy campaigns for eight issues-based coalitions;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organized two national summits, where government officials and citizen activists affirmed their commitment and devised plans to work together on high-priority issues;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fulfilled 31 grants to Afghan civil society organizations—many of which operate in remote corners of the country—that advocate locally to help Afghan women participate in mainstream society; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Established the Musharikat Knowledge Management Platform, where coalition members post and view information, ask questions, and chat online.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Musharikat-14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Musharikat-14&quot; title=&quot;A voting advocate from Badakhshan addresses the 2018 Musharikat National Summit. Photo: Mariam Alimi, Promote Musharikat.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2018, coalition leaders convened at the second Musharikat National Summit in Kabul, where John Bass, the U.S. Ambassador to Afghanistan, told attendees: “Simply creating new laws does not result in changes to the daily experience of Afghan women. Just having laws in place is not enough; they have to be implemented and executed” for women and society to benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Headquartered in Kabul and operating regional offices in the country’s north, south, east, and west, Musharikat—which means “partnership” or “participation” in Dari and Pashto—practices “learning by doing” with Afghan women and men applying their advocacy skills face to face in meetings with elders, mullahs, parents, officials, and other influencers, and on radio and television. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Musharikat network has trained 4,900 people on the law and women’s rights and hosted awareness-raising sessions with 9,300 more, including youth, community leaders, religious leaders, students, and teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Musharikat-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Musharikat-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;More Women Teaching, More Girls Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s and ’70s, Afghanistan was relatively progressive for women, with many women and girls freely attending school; since the 1990s, warlords and, later, the conquering Taliban subjugated females and banned girls from going to school. The country is slowly recovering from that oppression with assistance from the Musharikat coalitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Access to Education Coalition is advocating to increase the number of women teachers hired to staff girls’ schools, especially in rural areas where there are shortages of teachers, with coalition members appealing to the Ministry of Education and Independent Administrative Reform and Civil Service Commission to reach a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To inform these efforts, coalition members recorded the number of women teachers in their locales and created lists of potential women teachers, which they shared with ministry officials in Kabul. At the coalition’s request, the Ministry of Education in July sent to all provinces a letter directing them to allow coalition members to observe and report on teacher candidate testing, a process historically fraught with corruption and mismanagement. Coalition members have since visited education departments in more than 20 provinces, and before year’s end the coalition will summarize what it observed and present findings and formal recommendations to improve future testing to senior ministry officials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Musharikat-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Musharikat-12&quot; title=&quot;Roundtable discussion at the 2018 Musharikat National Summit in Kabul, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harassed Girls Return to School&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Girls in the Kama district of Nangarhar province were being harassed so much by boys on the way to school that their families decided to keep the girls home. The Training Human Rights Association for Afghan Women—a Musharikat grantee and founding member of the Access to Education Coalition—met with Afghan officials, local community elders, and influential mullahs. Once everyone understood the problem, the group decided that first the elders would talk with the parents of the misbehaving boys. At the same time, the mullahs would deliver Friday sermons directly addressing the importance of girls’ education and the community support that girls need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, 23 girls from the Kama district resumed attending school. “I am pleased that I have been able to support my daughter,” reported one of the girl’s fathers. Kama district school principal Mr. Shafiullah noted a “great change regarding girls’ harassment in the district,” and he sees a large increase in the number of girls enrolling. Similar impacts are being made throughout Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/aside&gt; 

&lt;h2&gt;Helping Women to Vote&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan’s sporadic elections process was halted completely by Taliban rule until 2004; since then, voting for provincial and national representatives has been uneven and frequently impossible for women. The Women’s Political Participation Coalition is working to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coalition sponsored a radio advertising campaign for voter registration that reached one-third of Afghanistan’s population, and members have hosted radio roundtable discussions in 15 provinces. Local members now help women obtain Tazkiras (national identity cards) that allow them to register to vote, monitor registration centers, and lobby local Independent Election Commission representatives when they identify voting centers that are not women friendly—that is, with separate voting areas for women, female staff, short lines, and women’s facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Musharikat-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Musharikat-13&quot; title=&quot;Talking about Musharikat on the radio in Jalalabad, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Recruiting Neighbors, Sharing Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 6th district of Faiz Abad City, Badakhshan, a woman named Hasina wanted to increase women’s participation in the 2018 elections. After talking to neighbors and going door to door, she found 62 women who did not have Tazkiras—the ID cards necessary for registration. Hasina met with the provincial Population Registration Department, which asked her to gather the women in one place so the department could deploy a mobile team to issue Tazkiras. Hasina, a teacher at the local Faizabad Teacher Training College, secured a meeting room there, and staff from the college took advantage as well—in the end nearly 100 people received their Tazkira. Hasina continued her campaign and registered many more women in her district to vote, and shared her experience online via the Musharikat Knowledge Management Platform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What I did gave me strength and I learned that even one person can bring positive change,” Hasina told attendees at the June 2018 Musharikat National Summit. “I am now sure that every member of the [Women’s Political Participation] coalition across the country can bring this positive change.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Musharikat-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Musharikat-11&quot; title=&quot;Discussing plans at the Musharikat regional meeting in Mazar-i-Sharif, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Consolidating Wins, Moving Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 150 coalition members met in June 2018 for the second Musharikat National Summit to set priorities for the next two years. Coalition leaders huddled with government officials vital to securing Musharikat’s gains and achieving future goals.
For the first two days, coalition members analyzed their strengths and weaknesses, developed action plans, publicized Musharikat tools, and prioritized additional women’s issues for future coalitions. This collaboration yielded two—covering the Harassment of Women and Girls and Women in the Peace Process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preventing Child Marriage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Musharikat grantee Labour Spring Organization in Daikundi province worked with the Department of Hajj and Religious Affairs on the issue of child marriage. As a result, the department sent a formal Assurance Letter to all religious leaders in their district urging them to ban child marriage. Thirty-four local imams in Daikundi stepped forward and committed to supporting this initiative with their sermons and practices, and at least four child marriages have been prevented because the imams reported them to the police. These efforts are being supported by USAID Rasana project radio stations, including Radio Daikundi, which broadcast an interview promoting the ban on child marriages that reached 200,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On the Road to Self-Reliance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Musharikat program is providing an outlet for a generation of women to become involved and contribute. It has already mobilized hundreds of women who have never been part of a movement, and many who were already fully capable now say they feel empowered to be part of a critical mass that will help Afghan women across the country. Musharikat has enabled 14,000 women to access training and worked with more than 120 Afghan government entities—local, provincial, and national—in planning and implementation. By project’s end in 2020, Musharikat expects to have enlisted more than 350 civil society organizations and 5,000 activists across all 34 provinces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the national government balances its promised pursuit of women’s equality with the day-to-day realities of elected office, it is crucial that women’s rights stay in the forefront of public consciousness. We intend that Musharikat’s advocacy coalitions will be a self-sustaining and continuous part of Afghanistan’s political landscape long after the project itself has ended.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baseline Study Prompts School Officials to Counter Violence in Honduras</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/baseline-study-prompts-school-officials-to-counter-violence-in-honduras</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 14:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/baseline-study-prompts-school-officials-to-counter-violence-in-honduras</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Too often, in our experience as development professionals, baseline surveys can seem like proforma exercises—dry, mechanical constructs conducted at the beginning of a project, shelved almost as soon as they are done, then dusted off for the midline survey. By the time we conduct the endline, the project is closing. Baseline findings don’t drive programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is far from the case with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/honduras-securing-education&quot;&gt;Asegurando la Educación’&lt;/a&gt;s baseline survey of school-based violence in Honduras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asegurando la Educación (Securing Education) is a five-year, U.S. Agency for International Development project designed to improve access to quality education—ensuring student retention, course completion, and academic performance—by reducing school-based violence in five major cities with the highest incidence of gang- and drug-related violence: Choloma, La Ceiba, San Pedro Sula, Tegucigalpa, and Tela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_72c97e8c-f3d2-49a6-a519-9b18b7b3aff5&quot; title=&quot;School survey&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?x4V&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conducted in April and May of 2018, the survey has become a roadmap for schools to design violence-prevention activities. The survey asked some 6,000 educators, principals, and students from fourth to ninth grades in 66 Honduran schools about their perceptions of security and their firsthand experience of the types and intensity of violent incidents in schools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning in August, just three months after the completion of the survey, Asegurando teams began presenting the findings to the schools: teachers, parents, students, and community members. The response was startling. Below are just four examples of local schools and communities mobilizing to address the challenges facing children and teachers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;San Pedro Sula&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One school in San Pedro Sula, Cortés, borders territory claimed by both the Mara Salvatrucha (MS-13) and Barrio 18 gangs. Territorial disputes have spilled onto the school grounds. In addition to gang violence, students must contend with violence based on gender, sexual orientation, race, or other social dynamics that adversely influence their behavior and academic performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/SanPedroSula%20Chicas_RiveraHernandez_SanPedroSula%20(1).jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SanPedroSula Chicas_RiveraHernandez_SanPedroSula (1)&quot; title=&quot;Schoolgirls from San Pedro Sula.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August, when staff reported that 87 percent of boys and 74 percent of girls feel unsafe going to the restroom, at first the teachers were in denial. Yet students confirmed the finding. “We were shocked to hear about some of these incidents,” said one fifth-grade teacher. “We will take action with the administration and parents to mitigate these instances.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the faculty has increased the monitoring of the restrooms and begun sending students to the washrooms in pairs. “I feel better now that the teachers understand what happens in the bathrooms… Going to the bathroom in pairs will help,” said the student government president.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon learning that 46 percent of female students and 36 percent of male students feel unsafe when leaving school premises at the end of the day, the community approached the local authorities. The police responded by sending officers to patrol the area at dismissal times. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to insecurity at school, young people face poverty, problems at home, and challenges in the broader community. The survey also identified high levels of bullying. These and other factors likely contributed to the survey finding that, in the month leading up to the study, 36 percent of boys felt that life was not worth living. In an attempt to address the bullying at school, the student council got involved. “Student government members will go to classrooms to talk about creating a culture of respect in this school,” said the student government president. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tegucigalpa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one high school in Tegucigalpa, six out of seven teachers reported that drugs such as marijuana and crack cocaine can be found just outside the school walls. Three out of seven said that drugs are available inside the school and four out of seven said alcohol is available at school. And three out of seven have witnessed students taking drugs or alcohol at school, all in the first three or four months of the school year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even before hearing the survey findings, parents and teachers of the high school knew substance abuse was a problem. Drugs are available on the school premises, but educators themselves feared broaching the subject of substance abuse because the drug dealers often misinterpreted counseling as law enforcement. “Most teachers are afraid to talk about drug sales. We have to be very careful,” said one teacher. “Last month, I went out in the hallway to answer a call from my husband and at that moment three students ran past who were being chased by the school guard. Other students immediately accused me of calling the police, and I had to give them my phone to prove that I didn’t. They returned the phone saying, ‘that’s what we like.’” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Asegurando shared the survey results, school officials sought assistance from the National Directorate of Social Intervention (DINIS), the government agency responsible for social protection. DINIS launched an initiative at the high school to train teachers how to conduct practical lessons on substance abuse without raising the suspicions of drug dealers. DINIS is also now providing clinical therapy to students most affected by substance abuse. “We will now be able to give talks to the students on the dangers of drug use,” said the teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_53ea47e9-cba4-4836-b20c-12956f2aa544&quot; title=&quot;Violence in Schools Honduras&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?F1C&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tela&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parents and teachers at Marco Aurelio Soto Primary School in Tela, Atlántida, learned that 60 percent of boys and 35 percent of girls had fallen victim to verbal assaults and 40 percent of boys and 25 percent of girls had been slapped or struck with a fist. In addition, 47 percent of male students had performed some type of self-mutilation with razor blades while 43 percent of the boys and 30 percent of the girls had felt that life was not worth living, all in the previous 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirna López, the school principal, called the findings eye-opening. “Students don’t usually share thoughts of suicide or incidents of physical violence with teachers,” she said. Supported by Asegurando’s university fellows, the Community School Committee—made up of parents, teachers, and students—and Asegurando-trained Educators for Peace conducted the school’s first anti-bullying workshop in October. The project will soon support a school-driven anti-bullying awareness campaign, including a film to be followed by discussion groups to attempt to confront the causes of, and offer solutions to, bullying. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;La Ceiba&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey revealed widespread bullying at Marco Antonio Ponce Primary School in La Ceiba, Atlántida. Some 60 percent of the students had been insulted, 43 percent called names, and 34 percent struck. Finally, 48 percent of boys described themselves as sad and felt life was not worth living while 33 percent had mutilated themselves with razor blades, all in the 30 days prior to the survey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LaCeiba%20Horadeclase_LaCeiba.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;LaCeiba Horadeclase_LaCeiba&quot; title=&quot;A classroom in La Ceiba.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alerted to the rate of bullying and suicidal thoughts in primary schools, parents and teachers decided to show an anti-bullying film, followed by discussions. School officials have also planned an anti-bullying awareness campaign in an attempt to change behavior and attitudes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Educators themselves cannot help but be affected by school-based violence. Three out of seven of the teachers at Marco Antonio Ponce school report that, at times, the classes are uncontrollable and students bully other students over their sexual orientation. Four out of seven report that students fight at school. And three out of seven teachers fear they might be harmed en route to or from school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce stress resulting from a work environment replete with violence, Asegurando is supporting a teacher well-being day that focuses on physical and psychological activities designed to ease stress and strengthen resilience. Principal Thelma Clavasquín said that the administration is well aware that it has neglected the mental health of its teachers. Teacher wellness will be “one of the primary tasks for the 2019 school year… and designing strategies that respond to the needs mentioned in the baseline,” she said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Responsiveness is Key&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asegurando la Educación’s baseline survey has become a tool that shed light on legitimate opportunities for short- and long-term interventions. We are discovering countless programmatic applications for the data and exploring new ways to interpret and analyze the numbers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsiveness of school communities to the survey findings has become the impetus for grassroots conflict-prevention activities driven not by Asegurando, but by the school community itself. Teachers, parents, students, police, and other community members across the country are identifying measures to make schools safer and healthier spaces for students to learn and teachers to teach.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Developing Countries Can Identify and Allocate Resources to Pay for Health Services</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/how-can-developing-countries-identify-and-allocate-resources-to-pay-for-health-services</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 18:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/how-can-developing-countries-identify-and-allocate-resources-to-pay-for-health-services</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Governments in many low- and middle-income countries have committed to provide affordable and high-quality health services to their citizens. To make good on these promises, they need to identify more money for health expenditure and need to invest it more wisely. Our recent policy paper—&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hfgproject.org/financial-management-mechanisms-to-support-increased-government-spending-on-health/&quot;&gt;Financial Management Mechanisms to Support Increased Government Spending on Health&lt;/a&gt;—provides some guidance on how they might do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put the situation in perspective, government spending on health in the low-income countries we considered ranged from $2 to $41 per capita in 2015, while &lt;em&gt;total&lt;/em&gt; spending on health per capita ranged from $17 to $107. The difference is often paid by donors and the low-income patients themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prepared for the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-health-finance-and-governance&quot;&gt;Health Finance and Governance project&lt;/a&gt;, our policy paper explains how public financial management (PFM) mechanisms can be used to help countries increase domestic expenditure in their quest to achieve universal health coverage. Health system stakeholders—policy makers, executives, and senior managers—should learn how these mechanisms work so they can use them to inform and advocate for strategic health spending. These mechanisms are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Government financial management information systems (GFMIS)&lt;/strong&gt; that manage revenue and expenditure;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revenue modeling and forecasting&lt;/strong&gt;, which determine the overall budget envelope that constrains government spending;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium-term planning and budgeting and program- and performance-based budgeting&lt;/strong&gt;—key areas where health system stakeholders can engage in PFM processes and potentially influence budget allocations for public health; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Earmarking&lt;/strong&gt; to ensure that sufficient government funds are allocated to public health, notwithstanding changes in political influences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;GFMIS—Armed With Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GFMIS government accounting software packages manage all types of financial transactions. While cash-strapped countries need a functioning GFMIS to manage their overall finances, GFMIS is also required to implement other PFM mechanisms, including those that support health budgeting specifically. With a properly functioning GFMIS in place, countries can control payments, track expenditures, develop realistic budgets, and share government spending &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/marshaling-the-evidence-to-better-help-developing-countries-improve-and-afford-their-health-services/&quot;&gt;information&lt;/a&gt; to improve accountability and transparency. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But implementing GFMIS has proven challenging in many developing countries due to the limited capacity of institutions, long delays in implementation (for various reasons), and poor data quality. Governments may need to replace or upgrade their GFMIS, provide staff with better training on how to use the systems, and improve data collection and quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put it in checklist form, governments should aim for their GFMIS to: 1) centralize all government financial transactions; 2) be used exclusively by all line ministries, including ministries of health, to process transactions; 3) capture all health expenditure data across the country; 4) prepare timely and complete government financial reporting; 5) fully implement Treasury Single Account—one virtual spending account within the GFMIS for managing government expenditures and payments, and; 6) improve cash management, which can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/philippines-facilitating-public-investment-fpi&quot;&gt;increase fiscal space&lt;/a&gt;—or the flexibility a government enjoys in its spending choices—to allow for more money to be spent on health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Yates-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Yates-1&quot; title=&quot;Health systems training as part of the USAID Haiti Strategic Health Information Systems Program.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Forecasting and Budgeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revenue forecasting is critical. Ministries of finance forecast revenues to guide revenue authorities on collection targets and support the budgeting process. But in many countries, revenue forecasting remains unsophisticated. Inaccurate revenue forecasts create uncertainty in budgeting, regardless of whether the forecasts are too high or low—low forecasts mean more funds are available than anticipated, while high forecasts can cause funds to be reshuffled, potentially away from health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Budgeting mechanisms represent the key area where health system stakeholders can influence the level of public health expenditure. While most countries have introduced some form of medium-term planning and budgeting, these countries—and donors providing technical assistance—should assess how well these PFM mechanisms perform because they provide a foundation for more advanced budgeting techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Program-based budgeting, which itemizes program costs within the health budget, and performance-based budgeting, which sets measurable indicators to those programs, present direct ways for health ministries and agencies to advocate for increased spending. This budgeting enables ministries to design programs to achieve specific public health goals and the budgets needed to meet them. It helps justify budgets based on increased specificity, and its implementation should increase transparency by enabling government to show the link between taxpayer funds and public health outcomes. For health system stakeholders, the ability to tie results to spending year-over-year is crucial to objectively making the case for increased spending on public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some countries are moving toward performance budgeting, but most do not have the ingredients in place to satisfy key preconditions and effectively implement the reform. For example, while the government of Nepal has moved toward performance-based budgeting and sets concrete annual goals, it lacks effective expenditure controls and suffers from rudimentary and inconsistent budgeting processes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many ingredients for performance-based budgeting exist in low- and middle-income countries, they rarely have been implemented robustly or at scale. These countries need to improve human and institutional capacity for performance-based budgeting, develop better monitoring and evaluation capabilities, and enhance the quality of the data that feeds the process. To support their goals of increasing health expenditures, health ministries should be early adopters of performance-based budgeting and work with finance ministries to implement (and benefit from) budget reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Yates-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Yates-3&quot; title=&quot;Community health workers graduate in Nigeria as part of the U.K. Department for International Development&amp;#39;s Women for Health program.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t Turn Your Nose Up at Earmarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earmarks have won a bad reputation for their rigidity and distortive effects on budgeting. However, since government budgeting processes are often susceptible to political pressure, they may be a justifiable means to protect government health funds and demonstrate the government’s commitment to health. Health funding, in particular, requires significant and stable &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/when-tax-reform-leads-to-increased-funding-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;revenue collections&lt;/a&gt;, which will affect the choice of the revenue source for the earmark—payroll and consumption taxes, for example, may be appropriate. Policy goals may also come into play, such as using taxes on activities deemed harmful to public health, including alcohol and tobacco sales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, countries such as Egypt, El Salvador, Philippines, and Tanzania use payroll taxes to fund public health programs, including different forms of national health insurance programs, while Ghana and Chile provide examples of earmarking value-added tax for public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, PFM mechanisms and PFM reforms can help national governments maximize the benefits of health spending, justify health budget allocations, and assure citizens and taxpayers that their resources will be well used. In &lt;em&gt;Financial Management Mechanisms to Support Increased Government Spending on Health&lt;/em&gt;, we hope to guide governments and donors on how best to use these mechanisms and achieve their health objectives, including for universal health care, and ultimately assist developing countries to be more self-reliant.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demand for Private Capital Draws USAID Units to INVEST Program</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/demand-for-private-capital-draws-usaid-units-to-invest-program</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/demand-for-private-capital-draws-usaid-units-to-invest-program</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) units around the world are increasingly asking for specialized support to mobilize private capital—requests now being met by the agency’s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-the-invest-project&quot;&gt;INVEST&lt;/a&gt; program. In less than one year, USAID missions, bureaus, and other operating units have hired the INVEST team to support 17 initiatives to develop market opportunities. These initiatives—to address demand for energy, food, health care, water, and other global needs—are under way or already completed in Afghanistan, Asia, Haiti, India, and North and Sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combined commitments of $37 million by USAID units to pursue these initiatives represent 40 percent of the INVEST goal set by USAID. A two-year project with three option years, INVEST’s success has already spurred USAID to green-light a third year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based in Washington, D.C., the INVEST team facilitates the expertise in finance and investment, technical subjects, and local knowledge required to generate investment pipelines and mobilize investment capital. INVEST orchestrates a network of specialists—more than 130 firms so far—that fill various niches to help USAID explore these opportunities. This network includes strategy advisory firms such as Tideline and Dalberg, transaction advisory firms including CrossBoundary and Open Capital Advisors, and innovative finance firms such as Kois Invest and Third Sector. These and other partners provide the appropriate mix of financial rigor and technical specialization required to tailor assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“[USAID is] embracing the ingenuity and the entrepreneurship that private enterprise offers and harnessing the efficiencies and effectiveness that private-sector competition and market forces can unlock. And this is something private enterprise is eager to do alongside us.”&lt;strong&gt;—USAID Administrator Mark Green&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreign.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/062018_Green_Testimony.pdf&quot;&gt;June 20, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent “buy-ins” by USAID units for market assessments and pipeline development, design and structuring support, and transaction advisors exemplify the early demand for INVEST’s services. They include initiatives to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitate trade between Afghanistan and India;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a first-of-its-kind investment mobilization platform in Haiti for sectors such as agriculture, housing, sanitation, and water;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze capital opportunities that benefit women in Ghana, Kenya, Nigeria, Senegal, and South Africa (USAID’s Office of Gender Equality and Women’s Empowerment); and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accelerate the solar off-grid energy marketplace in Uganda, building on the accomplishments of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-center-development-innovation-professional-management-services&quot;&gt;Center for Development Innovation&lt;/a&gt; project under the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scalingoffgrid.org/&quot;&gt;Scaling Off-Grid Energy Grand Challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These and other USAID investments reflect &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/blended-finance-in-actionhow-usaid-leveraged-100-million-in-east-africa/&quot;&gt;growing determination&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/eu-launches-26-billion-fund-to-attract-investment-in-the-european-neighbourhood-and-africas-fragile-states/&quot;&gt;donor community&lt;/a&gt; to enhance development impact by means of “blended finance”—blending private capital with donor-funded local expertise and risk-mitigation measures. The goal is to achieve development objectives by creating profitable partnerships while advancing countries on their journeys to self-reliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----INVEST-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----INVEST-2&quot; title=&quot;The USAID East Africa Trade and Investment Hub has facilitated $59 million in private sector investments in sectors such as food warehousing and logistics.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bull Market for Global Needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in mid-2017, INVEST has grown from a lean start-up to managing a growing portfolio of partners and activities. As manager of the INVEST network platform, DAI convenes and facilitates buy-ins by helping USAID units refine their “ask,” identify and engage the appropriate advisors through competitive procurements, and support implementation, including monitoring, evaluation, learning, and thought leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;INVEST is designed to operate in locales that have less-than-ideal investment climates yet have growing populations that require products and services. In addition to the initiatives cited above, the INVEST team is pursuing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health-Focused Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID missions in India, Liberia, and Tanzania worked with INVEST to deploy an investment roadmap and guidance tool to address high-priority health objectives in areas such as community and maternal health, nutrition, and tuberculosis. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The USAID Global Health Center for Innovation and Impact engaged INVEST to assess and recommend financial models for tackling cholera in Haiti.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Investment Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/India engaged INVEST to assess the energy, health, tuberculosis, and WASH sectors and design a new, blended finance-focused funding vehicle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID’s Office of Private Capital and Microenterprise, Bureau for Food Security, and USAID/Tunisia have partnered to better understand and leverage the strategic corporate investment trend, including: favorable models and structures in agriculture, energy, and water; appropriate support for these models; structures to attract investors and ensure replicability and additionality; and suitable corporate investment and partnership opportunities already in existence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initiatives in Energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/Haiti and the Government of Haiti are pursuing a public-private partnership for Caracol Power Utility’s operations, maintenance, and management; INVEST is providing transaction advice, including due diligence and transaction structuring, transaction implementation, and bidding. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/Kenya and Power Africa are working with INVEST to help household solar systems and off-grid companies attract investment and expand connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agricultural Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/Democratic Republic of the Congo engaged INVEST to explore opportunities and constraints associated with blended finance and the approaches and tools available to support investment in agricultural value chains and responsible mining in Eastern Congo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training and Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID’s Office of Private Capital and Microenterprise and Center for Transformational Partnerships are developing a learning strategy on private sector engagement to deepen USAID’s capacity in market-based solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----INVEST%203Finette-QA-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----INVEST 3Finette-QA-1&quot; title=&quot;Digital health products are among those that the INVEST team are helping USAID units to explore.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Developed for Business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalizing on unexplored economic opportunities in developing countries &lt;em&gt;requires partners&lt;/em&gt;—ones with local knowledge, financial resources, and entrepreneurial spirit, just for starters. The co-creation team that conceived INVEST in 2017 sought a long-term solution that will enable USAID to quickly engage new partners and mobilize private capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and investors seek capital supply, investment-ready projects, access to affordable and appropriate risk-mitigation instruments, and reasonable firm-level transaction costs. Locally, however, capital mobilization can be inhibited by a lack of skills among and imperfect information from financial intermediaries and advisors, immature market conditions, and lack of connective tissue among market actors, even where demand is strong for necessities such as energy, food, health care, and water, not to mention the jobs these sectors create. Meeting these demands can increase economic activity at scale and deliver the benefits that come with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it enters year two, INVEST is testing and scaling up approaches to blended finance, creating value for its USAID clients while using inclusive procurement and contracting mechanisms adapted for private sector partners. Meanwhile, INVEST’s Washington-based team is aggregating the experts, experiences, data, and best practices on blended finance that were previously scattered around the world. Together, these successes and activities are positioning USAID for the long term to facilitate the blended finance solutions necessary for sustainable, inclusive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afghan Women Re-Enter the Economy as Workers, Business Owners</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-women-re-enter-the-economy-as-workers-business-owners</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-women-re-enter-the-economy-as-workers-business-owners</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Afghanistan transitions toward a market-driven economy and away from one supported by foreign assistance, jobs will inevitably be lost. The Afghan Ministry of Labor, Social Affairs, Martyred, and Disabled predicts that 4 million jobs will be needed over the next five years to replace lost jobs and absorb the rising generation of graduates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand is increasing for entrepreneurial energy and new thinking to address these market needs, and women are essential to helping fill this void. After three decades of low employment for Afghan women—mostly in the agricultural sector—the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-women-in-the-economy&quot;&gt;Promote: Women in the Economy (WIE)&lt;/a&gt; program is opening doors for women-led enterprises to grow and for women to enter the workforce and launch startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results so far have been encouraging. Since its 2015 launch, WIE has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Placed almost 7,000 women in internships and apprenticeships, especially in fields such as teaching and healthcare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awarded another 1,300 women scholarships to train in areas such as finance and banking, information technology, and retail sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enabled more than 3,000 of these women to be hired full time. Another 54,000 women have registered for WIE services. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/297173022&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As importantly, more than 300 businesses that are either women-owned or with 30 percent women employment have obtained WIE technical assistance, industry-specific business skills training, and increased access to finance and markets. Of those benefitting from two years of WIE assistance, half reported at least a 40 percent increase in revenue, and 22 percent reported growing from a small to a medium-sized enterprise (more than 50 employees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“During our first outreach, the goal was to attract 50 applicants; we were shocked when we received 250 inquiries. Facts like this prove the willingness of women toward entrepreneurship; with a little incubation support, women entrepreneurship can be the next boom in our country.”&lt;/strong&gt; — Fahim Didar, founder of Startup Valley, Afghanistan’s first private business incubator for female entrepreneurs, which operates with a grant from WIE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-1&quot; title=&quot;Massoma Husseini, owner of Frogh Event Management, presents findings for the Access to Markets Panel at the Forward Together: National Businesswomen&amp;#39;s Summit.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Business Summit Inspires New Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2018 in Kabul, 140 businesswomen from 21 Afghan provinces convened for the Forward Together: National Business Women’s Summit, organized by WIE. They discussed operational, marketing, and management issues and business environment challenges, including accessing finance and new markets, registering and licensing businesses, managing taxes, developing skills among women in the workforce, packaging products, and improving business services and the business enabling environment for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-3&quot; title=&quot;Dr. Abdullah Abdullah, Chief Executive of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, after speaking at the National Business Women’s Summit.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Ministers from the ministries of Women’s Affairs and Commerce and Industry attended the VIP closing session, where H.E. Dr. Abdullah Abdullah, the Chief Executive of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/afghanistan/news-information/press-releases/Apr-19-2018-USAID-Supports-Afghan-Women-owned-Businesses&quot;&gt;emphasized full government support&lt;/a&gt; for the long-term strategies and reforms needed to assist Afghan businesswomen. The summit yielded a blueprint for action that WIE and others are acting on today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI incorporated participants’ feedback into the final year of WIE programming, which ends in June 2019. One new initiative is the Finance Corps, which will help women-led businesses improve their financial literacy and management, bookkeeping systems, inventory and pricing, investment decisions, and operational efficiency. In addition, WIE is planning a product development service that will teach Afghan MBA graduates, consultants, and service providers to assist women’s businesses in improving product quality, packaging, and regulatory compliance. The service will initially focus on the food processing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/WIE----2018-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WIE----2018-11&quot; title=&quot;MBA Corps assisting commercial garment retailer.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Women Lenders Spark New Lending&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summit highlighted how women who own businesses or are self-employed need better access to financing. One way to tackle this long-term problem is for more women to serve in mid- and senior-level positions in banking, microfinance, and commercial lending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 100 young women in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif have completed WIE’s Microfinance Training Program, 53 of whom have been hired full-time within the microfinance institutions where they apprenticed or at a similar institution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing the number of women in the finance sector, particularly in decision-making and lending roles, will make it more comfortable for other women to seek out financial services, many for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the Microfinance Training Program inspired WIE to design the Women in Commercial Banking activity, which aims to increase the presence and roles of women in banking, first in Kabul and then in other regions. Comprehensive classroom training will be followed by placement in three-month internships in commercial banks, where WIE anticipates 20 percent of these women will be retained as full-time employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----wie-2018-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----wie-2018-2&quot; title=&quot;Access to Finance Matchmaking Roundtable in Mazar-i-Sharif.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WIE’s Access to Finance (A2F) Matchmaking Roundtables have helped businesses learn about borrowing and facilitated mutually beneficial relationships between their representatives and lenders. Through June 2018, WIE had hosted 30 A2F awareness-raising events in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif, leading to 157 small loans, which combined with WIE’s direct-loan facilitation services are worth approximately US$170,000. These loans are typically used to buy the fixed assets needed to help a business grow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small-business lending is catching on—according to the Afghanistan Microfinance Association, a WIE grantee, as of December 2017 more than 77,000 women held active loans with financial institutions in 18 provinces of Afghanistan, representing 39 percent of the microfinance sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-7&quot; title=&quot;Regional trade fair in Mazar-i-Sharif.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Promoting Sales and Familiarity Through Trade Fairs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional trade fairs have proven effective at introducing Afghan women to the private sector and formal economy. These exhibitions have helped WIE clients find customers, suppliers, and contractors and improve their understanding of doing business. Over the past year, WIE organized five Forward Together: Women in Business Regional Trade Fairs—one each in the regional hubs of Kandahar, Jalalabad, Mazar-i-Sharif, Herat, and Kabul. Each event featured 25 to 30 women-owned or -managed businesses, with each representative first mentored in best practices for trade fair business and sales, followed by the actual experience and chance to network with buyers, distributors, and agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best-performing businesses earned a trip to the First Women Power Expo, held in June 2018 in Kabul. Nearly 100 WIE client businesses participated in the four-day national trade fair, held prior to the Eid holidays, Afghanistan’s busiest retail season. These included enterprises in jewelry/gemstones, garment and handicraft manufacture, dairy and food processing, business service providers, ICT and mobile app providers, and education—sectors where women are particularly active. Many of these businesses were participating in a national trade event for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On-site sales by WIE client businesses topped US$50,000 at the national event and $125,700 for all events combined. More significantly, they also signed 1,500+ wholesale or supply contracts, representing future transactions of approximately US$5.5 million, with another 3,000+ potential contracts in negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----WIE-2018-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----WIE-2018-6&quot; title=&quot;Startup Valley Business Incubator graduating class in May 2018.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Professionalizing Women-Led Startups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any economy, fresh business energy and thinking can forge new avenues for growth. WIE’s entrepreneurial workshops and learning programs have introduced aspiring entrepreneurs to experienced counterparts who have successfully navigated the startup process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kabul, two business incubators—Startup Valley (a WIE grantee) and Founder Institute—have graduated nearly 50 startups, many of which are woman-owned or -led, creating more than 200 jobs. These include startups in mobile applications and other IT solutions, online retail sales, graphic design, legal services, agricultural consulting, dairy and food processing, and light manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These and other emerging businesses have benefited from WIE’s MBA Corps program, which demonstrates the value of trained managers to owners of small and medium-sized women’s enterprises, some of which cling to traditional practices of retaining family or clan members instead of employing professional managers. WIE has matched MBA graduates with 58 client businesses in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif. Under a six-month agreement, a WIE mentor, the MBA graduate, and the business owner work to ensure each brings value to the respective enterprise and each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-9&quot; title=&quot;Women in Herat participate in an exercise to assess their professional strengths and weaknesses.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Sustainable, Generational Economic Growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustaining the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/out-of-hiding-assisting-young-educated-women-in-afghanistan-to-finally-enter-the-workforce/&quot;&gt;participation of women in Afghanistan’s mainstream economy&lt;/a&gt; requires a long-term, holistic approach. WIE incorporates youth into training programs so older and younger businesswomen and trainees learn from one another. As businesses owned or managed by women become more confident and vocal, and enter the forefront of Afghanistan’s business community, this movement will pave the way for more women with a business idea to step forward or seek skills training. Many of WIE’s client businesses start as small, home-based ventures, become viable with strategic assistance, and, in turn, create jobs. WIE considers no venture too small to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/WIE----Devs-2018-8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WIE----Devs-2018-8&quot; title=&quot;Ultrasound training in Kabul.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time has come to change the mindsets of Afghans—especially young ones—from being observers of government-sponsored programs to becoming employers and job creators through their own efforts. Afghanistan’s government, through its Women’s Economic Empowerment National Priority Program, is on board, though translating that commitment into practice requires practical assistance. By enabling more women to enter the formal economy and start and grow businesses, USAID’s Promote: Women in the Economy is laying a foundation for Afghanistan to sustainably create jobs, grow its economy, and deliver stability and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jordan Embraces Renewables to Fuel its Economy</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/jordan-embraces-renewables-to-fuel-its-economy</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/jordan-embraces-renewables-to-fuel-its-economy</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jordan needs to grow its economy. More than 700,000 of its young people—&lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/%20SL.UEM.1524.ZS&quot;&gt;39 percent&lt;/a&gt; of the available labor force ages 15 to 24—are without a job. Many have good educations and are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/addressing-jordans-youth-unemployment-bubble-usaid-program-aligns-workforce-with-emerging-opportunities/&quot;&gt;holding out for high-quality employment&lt;/a&gt;. Jordan is also hosting an enormous influx of Syrian refugees, which has helped swell its population from 7.5 million in 2011 to 10 million today. Many of these newcomers are also seeking work. But Jordan is almost completely reliant on imported oil and gas for its energy, limiting its ability to grow the economy and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-competitiveness-program-jcp&quot;&gt;Jordan Competitiveness Program (JCP)&lt;/a&gt; analyzed Jordan’s energy potential as part of the U.S. Agency for International Development’s support for the Kingdom. The analysis found that improving energy self-sufficiency alone could create 13,300 jobs in Jordan—4,200 in centralized renewable energy such as wind- and solar-power farms, 3,900 in decentralized (local) renewable energy generation, and 5,200 in supporting efficient energy use through insulation, better windows and lighting, and improved systems and machinery. Creating these renewable energy sources is projected to save the country 3.1 million barrels annually in imported oil. The analysis also documented a 25 percent average annual increase in demand for engineers and technicians to design, install, and maintain solar- and wind-powered systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The JCP team has since assisted Jordan in putting these recommendations to work. Today, Jordan is leading the Middle East and North Africa in &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.bnef.com/new-energy-outlook/&quot;&gt;renewable energy growth&lt;/a&gt; according to &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg New Energy Finance&lt;/em&gt;, and is ranked &lt;a href=&quot;http://global-climatescope.org/en/country/jordan/#/enabling-framework&quot;&gt;third out of 71 countries worldwide&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-4&quot; title=&quot;The Oasis500 CleanTech bootcamp assisted by the USAID Jordan Competitiveness Program promoted startups and facilitated access to investors.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Clean Tech Emerges as an Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan possesses scant natural resources. As a result, it imports 96 percent of its oil and gas. While this makes the country’s economy highly vulnerable to market and geopolitical forces, Jordan is blessed with one of the world’s highest solar irradiance levels—necessary for producing solar energy at scale. Jordan also has substantial potential in hilly areas for wind-generated power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assist Jordan down this path, the JCP team, which began its work in 2013, has helped mobilize US$3.2 million in private sector and government spending for solar panels and associated needs such as metering. JCP has helped 18 factories conduct detailed energy audits, which produced the information they required to finance energy efficiency upgrades, using loans made through institutions such as Jordan Ahli Bank, where JCP trained loan officers on the responsible financing of clean-tech projects, which takes into account energy savings and other factors. JCP also supported the Wasateia Municipality and Irbid Speciality hospitals as they made solar-energy investments that have now achieved financial closure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy audits that made these and other financing transactions possible were conducted through Jordan’s Energy and Environmental Sustainability (EES) unit that was established with JCP support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-wind.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-wind&quot; title=&quot;The Tafila Wind Farm was built with International Finance Corporation support and inaugurated by the Kingdom of Jordan in 2015. It produces enough energy to power 80,000 homes. Photo: Dominic Chavez/IFC.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Helping Jordan Meet New Demand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To meet Jordan’s increasing demand for renewable energy engineers, JCP partnered with EDAMA, a Jordanian business association, to launch energy training courses certified by the Association of Energy Engineers. This initiative helped certify more than 200 Jordanian professionals through programs such as the Renewable Energy Professional curriculum. Notably, JCP sponsored two waves of female engineers to acquire the international certification—64 women in all—in sought-after courses such as Certified Energy Manager, the world’s most recognized energy certification. These certifications have improved young Jordanians’ chances for getting hired in this growing sector, and their certifications are expected to help employers compete for international and regional contracts. Strengthening Jordan’s clean energy workforce has helped improve the country’s reputation as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://oxfordbusinessgroup.com/news/jordan-sees-rising-investment-clean-technology&quot;&gt;investment destination for clean tech projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-1&quot; title=&quot;The first electric vehicle charging station in Jordan was unveiled at the King Hussein Business Park.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pioneering Use of Electric Vehicles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years, the JCP team helped Jordan &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0DKmx1WV33o&quot;&gt;usher its electric vehicle industry&lt;/a&gt; from the drawing room to the showroom. JCP has &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/plugging-in-to-jordans-rising-demand-for-electric-cars/&quot;&gt;promoted electric vehicle charging stations&lt;/a&gt; by developing new regulations that enable private citizens or businesses to establish, own, or operate electric vehicle charging stations. With charging stations about to pop up at more locations, such as shopping malls, consumers are freer to consider electric vehicles. JCP &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/1.%20USAID%20JCP%20Competitiveness%20Brief%20-%20Building%20a%20New%20Electric%20Vehicle%20Industry%20-%20FINAL%20(Branded)%5B1%5D.pdf&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; that the industry can attract $3 billion in investment in the next decade to develop charging stations and infrastructure, electric vehicle dealerships, and the related support services needed to maintain the thousands of electric vehicles on Jordan’s roads. In fact, BMW and Tesla have already established related operations in Jordan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/M9rxRCfGfQANrLXKqrS4&quot; title=&quot;Jordan Electric Vehicles&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?7zI&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Energy Self-Reliance is Transformational&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to energy—and thus electricity—can dramatically improve people’s lives. Being able to turn on a reading lamp, for example, light up a town center, or power up enterprises small and large. While some of DAI’s work specifically addresses energy—notably our work in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/polseff-legacy-lower-energy-bills-for-businesses-across-poland-a-financing-model-to-scale-and-replicate/&quot;&gt;energy finance&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/helping-eastern-partnership-countries-meet-their-voluntary-commitments-to-reduce-emissions-address-climate-change/&quot;&gt;reducing emissions&lt;/a&gt;—all developing countries can benefit from better energy availability and more efficient use, including in sectors such as farming and agribusiness, water and sanitation, health, and, in Jordan’s case, job creation, post-conflict transition, and refugee integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-2&quot; title=&quot;Green Job Fair at the Landmark Hotel linked companies that work in the green technology sector with professionals and graduates who have relevant skills.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to its own unemployed, Jordan since 2011 has seen 1.4 million refugees cross its border from neighboring Syria. Half are registered and living mostly in encampments, while the other half have been absorbed by Jordan’s cities and communities. While this influx has &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/calculating-syrian-refugee-crisis-fiscal-crisis/&quot;&gt;strained Jordan’s resources&lt;/a&gt;, the country has been working with international donors and investors to recast this situation into an economic development opportunity. To do so, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-we-keep-the-promisemobilizing-business-on-the-refugee-frontline-in-jordan/&quot;&gt;Jordan Compact was created&lt;/a&gt; to support the Jordanian private sector in industries such as garment manufacture, plastics, and agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of its assistance to the Compact, DAI identified these sectors of potential competitive advantage and the barriers—including legal, policy, and regulatory—to developing them, one of which is the availability of energy. Jordan has fully embraced its need to develop its clean energy sector and take the journey to energy self-reliance. We believe the country will eventually achieve its clean-energy potential. And in time, it may even be able to export solar- and wind-powered electricity to neighbors in need such as Lebanon, Palestine, and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keep Up the Fight for High-Quality Education for All in Pakistan</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/keep-up-the-fight</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 19:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/keep-up-the-fight</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After more than five years of campaigning for the right of every Pakistani child to receive a quality education, &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; ended on August 31. Before we go, we should explain why the campaign is ending, and more importantly, we should thank the people that made this campaign as effective as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we began this journey on February 13, 2013, we had one overarching objective: to make education a more meaningful part of the political discourse in Pakistan. We promised DFID, the U.K. government department that funded &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;, that everything the campaign will do will serve the end of ensuring that education grows in importance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, there have been several changes in how education is perceived and treated in Pakistan. In the budget for fiscal year 2013/2014, all four provinces and the federal government allocated a total of just under PKR580 billion (GBP3.6 billion). In the fiscal year 2017/2018, total allocations increased to more than Rs. 900 billion (GBP5.6 billion). Over 4 million children have been added to the school rolls across the country since 2013. Teacher absenteeism has decreased dramatically in many parts of the country. And no teacher anywhere in Pakistan is hired without a test of their basic cognitive abilities through either the National Testing Service or a similar standardized metric. But these changes are a small start of a longer journey.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;’s role was to change the conversation about education for the better. We began tracking coverage of education in the print media in 2013 and tracked it until June 2018. In 2013, there were an average of 133 newspaper stories every month. The average number of stories per month so far in 2018 has been 1,016. This represents a nearly eight times increase in coverage of education. Our key objective to make education a more meaningful part of the political discourse in Pakistan has been met. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pursued this objective by working with you, by trying to inform you, by trying to engage you, sometimes by trying to provoke you, and sometimes trying to inspire you. You were the head and the feet, and the mind and heart of the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign. You were &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-2-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-2-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great campaigns have a clear start date, and a clear end date: Ours has arrived. But great causes never cease being important. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you believe that all Pakistani children should have the same opportunity as the luckiest children anywhere on the planet. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you believe that every Pakistani parent should be able to have full color, true black, 4k dreams for their children—and that no parent’s dream for her child should be limited by the lack of a decent education. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you believe that real reform in education starts with government schools and ends with them, too. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because 25 million children out of school was unacceptable in 2014, and 22.8 million is unacceptable in 2018. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because television channels used to think that nobody watches TV shows about education, but YOU watched them. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you forced the two biggest political parties in our country to fight each other on the issue of education—something that had never happened before. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign, in 2013, when you wrote more than 10,000 letters to politicians asking them to do more for education, and you were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign in 2018, when the winning party’s leader made children a central part of his first address to the nation. You were &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; this whole time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-1-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-1-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many nonprofit and nongovernmental organizations have been on this journey with us. They will continue to do amazing work. Many government officials, especially in the provincial capitals, made education a matter of personal pride. They will not stop serving our great country. Many politicians took on the issue of education as one that was important to them and their constituents. They will not stop working to serve the people. Perhaps most of all, every news channel, every reporter, every anchor, and every channel owner that we ever approached to make education a more important part of their coverage obliged. They will not stop informing, provoking and inspiring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout all of this, our digital footprint has been among the most carefully curated spaces we have engaged with. Our Facebook page, with more than 3 million followers, is the place that motivated us every day: young Pakistanis, engaging with serious content, in a serious manner. Our &lt;em&gt;Taleem Do&lt;/em&gt; website and application for the 2018 election were the final pushes for the campaign to try—as one government was going out, and another was coming in—to ensure that education remained an important part of the conversation. As we hand over our Facebook page and other digital assets to DFID, we are humbled by how impactful these platforms have been in engaging you, informing you, and once in a while, provoking and inspiring you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----4%20(1)-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----4 (1)-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign ends, new narratives in the struggle to ensure quality education for all Pakistani children are emerging. &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; incubated the Pak Alliance for Maths and Science, a collective of more than 50 civil society organizations, businesses and government bodies—so that Pakistani children are provided with more and better opportunities to learn 21st century cognitive skills. We have also worked with almost two dozen local campaigns, originally initiated by &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;, and now coming into their own. They will take forward the important conversations about access to school at the middle and high school levels, about the link between nutrition and cognition, about better utilization and better use of public funds for education, and most of all, about quality and learning outcomes in the weeks, months and years to come. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing gives us more confidence about the future of education reforms in Pakistan than knowing this one simple truth: since you were &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; all along, you will continue to argue and fight for every Pakistani child’s right to a high-quality education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your voice has made a big difference, and it needs to continue to do so. Please don’t ever stop demanding a better future for Pakistani children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Mosharraf Zaidi and the entire &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;&lt;p&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/pakistan-transforming-education-pakistan-tep&quot;&gt;Transforming Education in Pakistan (TEP)&lt;/a&gt; programme was launched in 2013 to address a severe problem: 25 million school-aged children in Pakistan were not attending school, due in part to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children/&quot;&gt;complacency in government&lt;/a&gt; regarding education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past five years, TEP amassed an impressive following for its political advocacy and media campaign: &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan.&lt;/em&gt; The campaign focused on prompting parents and communities in Pakistan to demand &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6nciO3A-MhI&quot;&gt;high-quality education&lt;/a&gt; and urging elected and appointed officials to take tangible steps toward its provision for children ages 5 through 16, as Pakistani law requires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; succeeded in elevating education issues into the political discourse, promoting data-informed journalism on education, pioneering ground-breaking publications, and lobbying the Pakistani government to research, calculate, and publish a nationally accepted number for out-of-school children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID)-funded programme wound down in August, its champion, Team Leader Mosharraf Zaidi, wrote this farewell letter to the people of Pakistan documenting the movement’s impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Placing Women at the Center of Water Supply Management in Kenya</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/placing-women-at-the-center-of-water-supply-management-in-kenya</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 13:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/placing-women-at-the-center-of-water-supply-management-in-kenya</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Christine Kanini checks water meters on her weekly rounds, she recalls that 18 months earlier she could not aspire to this job. “We had mainly male meter readers,” Kanini said. “Then I was promoted to this position from gate keeping. I am happy with the work.” Over the past year, the Wote Water and Sewerage Company (WOWASCO), which serves the small city of Wote in south-central Kenya, has opened up opportunities for women such as Kanini in fields that were previously deemed suited for men only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes are part of gender initiatives supported by the U.S. Agency for International Development’s Kenya Integrated Water, Sanitation and Health (KIWASH) project. To improve the lives and health of 1 million Kenyans across nine counties, the five-year project (2015–2020) focuses on developing and managing sustainable water, sanitation, and hygiene (WASH) services. Central to this objective is ensuring that everyone—especially women—has equal access to the opportunities created through improved WASH services, including jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-2&quot; title=&quot;Christine Kanini, right, speaking with a customer in Makueni County, Kenya. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Water Services Affect Women&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men and women benefit from water differently—both as users and water services providers. As users, given their conventional primary role in child care, domestic work, and water collection, women and girls are most disadvantaged and even put at risk when they must travel several kilometers or queue for many hours at local kiosks to gather the water they need to complete daily chores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these adverse conditions have become widely known, women’s potential roles in water services are less understood. Specifically, women’s lack of engagement and voice in providing water services has detrimentally affected their economic opportunity in the sector—especially their ability to get jobs—and limited their influence on investment and service decisions. Kenya typifies this sectoral imbalance. Despite women’s heavy role in water use, men in Kenya have dominated almost every water utility and related decision authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationally, Kenya has made significant progress toward improving these inequities: its new constitution from 2010 lists access to water and sanitation as a basic human right and mandates equal gender representation in these public sectors. Likewise, the government’s Vision 2030 plan recognizes that gender equality will play a critical role in achieving the country’s development goals. 
Despite these stipulations, however, progress has been slow. To help the country increase gender equity, KIWASH analyzed 13 water utilities across the nine counties where we work to determine the barriers women face as both employees and customers and to identify areas for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-6&quot; title=&quot;Cooperative Bank of Kenya staff received training on water sector financing and ways to improve loan quality and reduce risk. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Improving the Gender Ratio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH’s assessment found that none of the 13 water utilities met the minimum requirement of 30 percent female representation—whether on the Board of Directors or in corporate or technical management roles. None were led by women or had in place approved gender or sexual harassment policies. In addition, utility employees generally perceived that discrimination existed in recruitment, job placement, and advancement, and in the treatment of pregnant or lactating women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH worked with each utility to develop Gender Equity Action Plans; these plans established improvement goals, training on gender equality awareness, and policies and recruitment strategies to attract female leaders and employees. Several of these utilities have now drafted or implemented new recruitment policies that stipulate gender ratios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Nairobi City Water and Sewerage Company (NCWSC) employs 3,000 people. One year ago, only two of eight of the company’s leadership positions were held by women; today, men and women are equally represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vicky Maiyo, the Donor Project Officer with NCWSC, described the progress she is starting to see. “Initially, leadership in the utility company was a male affair,” Maiyo said. “After the trainings, we have four women heading the regions and three of our six managers are women. And with technical work, like those operating water tankers, excavators, or driving heavy commercial vehicles, there is [increased female] representation where before those jobs were dominantly male.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-4&quot; title=&quot;Water company staff in Mbooni, Makueni County, received training to reduce revenue losses caused by leaks, theft, poor billing systems, and weak metering policies. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Women Doing a Great Job&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KIWASH team has heard reports that women water staffers take more time to explain service delivery issues to customers and are particularly effective in collecting revenue, where customer relations are key. In one striking example, the best performer at NCWSC was a female staff member who collected KES120 million (US$1.2 million) in one month, setting a company record for monthly collection. Some water company staff have noted that women leaders have helped improve discipline among staff through closer monitoring and engagement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wote, WOWASCO did not meet the 30 percent female representation required by law. WOWASCO is now encouraging and seeking out qualified women to apply for vacant board positions and lobbying the county government to consider recruiting women to its Public Service Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two female WOWASCO staff were recently allowed to join the formerly all-male meter-reading team. They received on-the-job training and are now enjoying interacting with customers and learning more about the water delivery part of the business. “I like this job,” Kanini said as she drove from one house to the next in Wote Town, speaking with customers and reading meters. WOWASCO Managing Director Joseph Kuti is also pleased with the changes he is seeing. “We thought these were men’s jobs,” Kuti said. “Yet Christine performs well in her job. Her zone has the least complaints.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Addressing Sexual Harassment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH carries out quarterly assessments of water services providers to track improvements in gender equality mainstreaming. These assessments are premised on short- and medium-term action plans developed during KIWASH trainings. As sexual harassment affects women’s dignity as well as water provider performance and utility/customer relations, sexual harassment needs to be tackled head on. KIWASH worked with the utilities to conduct 11 training sessions and develop action plans that raise awareness of what constitutes sexual harassment and how it harms people and job performance. KIWASH is now advising water companies on how to develop sexual harassment policies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-1&quot; title=&quot;Vicky Maiyo, seated center, and women officers from the biggest water company in Kenya after gender mainstreaming training in Nairobi. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Reaching More Female Customers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH’s gender assessment revealed another barrier women face: 85 percent of the utilities required a title deed to apply for a water connection. In a highly patriarchal society such as Kenya, men tend to hold such deeds. As a result, many widows and single mothers—especially in poor households—are unable to apply for water connections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With support from KIWASH, two water companies have addressed this challenge. The Kitui Water and Sanitation Company no longer requires a title deed to apply for a water connection. Since the change, the connections officer noted that most new applicants are women without title deeds; dropping this requirement has helped hundreds of households to access water. WOWASCO also changed its application requirements and now only asks for an identification card. Kuti, the managing director, is at the forefront of promoting gender equity in service provision. “Our next step is to develop a gender policy for generations to come, so that the changes we are making last forever,” Kuti said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tailoring some of its key communications to women has also led to increased engagement from female customers. Maiyo recollects how NCWSC did not have a direct gender policy for customer outreach. “The company used to hold joint community meetings with men and women during feasibility studies,” Maiyo said. “Men would dominate the meetings. However, we have learned that in some communities it is better to hold separate meetings for men and women. As a result, women express themselves freely and this is a good step for the company as we obtain inclusive feedback from the community.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-5&quot; title=&quot;Demonstration garden in Kisumu County where local suppliers provide seed and fertilizer to showcase production of nutrient-dense, high-value crops using efficient irrigation and water management. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Removing Barriers, Strengthening Society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender equality is a fundamental human right but also necessary to fuel a prosperous and sustainable economic future in Kenya. With KIWASH support, Kenya’s water utility sector is increasing gender equity, providing more and better job opportunities for women, improving the workplace environment, and increasing access to water services for thousands of women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the office to conduct field work, Kanini smiled and reflected on the opportunities now available to her. “My future at this company is bright; I have hope that I can be promoted to another position in the office,” she said. “Thanks to KIWASH, I have more opportunity and flexibility to organize my work, and my life will be better because of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
