<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DAI Online Publications</title>
    <link>http://dai-global-developments.com</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2018 16:02:41 -0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>$36 Million Investment Partnership Finances Warehouses in Malawi to Improve Food Security</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/36-million-investment-facility-finances-warehouses-in-malawi-to-improve-food-security</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2018 15:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/36-million-investment-facility-finances-warehouses-in-malawi-to-improve-food-security</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Malawi has suffered from poor food production for decades—its 17 million people are mostly smallholder or subsistence farmers who have struggled to overcome drought, pests, and outdated farming practices. Even successful harvests are diminished because they have few options to process and store their crops for sale, resulting in post-harvest losses that cut deeply into already small profits. But development assistance from the United States and European Union is helping Malawi address its shortage of warehousing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Agency for International Development&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; (the Hub) brought together the European Investment Bank, National Bank of Malawi, and the Agricultural Commodities Exchange for Africa to develop a first-of-its-kind Agricultural Storage Investment Facility (ASIF). Through ASIF, the European Investment Bank is channeling a credit line of €30 million (approximately $36 million) through National Bank for on-lending to seven Malawian agribusinesses to build more than 200,000 metric tons of new storage capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, National Bank has loaned $12 million to four warehouse operators to build 100,000 metric tons of new storage, benefiting agribusinesses and—notably—potentially thousands of farmers. The Hub and its partners expect the remaining $24 million to be utilized over the next 18 months. The Hub will also support integrating these facilities into Malawi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/SATIH%20Infographic.pdf&quot;&gt;Warehouse Receipt System&lt;/a&gt;, which enables farmers to borrow money against their stock of warehoused crops to buy seed, fertilizer, and household necessities. Warehouse and grain silo operators such as Rab Processors and CP Feeds have already added more than 200 jobs after receiving financing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The Hub played an integral role in supporting National Bank to bring the ASIF to market,” said Harold Jiya, National Bank’s Director of Wholesale Banking. “By bringing these new sources of ﬁnance into Malawi, we are now able to ﬁnance important long-term investments that our clients highly value.&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/gS1JZtUhQtFajjLKHzZa&quot; title=&quot;Malawi Agricultural Storage Investment Facility &quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?Pyq&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Developing the Finance Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To develop the ASIF, the Hub team convened international ﬁnanciers, agribusiness and farmer organizations, and other stakeholders. The Hub assisted in developing the instrument, building the financing pipeline, bringing in investors, coordinating investment appraisals by both the European Investment Bank and National Bank, and supporting transactions as they progressed through the approval process. The Hub is also supporting the Agricultural Commodities Exchange to integrate the new warehouses into its system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Storage bottlenecks have hindered Malawian smallholder producers from realizing returns on their activities,” said Kristian Schach Moller, CEO of the Exchange. “The Hub&amp;rsquo;s [ASIF] initiative is helping to overcome those bottlenecks.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malawi and other countries in southern and eastern Africa have increasingly endured drought conditions and crop-devastating infestation of pests such as Fall Armyworms. While these countries have historically turned to food relief programs to survive, they aspire to solve their food issues through trade, investment, and agricultural technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Storage facilities such as the ones receiving ASIF financing reduce post-harvest losses by controlling the temperature, shade, and humidity so harvested crops last longer and farmers can sell more of their harvests in the off-season, often for a better price than when they are desperate to sell expiring goods to opportunistic traders. In addition to staple crops such as maize, other grains, pulses, and legumes, high-value crops such as tomatoes, peppers, and fruit can also be stored in these warehouses for short periods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SATIH-EIB-Malawi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SATIH-EIB-Malawi&quot; title=&quot;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub officials meet at Rab Processors in Lilongwe.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mobilizing Local Investment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To borrow money from ASIF, warehouse entrepreneurs must put up their own capital as well as present well-articulated business plans. The four facilities built or expanded so far under ASIF are in and around Lilongwe and Blantyre, locations chosen to best serve farmers, cooperatives, traders, and transporters. Other warehouses are planned for locations such as Kasungu and Mchinji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ASIF is part of a trend of financing facilities that use European Union financing to generate local investment in areas such as energy efficiency in Eastern Europe and private sector engagement in at-risk countries. In Malawi, there is confidence that the ASIF will help farmers and others in Malawian agricultural value chains to earn more income—as well as serve as a model for agricultural storage investment facilities in other countries that rely on smallholder farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LTA Program Shows Benefit of Truly Participatory Approach</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lta-program-shows-benefit-of-truly-participatory-approach</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 14:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lta-program-shows-benefit-of-truly-participatory-approach</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/tanzania-feed-future-tanzania-land-tenure-assistance-lta&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Land Tenure Assistance&lt;/a&gt; (LTA) activity—which has completed mapping of more than 36,000 land parcels in 26 villages with more than 27,000 Certificates of Customary Rights of Occupancy printed and registered—is a powerful example of how digital technology applied in a participatory process can enable rural people to strengthen their land rights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demarcation and mapping facilitated by the Mobile Application for Secure Tenure (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MASTUSAID&quot;&gt;MAST&lt;/a&gt;) has increased the speed of registration and certificate issuance, reduced costs, and engaged young people in a way that has led to wide acceptance of the program and prompted calls by government, donors, and other development agencies to implement the program nationally. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Agency for International Development’s LTA program is moving the needle on land registration and security in a country where less than 10 percent of individually owned land is registered. And there are encouraging signs that this expansion of formal land titling is beginning to translate into income gains. Both women and men, for example, have been able to use their new CCROs to secure loans enabling them to invest in their land holdings. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Residents Included—From Start to Finish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the moment the program is introduced to a village council to the issuing of the last CCRO, residents of each village are fully and directly involved in the registration process. Residents, for example, serve on Village Land and Adjudication Committees and the Village Land Use Planning Committees. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mpl.ird.fr/crea/taller-colombia/FAO/AGLL/pdfdocs/tanzania.pdf&quot;&gt;participatory rural appraisal approach&lt;/a&gt; is used to draft and approve &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/templates/nr/kagera/Documents/PES_workshop_August2011/Day1/LAND_USE_PLANNING_AND_LAND_TENURE_IN_TANZANIA.pdf&quot;&gt;Village Land Use Plans&lt;/a&gt;, which ensure that land parcels are not allocated and registered across village boundaries or in wetlands, and that corridors are set aside for pastoralists to move their cattle. These issues sometimes require negotiation and agreement between parties with competing interests but have to date been amicably resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DSCN8551.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;DSCN8551&quot; title=&quot;A representative of a Masai pastoralist community participating in the Village Land Use Planning process in Makuka Village, Tanzania&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents also participate directly in the digital capture of land parcel data. They are invited to volunteer for one-week adjudicator and para-surveyor training in the use of MAST for land demarcation. Those who pass the course accompany the Adjudication Committee members, LTA staff, and District Land Office representatives to demarcate the boundaries of every land claim in the presence of neighboring claimants. They capture the GPS coordinates of the parcel boundaries using MAST on a smartphone or tablet, together with a GPS enhancer for greater accuracy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents are trained in  the registration process, as well as educated on their &lt;a href=&quot;http://extwprlegs1.fao.org/docs/pdf/tan23795.pdf&quot;&gt;land rights&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://extwprlegs1.fao.org/docs/pdf/tan53306.pdf&quot;&gt;legislation&lt;/a&gt; governing land tenure. These learning sessions take place at the Village Assembly, at hamlet-level meetings, at special meetings for women, and at schools. Participants are educated about the type of occupation which may be most suitable to protect their interests and informed about the right of women to have CCROs registered in their names as single occupants, as joint tenants, or as tenants in common with their husbands. Tanzanian law enshrines women’s right to occupy land. The number of claimants to date is close to equal between men (52 percent) and women (48 percent). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After claimants have been identified and parcel boundaries recorded, maps are produced for public display for two weeks at the Village Council office. During this period, residents inspect the maps and confirm their claims or raise objections and corrections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_ae8ab2f6-e786-4a83-b8ba-db686285a1bc&quot; title=&quot;LTA Results To Date&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?05u&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Increased Efficiencies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTA has greatly streamlined and automated the printing and processing of CCROs to increase speed and reduce costs. Up to 500 CCROs can be printed each day by a small team of District Land Office staff. Registered CCROs are returned to the Village Council, which retains hard copies in Village Registry Offices refurbished with LTA assistance to provide secure storage. Issuance &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/more-than-500-rural-tanzanians-now-have-land-titles&quot;&gt;ceremonies&lt;/a&gt; celebrate the claimants receiving their CCROs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high level of participation by residents and village leaders has proved to be invaluable in reducing disputes over boundaries, resolving intra-family disputes, and resolving land use planning conflicts. Disputes referred to the dispute resolution process make up less than 0.02 percent of all land parcels demarcated to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involvement by district-level government officials at all stages of the program has resulted in District Land Office staff being fully engaged with the program and capable of conducting public outreach meetings, capturing and correcting the data, printing and registering the CCROs, and leading issuance ceremonies with ever-decreasing supervision by LTA. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, the program has been well received by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://landportal.org/organization/ministry-lands-housing-and-human-settlements-development-tanzania&quot;&gt;Ministry of Land Housing and Human Settlements Development&lt;/a&gt;, which recently moved to implement MAST and the processes used by LTA on other donor- and government-funded land registration programs. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aru.ac.tz/&quot;&gt;Ardhi University&lt;/a&gt; is collaborating with LTA to use its processes and MAST for its practical training of students and has asked DAI to provide technical assistance and set up an internship program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mozambique: Even a Progressive Land Law Needs Revision After a Generation of Experience</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/mozambique-even-a-progressive-land-law-needs-revision-after-a-generation-of-experience</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/mozambique-even-a-progressive-land-law-needs-revision-after-a-generation-of-experience</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mozambique is widely regarded as having a modern and progressive land tenure framework, following the enactment of the 1997 Land Law. However, in its implementation, the law has not always lived up to its promise. Twenty years of experience reveals a number of areas in which the legal framework would benefit from revision and better serve its primary aims of promoting productive land use while protecting legitimate customary and smallholder land rights.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As demand for access to agricultural land increases—whether from national investors, international conglomerates, or just a local smallholder wishing to increase the size of his or her farm—the pressure for clarity and transparency in land administration has grown accordingly.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full privatization of land remains politically unacceptable, but other topics once off-limits—for example, loosening the restrictions on land rights transfers in rural areas—are now openly discussed in the press and at the government-led Land Consultative Forum. The time is right to address this and other weaknesses in the legal framework and thereby catalyze investment, increase productivity, and enhance transparency in land administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues were also openly discussed and debated more recently at the private sector-sponsored 15th Conferência Anual do Sector Privado (CASP) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dais-ian-rose-on-legal-reform-in-the-land-sector&quot;&gt;held on March 12&lt;/a&gt;, during which the DAI presented in front of an audience including Prime Minister Carlos Agostinho do Rosário, Minister of Land and Rural Development Celso Correia, and Minister of Industry and Commerce Ragendra Berta de Sousa. The conference was widely covered in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/SAVANA%201262.pdf&quot;&gt;Mozambican press&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The donor community is poised to provide technical assistance based on best practices from relevant contexts, and the Mozambican government has indicated its willingness to engage in a multistakeholder participatory reform process. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/mozambique-support-program-economic-and-enterprise-development-speed&quot;&gt;Supporting the Policy Environment for Economic Development (SPEED+)&lt;/a&gt; project, implemented by DAI and funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development, is in discussions with the Mozambican government on how best to support reforms, with the National Land Directorate (DINAT) signaling its preliminary agreement with several recommendations already being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Keep It Simple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informed by extensive stakeholder discussions and economic analysis, SPEED+ is working on the premise that increasing transparency and simplifying the procedures for acquiring and transferring secure leasehold access to land via DUATs (&lt;em&gt;Direito de Uso e Aproveimento de Terra&lt;/em&gt;, or Land Use and Benefit Right) will lead to a higher volume of transactions, with more of these transactions brought into the formal registration process. A more fluid environment for transactions will eventually lead to a more market-oriented allocation of land rights, with the legal framework—engaged rather than skirted—protecting the rights of the most vulnerable. In turn, a more efficient allocation of land rights means that land will flow to those people and enterprises with the capacity and capital to put the land to more productive use. Increased investment will lead to greater productivity and economic growth, primarily in agriculture but also in sectors—such as housing or light industry—that require secure access to land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the government in February 2018 launched a National Land Audit Campaign to revoke DUATs from people or enterprises that were not putting their land to productive use. We believe that a more market-oriented legal framework could accomplish similar goals more efficiently and cheaply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically speaking, all land in Mozambique is owned by the state, held in trust for the people to be managed for their benefit. Citizens, foreigners, and corporate entities may acquire DUAT rights in various ways. Essentially leaseholds granted or recognized by the state, DUATs run for varying periods of time (the length of a DUAT&amp;rsquo;s validity depends on a number of factors and can even be of indefinite duration under certain circumstances). Technical ownership of the land by the state is not a constraint to secure tenure or a more fluid land market (or its functional land rental equivalent). Rather, constraints arise due to partial restrictions on DUAT transferability and to inefficiencies in land administration that lead to actual and perceived weak title or insecure tenure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mozambique can therefore make significant strides toward promoting increased investment in land by revising the current legal framework but leaving the fundamental premise of the 1997 Land Law—the state&amp;rsquo;s unequivocal ownership of all land—untouched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/moz%20ag%20land%202.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;moz ag land 2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Change for the Better&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In analyzing the policy environment for land-based investments, SPEED+ has organized its recommendations around four investor-driven criteria for secure access to land:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certainty and Transparency &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protection of Investment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Community Consent and Participation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sustainable Land Administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If concerns in these areas can be adequately addressed, then the investor can appropriately focus on its core business: determining market demand, putting the land into production, and supplying product to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. Certainty and Transparency&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The investor strives to reduce unknown risk to the extent possible: the &amp;ldquo;rules of the game&amp;rdquo; should be known to all players and should be enforced in a consistent manner. Our recommendations to increase certainty and transparency can be summarized as follows: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issue official technical norms for DUAT acquisition, addressing both government-sponsored mass title regularization as well as privately initiated DUAT applications. The most recent official norms date back to 1989 and are obsolete in many aspects. This has led inevitably to inconsistency in the way cadaster services are implemented across the country, posing risk for the investor. Proposed norms cover both urban and rural contexts and clarify such issues as accuracy requirements for surveys, eligibility for free registration under state-initiated regularization programs, appropriate use of spatial technology, and when the need for physical &amp;ldquo;marcos&amp;rdquo; (expensive concrete boundary markers) may be waived. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant the public online access to land use planning instruments and to cadastral data. Privacy concerns have complicated the public dissemination of cadastral data online. One approach would be to authorize online secured read-only access via the digital registry of the geographic borders of all DUATs with the names of the holders, but without any further personal information. A more cautious approach might be to withhold names (but not the geographic information) of private individuals, but not of corporate holdings. Transparency of land rights data should reduce multiple sales (or attempted sales) of the same property.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish accurate Land Use Plans. The current inventory should be analyzed to determine which plans are not outdated. Plans deemed useful and relevant should be geo-referenced accurately and published online. This step should presumably be uncontroversial, given the absence of privacy concerns and the state&amp;rsquo;s clear interest in widespread dissemination of such plans. Better access to the plans should reduce unwelcome surprises when a purchaser learns it cannot implement the project it had in mind. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. Protection of Investment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If they are to invest in the land, potential investors need confidence about the following issues: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability, if necessary, to recoup their investment by selling improvements on the land (in buildings, irrigation infrastructure, planted crops, and so on). In practical terms, their ability to sell such improvements—that is, the attractiveness of the transaction to a buyer—depends on the seller&amp;rsquo;s ability to transfer the underlying DUAT to the buyer. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility to transfer use rights over part of their granted DUAT (that is, their ability to subdivide the DUAT).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexibility to change development plans (wholly or partially), within reason and without excessive fear of DUAT revocation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protection against expropriation without just compensation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarity on compensation and resettlement guidelines for occupants of land earmarked for development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ability to challenge arbitrary or arguably &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;illegal&amp;rdquo; acts in a timely fashion (in court or via alternative dispute mechanisms).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key constraint affecting all these issues is the current restriction on the transferability of land use rights in rural areas. In rural settings, transfer is possible but subject to a high degree of local government discretion. By contrast, transferability of land use rights of developed urban land is less problematic, since the legal framework provides for what amounts to a nearly automatic transfer of a DUAT—that is, with minimal government discretion—when an improvement on that land is sold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investors need to know that if they are running short on capital mid-way through a project, the improvements and DUATs can be sold and transferred to another interested party. There are many examples in Mozambique of &amp;ldquo;abandoned&amp;rdquo; improvements (which ultimately revert to the state if the DUAT is revoked), but it is not clear if they would have been abandoned if the DUAT transfer procedures (or DUAT partition procedures) in rural areas were automatic or at least less discretionary. SPEED+ will draft proposals to make the transfer of rural land rights more similar to urban land rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state&amp;rsquo;s ability to revoke DUATs is another area that would benefit from revision. DUAT-holders are at risk of losing their leasehold rights if they are in violation of their development plan. Once again, the standards for when a DUAT-holder is in violation vary among the provinces, with opportunities for rent-seeking resulting from the discretionary power of government officials. While the state surely has a legitimate interest in how land is used, these interests can be served in many instances by greater attention to, and enforcement of, district land use plans. SPEED+ seeks to clarify the criteria for DUAT revocation as well as make development regulations more flexible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Community Consent and Participation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most critical issues for investor confidence and security, as well as for the protection of community members&amp;#39; land rights, remains the mechanism for community consent. The Land Law anticipated that the mechanisms of representation of local communities with respect to land rights would be defined by the enactment of future legal instruments to regulate such procedures. However, no such law has ever been enacted. There has been some guidance as to the procedures for conducting a community consultation within the context of awarding a DUAT to a third party on land that may affect or involve community land, and there is guidance on the process by which a community delimits its land. Strictly speaking, these are two different processes, though in reality they may often occur at the same time, and the differing guidelines may create confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The procedures for community consultation and community land delimitation should be harmonized, and procedures should also be clarified for the community to become a legal entity capable, for example, of opening a bank account and receiving funds to which it is entitled (either because of contracts with outside investors, or via the percentage of mining, forestry, and tourism-related fees it is entitled to under those corresponding laws). Banks have been known to refuse to open accounts for communities, insisting the legal framework is not sufficiently explicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that consultations must be genuinely participatory and foster informed consent. Informed and effective consent by the local community to a proposed project is not only a protection for members of the local communities—it&amp;rsquo;s also a protection for the investor who does not want to see an initial investment of time, money, and effort wasted if, at a later time, disaffected members of the community object to the project and successfully pressure community leaders or the state to cancel the contract, citing insufficient consultation. In short, hasty and incomplete &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/to-realize-the-promise-of-renewables-address-the-concerns-of-local-people/&quot;&gt;community consent&lt;/a&gt;, as well as one-sided negotiations, may backfire later in the form of community opposition. SPEED+ is reviewing the relevant legislation to ensure the protection of community rights with an approach that will not deter investors but rather attract investors who wish to conduct business in a more defined, predictable, and transparent environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;4. Sustainable Land Administration&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Mozambique is to provide an attractive venue for increased land-based investment, then it must perform its land administration functions in a sustainable fashion. This includes maintaining its digital cadaster database, as well as staffing district, provincial, and national positions with sufficient numbers of well-trained staff. Unfortunately, these government offices have not been given sufficient human and physical resources to run the land administration services at the optimum level, and the demands will only increase—for example, as greater numbers of parcels enter the formal system via the government&amp;rsquo;s massive &amp;ldquo;Terra Segura&amp;rdquo; titling program, and as foreign investors continue to look to Mozambique for opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, increased formalization of land rights does hold out the promise of greater revenue opportunities. Increased land-based taxes and fees are a natural source of funds to help sustain Mozambique&amp;rsquo;s land administration services while also discouraging idle land. We recommend efforts to: (a) increase collection rates; and (b) increase tax rates, with an assessment base tailored more proportionately to &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; or market-oriented values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mozambique legal framework already exempts the great majority of parcels from the DUAT tax because they fall under the category of &amp;ldquo;family use&amp;rdquo; or because the DUAT-holders are local communities or members of local communities. As a first step, Mozambique would benefit from more clearly defining the exemption categories with an eye toward limiting the exemption to subsistence farming households and the urban poor. Although the philosophy of generous tax exemptions may originally have been conceived to guarantee universal access to land for productive use, the impact of the generous exemptions appears to have the contrary result—namely, the lack of a disincentive to leave the land unproductive. Of course, due attention must be given to avoiding the other extreme, in which overly burdensome taxes push transactions back into the informal sphere and pose undue hardships on vulnerable households and populations.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Moz%20image%20copy.png&quot; alt=&quot;Moz image copy&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When is the Right Time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current administration, soon after the 2014 general elections, emphasized secure land tenure as one of its priorities. In April 2015, President Nyusi himself launched the Terra Segura program, which promised to issue 5 million DUAT titles in five years. Although it does not demonstrate political will for legal reform per se, the program provides a window of opportunity to push forward a land sector reform agenda that can assist in streamlining the legal framework to facilitate more fluid acquisitions and transfers of rural land DUATs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the goals of Terra Segura lend critical weight to the argument that a stable and reliable digital cadaster must be maintained. The registration of 5 million DUATs will mean little unless the cadaster is maintained with up-to-date information, such as changes in DUAT titleholders due to death, marriage, divorce, transfers, expiration, revocation, and other modifications. The advent of Terra Segura underscores the need to adopt measures to maintain the integrity of the digital cadaster database, as well as the recommendations related to reforming the land tax revenue base, given that the enormous influx of formal titles into the cadaster system will require a much higher volume and level of services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more explicit expression of the political will for reform was made by the Land and Rural Development Minister Celso Correia at the national land forum in November 2017, which closed with a formal commitment to make a targeted revision of the Land Law (albeit one that leaves some issues—such as full privatization of real property—unequivocally off the table for the time being). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the level of DINAT, the openness to reform is a mix of outward cautiousness regarding donors while, at the same time, internal preparations are underway to consider a vast range of reforms, including not only changes to regulatory instruments but also amendments to the 1997 Land Law itself. In fact, DINAT has prepared a list of approximately 40 legal instruments in need of revision (or in some cases creation). Although the list may be ambitious, it certainly reflects the realization within DINAT of the need for reform. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the lower levels of bureaucracy, there is a predictable mix of openness and resistance to change. In project visits to local cadaster offices, we encountered some directors committed to the integrity of the new digital database and others who retain paper-based procedures, perhaps intentionally opting for opacity over transparency. However, previously taboo subjects—such as the sale (not just &amp;ldquo;transfer&amp;rdquo;) of DUATs—are now openly advocated by some university faculty. The existence of an informal rural land market is now widely acknowledged, and there is a growing understanding that bringing these informal transactions into the formal sector can increase tax and fee revenues to the state, as well as provide more security to smallholders wishing to consolidate and grow their businesses. The demand for formal title among communities and smallholders is also growing as external investors insist on formal title (or at least some assurance of land rights) in out-grower schemes. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite what appears to be a gathering consensus for reform, some pockets of resistance should be expected. For example, the reduction of procedural discretion (and corresponding process simplification) will reduce rent-seeking opportunities enjoyed by some cadastral officials. In addition, it is still widely mentioned that an element of the political elite prefers a lack of transparency in land transactions such that deals favorable to these elites, that might not survive public scrutiny, can be cut in relative secrecy. Nevertheless, the bulk of investors, and particularly foreign investors, welcome more transparency as a precondition for expanding opportunities throughout the provinces.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Nigeria, Governance Champions Can Transform Resource Wealth into Development Results</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/in-nigeria-governance-champions-can-transform-resource-wealth-into-development-results</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/in-nigeria-governance-champions-can-transform-resource-wealth-into-development-results</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nigeria is well known for its glaring inequalities, particularly the disparity between the impoverished northern states and its oil-rich south. This disparity covers more than just wealth and economic growth, as large segments of the country’s 185 million people want for simple stability and basic public services. But just as Nigeria’s economy is powered by more than oil, so the country’s inequities stem from more than just the so-called “resource curse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nigeria’s oil industry is the largest in Africa, in 2016 it represented only 8.4 percent of the country’s overall gross domestic product (GDP). Non-oil exports have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailytrust.com.ng/nigeria-records-rise-in-non-oil-export.html&quot;&gt;continued to rise&lt;/a&gt;, with total exports increasing by 73.5 percent in the second quarter of 2017 year-over-year, according to Nigeria’s National Bureau of Statistics, driven largely by economic diversification efforts focusing on agricultural goods. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/willem-buiter-3g-countries-2011-2?slop=1#nigeria-8&quot;&gt;2011 Citigroup report&lt;/a&gt; suggests Nigeria will achieve the highest average growth in GDP in the world between 2010 and 2050, and Nigeria already has the largest economy in Africa—surpassing South Africa in 2014. We would do Nigeria a disservice to pigeonhole it as resource-cursed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, economic growth alone is not working for most Nigerians. In 2016, the National Bureau of Statistics reported that Nigeria’s poverty rate was 67.1 percent, making it one of the poorest—and economically unequal—countries in the world. But this can be fixed, not by natural resources alone but by human resources in the service of good government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transforming Nigeria’s economic growth into countrywide development results rests on improving three elements of governance: strategic planning, financial management, and—critically—institution-focused capacity development at the state and national levels. These elements form a stable three-legged stool of governance required to steer economic growth toward inclusive growth, and to optimize Nigeria’s capacity in public service sectors such as education, health, and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Abah-Nigeria-top.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Abah-Nigeria-top&quot; title=&quot;Market in Ibadan, Oyo State. Photo: Mary Gillham Archive Project&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Strategic Planning: Knowing Nigeria’s Public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the development space, Nigerians are often faulted for poor implementation of good plans. In truth, many of those plans are written with lofty ambitions but little consideration for the country’s prevailing institutional, political economy, and human resource constraints. This factor renders many plans virtually undeliverable before they leave the consultant’s desk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigerians are no more incapable of project implementation than any other nationality. They effectively implement communal self-help and religious projects on time, at the agreed cost, and with the requisite quality, often without issues of corruption, embezzlement, or diversion of funds. However, when it comes to implementing &lt;em&gt;government&lt;/em&gt; projects, the same commitment, transparency, and unity of purpose are too often absent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should that be the case? As far back as the 1970s, Nigerian academic Peter Ekeh described what he calls &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/178372?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;two publics&lt;/a&gt; in the minds of the post-colonial African citizen, even among the more privileged classes: a “primordial public,” which exists at the communal level and to which Africans are generally loyal; and a “civic public” representing Western-style government, to which most Africans have no such intuitive loyalty, and from which they will accordingly seek to extract whatever might support themselves. Whatever its merits, this framework certainly accords with Nigeria’s record of unfulfilled government projects, public sector corruption, and high degree of nepotism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressing this point of view in the development lexicon of the 21st century, we would probably say that development plans failing to take account of the local political economy are dead on arrival—they have virtually no chance of being implemented. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As development professionals working in Nigeria, we must improve the quality of planning between Nigeria’s public and private sectors. But to do that we must acknowledge that a realistic plan—whether for tax reform, domestic resource mobilization, transparency and accountability, or other areas—needs to understand local political economies and work to optimize the capacity of local institutions and their staffs. Plans for public-sector reforms should identify ways to quickly gain stakeholder buy-in and account for risks to successful implementation at the communal level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Abah-Nigeria-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Abah-Nigeria-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Financial Management: Marrying Rules to Reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria has made good progress in putting into place rules-based public financial management systems that accord with international standards. The country’s Public Procurement Act of 2007 follows a template of the International Monetary Fund, the National Chart of Accounts meets international requirements, and the national accounting system is designed to conform with International Public Sector Accounting Standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, budgeting across the country remains uneven, despite the 2016 adoption by the federal government of a zero-based budgeting system. Auditing and financial reporting throughout Nigeria also leave much room for improvement. Notable here is the interplay between rules-based financial management systems and institutional factors that are often informal and not rules-based. Failure to understand this conflict—another manifestation of the friction between Nigeria’s primordial and civic publics—will lead only to more rules-based efforts that deliver little discernible change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encouragingly, we know that reform is possible: for example, a number of African countries—including Nigeria at the state level—have improved their public financial management and domestic resource mobilization performance, thanks in part to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/governance-solutions/public-financial-management&quot;&gt;effective development assistance&lt;/a&gt;. In January 2018, DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-joins-forces-with-nigerias-grid-consulting&quot;&gt;acquired&lt;/a&gt; Lagos-based GRID Consulting, a longtime partner of DAI’s that specializes in financial advisory services, human resource management, and development program implementation. GRID’s combination of local acumen, demonstrated integrity, and financial expertise will be an essential ingredient of our commitment to provide effective assistance in public finance and other aspects of Nigeria’s development challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-Abah-hospital.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-Abah-hospital&quot; title=&quot;Hospital in Katsina in northwest Nigeria. Photo: Eugene Kim&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Building Institutions: Unleashing the Capacity of Capable Nigerians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Nigeria, it is critical to differentiate between individual capability and institutional capacity. In virtually every sector or industry in Nigeria—both public and private—one finds capable Nigerians. Yet, too often, donor-supported development efforts focus on developing the capabilities of Nigerians as opposed to unleashing their collective capacity. The distinction is subtle but important. Capable Nigerians are individuals, while capable Nigerians acting in concert can dramatically improve an institution’s ability to deliver results. In other words, capacity development may involve developing the skills of individuals, but should do so in the context of improving institutional capacity. In practice, this means we should complement formal education with skills such as negotiating and managing contracts, developing public-private partnerships, optimizing organizational performance, and managing programs. In this way, we can unleash the institutional capacity of capable Nigerians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most effective way to unlock institutional capacity is through on-the-job training: providing coaching, mentoring, and skills development &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; institutions, as opposed to within classrooms—with a focus on the skills people need for their &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; job in the institution, not the one they currently hold. Too often, individuals are mired in positions where they are unable to increase their contribution to the capacity of the institution over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know this approach works in Nigeria. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-state-partnership-accountability-responsiveness-and-capability-sparc&quot;&gt;State Partnership for Accountability, Responsiveness, and Capability (SPARC)&lt;/a&gt;, funded by the U.K. Department for International Development, carefully and progressively aligned Nigerian capability to institutional capacity needs. SPARC itself was able to move from a composition of approximately 70 percent foreign consultants and 30 percent Nigerian consultants in 2008 to the reverse composition by program’s end in 2016. “SPARC has strengthened core State Government business processes,” according to the project’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opml.co.uk/sites/default/files/SLP-Final-Evaluation-Volume-1.pdf&quot;&gt;final evaluation&lt;/a&gt;. By 2016, the Nigerian-led SPARC team supported 10 State Development Plans and had helped state governments collect an additional GBP600 million (equivalent) to support public services by improving domestic revenue mobilization—reclaiming funds from dormant bank accounts, reducing procurement costs, and recovering outstanding debts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, there were capable Nigerians available, but those capabilities needed to be developed, tailored, and aggregated to unlock the full capacity of SPARC and its government partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Nigeria-Abah-bottom.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Nigeria-Abah-bottom&quot; title=&quot;Nigerian volunteers mobilized against the Ebola crisis. Photo: CDC Global&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mobilizing Nigeria’s Potential Champions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s oil industry and related wealth might be concentrated in the south, but its entrepreneurial and business energy is more widespread. Likewise, public servants throughout the country have shown they possess the collective capacity and potential to reform public finance, plan strategically, and raise and mobilize revenues for the public good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under SPARC, the northern state of Kano mobilized GBP14 million more revenue from 2012 to 2014, an 11 percent increase; the resulting expenditures benefited health, education, and other services. In the northwest state of Niger, budget variance for expenditures decreased from 50 percent in 2011 (budget vs. actual) to 15 percent in 2013, enabling improved planning. As noted above, these and other gains were achieved largely thanks to Nigerian consultants and their local counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To strengthen the three legs of the governance stool—strategic planning, institutional capacity, and financial management—we must identify, support, and empower those Nigerian champions in both the public and private sectors who seek to align traditional loyalties with civic reforms in ways that broaden and deepen the country’s economic successes to benefit all Nigerians. These champions are there—in business, government, schools, and communities. They are many.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EC Helps Position the Southern Africa Development Community for 21st Century Success</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ec-helps-position-the-southern-africa-development-community-for-21st-century-success</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/ec-helps-position-the-southern-africa-development-community-for-21st-century-success</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Launched in 1992, the Southern Africa Development Community (SADC) was based more on ideals than economics. Born of the anti-Apartheid movement, the SADC aimed to help Southern Africa countries build economic ties and reduce dependence on the Republic of South Africa. As the region changed, the SADC’s membership grew and the organization adopted lofty goals. But the SADC’s outmoded inner workings did not meet the needs of its escalating staff and ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the SADC’s Secretariat—based in Gaborone, Botswana—asked the European Commission (EC) to help modernise the SADC’s processes and recalibrate the organisation for success. After four years of sustained collaboration, the SADC now operates with new systems and a renewed focus on rigorously planning and managing its projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/lfYchLjWLYbcc7p8s6a4&quot; title=&quot;SADC Map&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?lYq&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This accomplishment was assisted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/botswana-technical-assistance-sadc-secretariat-institutional-capacity-development&quot;&gt;Technical Assistance to the SADC Secretariat Institutional Capacity Development Programme&lt;/a&gt;, which worked closely with the Secretariat’s executive team, supporting them through the setbacks and successes of organisational transformation. Over the past four years, the team:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trained the Secretariat on revised procurement policies, supply chain management, and contract administration;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepared the SADC to work directly with international donors to manage projects;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teamed with SADC directorates to improve evaluation guidelines and build capacity among personnel responsible for monitoring and planning;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed program dashboards to track projects and created statistical yearbooks to support data-driven planning;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enabled the SADC to better manage members’ obligations;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aligned human resources policies—including job descriptions, hiring standards, and performance reviews—to support the SADC vision and values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme, managed by DAI, also helped the SADC to develop a comprehensive plan for how it will utilise the current round of European Development Fund (EDF) funding for its programmes, which address agriculture, water, trade, and other regional needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Regional Communities Matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The African Union recognizes eight regional economic communities on the continent. The SADC member states— Angola, Botswana, Democratic Republic of Congo, Lesotho, Madagascar, Malawi, Mauritius, Mozambique, Namibia, Seychelles, South Africa, Swaziland, Tanzania, Zambia, and Zimbabwe—have long depended on regional cooperation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regional economic communities play increasingly important roles, from improving intra-region trade to preventing conflicts between member states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Harmonized financial regulations can facilitate commerce and create jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strong regional cooperation can attract donor agencies and private investors to support cross-border infrastructure projects, such as highways and electrical grids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six SADC member states are landlocked and rely on neighbours to import and export products by sea.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;SADC Commits to Intensive Reform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with a complex and diverse regional body prompted DAI to apply an adaptable, demand-driven approach. The programme focused on improving SADC staff attitudes about their work over publishing documents. The SADC Secretariat staff proved to be receptive partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Initially, the programme was run like a framework contract, but this didn’t allow enough flexibility—the typical 20-day timeframes for consultants didn’t provide time for knowledge transfer,” said David Ablett, Team Leader for DAI. “We didn’t want to just drop off documents and then leave. We wanted to nurture people and test things.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the Secretariat was struggling with the key processes it needed to plan, implement, and monitor projects, but its leadership knew what the organization needed and committed to bringing about sustainable change. In turn, DAI’s team formed a close working relationship with the SADC’s executive team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fixing the Procurement Struggle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the procurement difficulties of the Secretariat, for example, the DAI team and SADC leadership developed and implemented procedures and created an internal audit manual. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Staff from across the Secretariat were trained on the revised policies. The cross-trained staff can now effectively manage an annual procurement budget, allowing the Secretariat to hire directly and manage technical consultants or upgrade its own information technology (IT). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes had an immediate effect on efficiency and staff morale. Several large tenders that had been blocked in the SADC’s system for years have been executed as a result, and staff are now working on projects directly with international donors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;Among SADC’s offerings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service centres&lt;/strong&gt; addressing areas such as agriculture standards, climate resilience, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sadc.int/sadc-secretariat/services-centres/rptc/&quot;&gt;security&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financing facilities&lt;/strong&gt; for jumpstarting project planning, water projects, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sadc.int/sadc-secretariat/directorates/office-deputy-executive-secretary-regional-integration/trade-industry-finance-investment/sadc-trade-related-facility-trf/&quot;&gt;trade&lt;/a&gt; technical assistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consultancies&lt;/strong&gt; including for health, infrastructure, defence, and agriculture.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Promoting Merit-Based Human Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SADC Secretariat’s annual budget of $71.9 million is made up of contributions from member states. While revamped administrative processes were essential, addressing the SADC’s human factors was equally important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat worked with DAI’s team to revise HR policies. Incomplete job descriptions were updated and performance reviews adjusted to connect employee’s objectives to larger organizational goals. Improving hiring standards and rewarding top performers helped rejuvenate the organization and boost morale, while enabling the Secretariat to hold underperforming and corrupt employees accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Dusting Off Manuals, Putting Policy into Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Secretariat worked with DAI’s team to strengthen financial management and upgrade IT systems. While previous consulting projects had developed valuable technical manuals and plans for the Secretariat, the EC and DAI’s team recognised that different approaches would be needed to ensure that what was put down on paper during previous programmes was also put into practice. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EC Delegation in Botswana supported DAI’s team in taking a long-term, iterative approach, with a focus on attitudinal change, and allowed the programme to hire consultants for extended periods. “We took a more in-depth, hands-on project approach to a typical technical assistance framework contract,” said Ablett. “It was a frustrating process at times to design and test, but the EC saw benefit in it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SADC-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SADC-1&quot; title=&quot;SADC Executive Secretary Ms. Stergomena Lawrence Tax Gaborone, right, meets in November 2017 with United Nations Special Representative Maman Sidikou in her office in Gaborone, Botswana. Photo: MONUSCO.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New Confidence Attracts New Partners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The positive changes were noticed outside of the Secretariat. With new confidence in the SADC’s administrative capabilities, donor agencies from France, Italy, the United Kingdom, and other countries began approaching the organisation about leading regional development projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those working on U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)-funded projects in the region, the SADC’s improved capacity was noticeable. USAID’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern Africa Trade and Investment Hub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-feed-future-southern-africa-seed-trade-project&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Seed Trade Project&lt;/a&gt;, both led by DAI, have partnered with the SADC Secretariat on activities, including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.satradehub.org/food-safety-and-production/537-sadc-convenes-to-improve-seed-trade?highlight=WyJzYWRjIiwic2FkYydzIiwiJ3NhZGMnIl0=&quot;&gt;SADC Seed Technical Meeting&lt;/a&gt; in November 2017 to discuss agricultural issues affecting the region. With its newly streamlined procurement process, the Secretariat directly paid its contribution of $20,000 rather than having to pass funds through an intermediary member state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With its new policies and procedures, the Secretariat can confidently address operational challenges. Most importantly, this regional economic community—accounting for 300 million people and gross domestic product of $600 billion—has the potential to play a positive role in transforming the economy of Southern Africa and the wider continent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Zealand Aid Helps Rwandan Smallholders Enter Fortified Foods Supply Chain</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-zealand-aid-helps-rwandan-farmers-reduce-losses-sell-more-maize-to-producer-of-maternal-infant-foods</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-zealand-aid-helps-rwandan-farmers-reduce-losses-sell-more-maize-to-producer-of-maternal-infant-foods</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Small-scale farmers in Rwanda struggle to capture the full value of their maize harvests. Farmers typically process their maize manually or using basic tools. With limited infrastructure available for threshing, cleaning, and drying, the full harvest and post-harvest process takes six weeks, on average. Apart from being burdensome for farm families, the lengthy process exposes their maize to rotting, pest infestation, and mould. As a result, the farmers lose an estimated 30 percent of their yields, and traders capture much of the profit generated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Rwandan farmers seek to earn more from their maize, an emerging food producer in Rwanda is seeking locally grown maize for its nutrient-fortified products, presenting a clear market opportunity. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.africaimprovedfoods.com/&quot;&gt;Africa Improved Foods Limited (AIF)&lt;/a&gt;—a social enterprise with a mission to create jobs, produce and sell food, and support local farming—launched its state-of-the-art food processing facility in 2015 in Rwanda’s capital of Kigali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running at full capacity, AIF needs up to 30,000 metric tons of maize and 11,000 metric tons of soybeans per year. Currently, though, AIF can procure only a small fraction of that volume locally; it buys the rest from commercial maize producers and commodity traders in neighboring countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Wallis-pic-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Wallis-pic-2&quot; title=&quot;Rwandan farmers bring their maize to a collection point for processing. Photo: Kumwe Logistics.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With financial support from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mfat.govt.nz/en/aid-and-development/&quot;&gt;New Zealand Aid Programme&lt;/a&gt;, DAI is assisting a pilot process that has nearly eliminated post-harvest losses for targeted Rwandan farmers and helped them enter the AIF supply chain. Initial results suggest that post-harvest losses are being reduced to approximately &lt;em&gt;2 percent&lt;/em&gt; with no adverse effect on crop quality. The difference maker: a cob-to-factory concept supported by the Clinton Health Access Initiative (CHAI) that shortened the farmers’ maize processing time from weeks to days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Moving Maize Directly From Cob to Factory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, AIF, which makes fortified porridge flours, has been challenged to source grain of sufficient quality at targeted prices. The difficult growing season across East Africa—the 2016 El Niño phenomenon led to the worst drought in 60 years—diminished maize yields regionally and pushed prices upward. CHAI had been arranging forward contracts between farmers and AIF to transact maize at an agreed price and date, but conditions rendered the contracts unenforceable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new sourcing approach, advocated by DAI Team Leader James Allen from AgFirst in New Zealand, was piloted during the 2017 maize harvest. The idea was to streamline post-harvest handling and sales, moving maize as quickly as possible from the farm to the AIF factory. CHAI partnered with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kumwelogistics.com/&quot;&gt;Kumwe Logistics&lt;/a&gt;, a local transport company, to set up mobile maize processing centres with threshing and cleaning equipment. These centres were hosted by partner cooperatives with drying infrastructure on site and access to a network of farmers. The mobile centres had cash on hand to buy maize cobs directly from farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The participating cooperatives were [also] empowered, being able to offer a full post-harvest service to all farmers—something not previously possible given limited infrastructure.”&lt;/em&gt; —Kumwe CEO Cyril Khamsi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Wallis-pic-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Wallis-pic-1&quot; title=&quot;Touring the Africa Improved Foods processing facility in Kigali. Photo: Africa Improved Foods.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial calculations by Kumwe indicate that although farmers pay for some additional costs in this process, they earned 35 percent more net income due to the significant reduction in wastage. Additionally, the streamlined handling process helped maintain high-quality maize grains—no aflatoxins were detected in the 80 metric tons of threshed maize output sold to AIF—and farmers gained more time to sow the next crop. The concept is still under development, but initial results are encouraging, as the pilot proved that targeted sourcing of maize cobs could align the market incentives of farmers with those of AIF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other benefits include farmers being paid six to 10 weeks &lt;em&gt;earlier&lt;/em&gt; and having the cash flow to invest in the subsequent season, which begins shortly after harvest, as well as ancillary impacts such as improved education for children not pulled from school to harvest and process maize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Scaling Up the Fresh Maize Purchasing Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the pilot, Kumwe worked in Rwanda’s Nyagatare (East) and Kamonyi (South) districts, engaging approximately 680 farmers and four cooperatives. Farmers each earned approximately 35 percent more income, or RWF 88,000 (US$100) on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----MFAT-Wallis-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----MFAT-Wallis-3&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Africa Improved Foods.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fresh maize purchasing model will be scaled up during the 2018 growing season. For the next phase, Kumwe established a processing centre adjacent to the AIF processing factory. After harvest, Kumwe will deliver the maize cobs from collection sites directly to the processing site, where there will be a centralized set of machines for shelling and winnowing. This fixed site enables far greater utilization of the machines, reduced breakdowns due to less wear and tear from transporting them, and easier repair given their location in Kigali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI has a contract through 2019 with the New Zealand Aid Programme to assist CHAI, and we look forward to supporting the “cob-to-factory” program as it scales up to provide more income for farmers and more maize for the AIF social enterprise as they produce affordable nutritional porridge flours for mothers, newborns, and infants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afghan Cities Assisted by USAID Project Achieve Highest Ratings in Citizen Survey</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-cities-assisted-by-usaid-project-achieve-highest-ratings-in-citizen-survey</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 17:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-cities-assisted-by-usaid-project-achieve-highest-ratings-in-citizen-survey</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a citizen assessment of government services in nine Afghan municipalities, the four that ranked the highest—Chaharikar, Hirat, Mazar-e-Sharif, and Jalalabad—are all partners with a U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) project working to improve the capacity of Afghan municipal officials to meet citizen priorities and service delivery needs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/map-of-afghan-cities-in-survey%20Green.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;map-of-afghan-cities-in-survey Green&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-strong-hubs-afghan-hope-and-resilience-shahar&quot;&gt;Strong Hubs for Afghan Hope and Resilience (SHAHAR)&lt;/a&gt;, offers targeted support to municipal governments—as well as to the Deputy Ministry of Municipalities and Municipal Advisory Boards—to improve municipal financial management, urban service delivery, and citizen consultation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent that such improved governance confers legitimacy on government institutions and weakens the hand of anti-government elements, SHAHAR&amp;rsquo;s success offers an encouraging example of how technical assistance can be an effective tool in countering violent extremism in fragile environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conducted by the independent Integrity Watch Afghanistan (IWA), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://iwaweb.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/CITIZEN-REPORT-CARD-ON-MUNICIPAL-SERVICES-IN-AFGHANISTAN-2017.pdf&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; used the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pria-academy.org/pdf/2.m4-2-Citizen-Report-Cards-Civicus.pdf&quot;&gt;citizen report card&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; approach, seeking to prompt reform by imitating the type of consumer pressure that drives private companies to do better. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fifth SHAHAR partner municipality included in the study is Gardez, which was without SHAHAR embedded advisors from mid-November 2016 until June 2017, due to a funding reduction that was subsequently partially restored. Consequently, the citizen service center, a number of community outreach activities, and public awareness campaigns were not completed in Gardez until after IWA conducted its survey in April 2017. Additionally, the increasing insecurity in and around Gardez in 2017 also caused several project activities to be cancelled. These issues may have contributed to its lower score. In compiling its scorecards, IWA conducted a total of 4,444 surveys, spread evenly across the nine municipalities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_50a861c4-dff4-44a4-bcfb-8b1092b82ad4&quot; title=&quot;Afghanistan Survey&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?vki&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IWA concluded that, overall, &amp;ldquo;Afghan municipalities must do more to improve the quality of services delivered to citizens, the level of overall governance, and the extent to which they communicate effectively with citizens.&amp;rdquo; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cities that scored relatively well are those where SHAHAR has led targeted activities around improving the services offered by local governments. These activities include establishing Citizen Service Centers (CSCs) equipped with systems that track business licensing, parcel registration, tax billing, and collection, and holding community meetings to spread awareness around municipal services such as waste collection. To reduce corruption, SHAHAR introduced a practice whereby citizens pay their taxes or fees at a bank or the CSC—instead of paying a government employee directly—and receive a receipt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since SHAHAR started in 2014:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partner communities have raised &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-municipalities-raise-more-revenues-deliver-better-services-enhance-stability/&quot;&gt;legitimate municipal revenues&lt;/a&gt; by as much as 38 percent year over year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its partner municipalities improved their governance scores by an average of 239 percent between July 2015 and August 2016 in the areas of revenue and finances, planning, service delivery, administrative reform, and community outreach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Its partner municipalities have successfully bid out and completed 14 small infrastructure projects (such as new bus terminals, markets, renovated parks and sports fields, and improved drainage).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about what SHAHAR is doing to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-municipalities-raise-more-revenues-deliver-better-services-enhance-stability/&quot;&gt;improve local governance&lt;/a&gt; and service delivery, watch this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/204593033&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Philippines’ New Tax Bill Promises More Revenue for Social Programs, Infrastructure</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-new-tax-bill-promises-more-revenue-for-social-programs-infrastructure</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 20:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Bryan Schuetz</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-new-tax-bill-promises-more-revenue-for-social-programs-infrastructure</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It has been more than 15 years since the Government of the Philippines undertook its last comprehensive tax policy reform. Over that period, tax revenues have seen a steady decline, from a high of nearly 17 percent of GDP in 1997 to only &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/GC.TAX.TOTL.GD.ZS?locations=PH&quot;&gt;13.6 percent in 2016&lt;/a&gt;. This decline can be attributed to both domestic and external factors. On the international front, the Asian financial crisis of 1997–1998 and the global recession of 2008–2009 certainly contributed to sharp drop-offs. But the Government of the Philippines’ limited ability to enforce fiscal discipline also was a factor, allowing special interests to introduce loopholes, weaken tax laws, and chip away at previous reforms. These factors were compounded by lower import duties (motivated by the prospect of improving trade) and flaws in the 1997 excise tax reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/SBkjBbLfUQ7SFLOAP4Vz&quot; title=&quot;Philippines Infographic&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?dmj&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recent years have seen an uptick in the tax revenue-to-GDP ratio since the low of 12.1 percent reached in the post-recession year of 2010, helped by adjustments to corporate, excise, and value added tax rates in the early 2000s and &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GNP.PCAP.CD?locations=PH&quot;&gt;steadily increasing incomes&lt;/a&gt;. These recent increases were also in no small part due to the efforts of the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/philippines-facilitating-public-investment-fpi&quot;&gt;Facilitating Public Investment&lt;/a&gt; (FPI) program in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates/&quot;&gt;modernizing and expanding the electronic tax-filing system&lt;/a&gt;, which among other achievements increased the e-filing rate to 76.23 percent by October 2017, compared to 8 percent in 2013. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/philippines.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;philippines&quot; title=&quot;Participants at one of the roadshows for the Tax Reform for Acceleration and Inclusion bill (TRAIN). FPI Chief of Party Roberto Toso is third from left.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not content with capturing significantly more tax revenue through expanded e-filing, FPI has also been working to push sweeping tax reform legislation. Building on comprehensive technical support to the Department of Finance (DOF) and the Bureau of Internal Revenue (BIR), FPI facilitated passage of the Tax Reform for Acceleration and Inclusion bill (TRAIN), culminating with President Rodrigo Duterte signing it into law on December 19, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;The TRAIN Bill: A Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Reduces income taxes on 99 percent of taxpayers while increasing them for the wealthiest&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Raises taxes on certain goods and services (cars, fuel, tobacco, cosmetic surgery, tobacco, and sweetened beverages)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Removes 54 lines of exemption in the value added tax (VAT), while increasing the threshold from P1.9 million to P3 million (small business with annual sales of P3 million and below would now be exempt from paying VAT)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Levies new 6 percent estate and donor tax&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Increases rates for the documentary stamp tax (a tax on documents, instruments, loan agreements, and papers evidencing the acceptance, assignment, sale, or transfer of an obligation, right, or property) and imposes a tax on currency deposit units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major overhaul of the tax code, the TRAIN bill is expected to raise P130 billion (roughly US$2.5 billion) in new revenue, 70 percent of which will go toward funding the government’s “Build, Build, Build” infrastructure program and 30 percent toward social programs, such as the Unconditional Cash Transfer structure that provides P200 per month to the 10 million poorest Filipino families who will be affected by the higher prices of goods and services resulting from the bill. A major feature of the bill is the reduction of income taxes for most wage earners while increasing them for the very wealthy. This change in itself represents a net reduction in revenue, but is made up for by the introduction of new excise taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FPI drove outreach and consensus building for the legislation through nationwide tax reform roadshows in collaboration with the Philippine Chamber of Commerce and Industry. The resulting tax reform coalition—composed of private and business sector associations, the Open Government Regional Dialogues with the Philippine Open Government Partnership Secretariat, and civil society organizations—proved to be an effective advocate for bringing tax reform into the public discourse and garnering public support for the legislation. FPI also worked with the DOF’s Strategy, Economics, and Results Group and led meticulous assessments of the TRAIN bill’s Lower and Upper House versions, proposing detailed amendments and sharing them with DOF stakeholders to arrive at the final bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;h3&gt;TRAIN 2: Proposed Reforms&lt;/h3&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Reduces the corporate income tax rate from 30 percent to 25 percent by 2022, while expanding the tax base by 0.75 percent of GDP&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Enforces the minimum corporate income tax&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Allows BIR to prosecute tax cases&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Targets corporate incentives to activities with significant positive externalities, as specified in the strategic investments priority plan&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Eliminates VAT incentives: all firms to pay VAT and prove they export to be able to get a refund&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TRAIN’s passage begins to address some of the Government of the Philippines’ signature priorities, namely to invest heavily in infrastructure and to simplify the tax code. However, TRAIN is just the first of five planned reform bills. One major intended component of TRAIN 1 that was not finalized in time for the bill was the Tax Administration Reform Act (TARA). TARA was meant to complement TRAIN by providing a modernized tax environment that is conducive to the proper implementation of the Philippines tax law.  However, tax reform pragmatists in both Houses and the DOF decided to prioritize the passage of TRAIN 1 and leave TARA for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As FPI enters its fifth and final year of implementation, it will continue to support the tax reform agenda, including pursuing TARA in subsequent TRAIN packages. FPI will continue to provide technical studies, advice, training, outreach strategy, messaging, and other support to DOF, and we are already working with the BIR’s new Implementing Rules and Regulations to help roll out changes enacted in the bill. We will continue to advance the tax reform agenda as we look ahead to TRAIN 2 and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>With Elections Looming, Can Pakistan Fulfill Its Education Promise to Unschooled Children?</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More than 23 million children in Pakistan do not attend school. More than half of children who start at government schools drop out before completing primary school. These stark facts are harming a rising generation of Pakistanis already vulnerable to unemployment, instability, and extremism. And while upper-class Pakistanis enjoy excellent private schools and universities, much of the rest of the country has become resigned to derelict classrooms and substandard government-provided education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2013 and funded by the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID), the Alif Ailaan campaign is moving education to the front and center of the 2018 general election, in which 342 seats in parliament are at stake. In vying to make 2018 the “education election,” Alif Ailaan has inspired groups throughout Pakistani society—rural and urban, rich and poor, traditional and progressive—to mobilise in demand of improved public education. The campaign’s “ask” is succinct:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better budgets&lt;/strong&gt;—more government funds on education, better spent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better data&lt;/strong&gt;—led by Alif Ailaan’s annual &lt;a href=&quot;http://rankings.alifailaan.pk/&quot;&gt;Pakistan District Education Rankings&lt;/a&gt; that call out where government education is failing and why;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better teaching&lt;/strong&gt;—with a focus on mathematics and science; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better government schools&lt;/strong&gt;—with an emphasis on the poorest and most vulnerable 40 percent of the population who use them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximately 1.5 million supporters have signed up for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/&quot;&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/a&gt; campaign, including politicians from all major parties, educators, parents, and civil society organisations. The campaign’s Facebook account has amassed more than 2 million followers. The question now is whether this groundswell will translate into more and smarter funding for public education, more prestige for teachers, and higher-quality schools for millions of marginalized kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/pakistan-transforming-education-pakistan-tep&quot;&gt;Transforming Education in Pakistan&lt;/a&gt; (TEP) project, Alif Ailaan is implemented by DAI and London-based subcontractor Accadian Ltd. TEP’s assistance is not designed to pay for books or desks or rehabilitated schools. Instead, given that the Constitution of Pakistan guarantees government-funded education to every Pakistani child between the ages of 5 and 16, TEP’s job is to make parents aware of this right and help them demand high-quality schooling for their children. At the same time, TEP encourages politicians to deliver on the right to education and work with education providers to improve the quality of that education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan is a high-priority country for U.K. assistance. In designing the TEP programme, DFID concluded that a crucial long-term intervention—in terms of stabilisation, economic development, countering violent extremism, and meeting the needs of a fast-growing, younger population—would be to help tackle Pakistan’s education emergency. Alif Ailaan is on track to get more Pakistani children into school, stay there, and achieve literacy, numeracy, and other skills so they can contribute to a more stable and prosperous Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-graphic-1-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-graphic-1-new&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Galvanising Political Will, Mobilising Demand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In making education politically relevant, DAI and Accadian have drawn on political campaigning techniques to influence political will and mobilise demand. TEP identified and analysed every interest group involved in providing education and constructively engaged those group members willing to be part of positive change while marginalising any blockers. This outreach required creating a strong, independent, authoritative campaign that would become the leading voice for education reform in Pakistan, which is what we have built with Alif Ailaan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TEP team, led by DAI&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/mosharraf-zaidi&quot;&gt;Mosharraf Zaidi&lt;/a&gt;,  emphasizes smart political engagement to support reformers across all the main political parties and groupings, and to empower other stakeholders in the education system to understand what needs to be done and start doing it. As we come to the second set of elections to have taken place during the campaign (the first was in 2013), we will be refocusing attention explicitly on voters—especially parents—and helping them to make education a salient issue for politicians seeking their votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----TEP-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----TEP-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Importance of Smart Startup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In setting up Alif Ailaan, the most important first steps we made were recruiting the best Pakistani campaign team we could find. Our Islamabad-based team of more than 25 people were personally selected and have spent a good deal of time developing their skills as campaigners, first and foremost, and as professionals working to DAI’s high standards. We invested the rest of our inception period in testing our strategies and systems. TEP is not a typical development project—it involves generating political will and pushing for change—so we have been fortunate to have the active support of our colleagues at DFID Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the outset, TEP had to establish Alif Ailaan as a voice in the public political discourse but first and foremost to make people acknowledge the “education emergency” they face. Key to this was our lobbying the government to research, calculate, and publish a nationally accepted number for out-of-school children. Achieving consensus in 2013 that there were 25 million Pakistani children out of school was a critical initial achievement. Through sustained advocacy and communications efforts, TEP has since developed a layered understanding and buy-in around the four themes central to fixing Pakistan’s education system: budgets, data, quality of teaching, and the focus on government schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-graphic-2-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-graphic-2-new&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Is Your School Passing or Failing? Click Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TEP made education more pressing and locally relevant to politicians by building and launching a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/district_rankings&quot;&gt;nationwide data platform&lt;/a&gt; that uses the government’s own statistics to rate school districts in areas such as grades, security, water and toilets, enrollment, and gender equity. This data is open to parents and politicians alike and has spurred social and political discourse and competition between districts to move up in education rankings. We have also partnered with MIT media labs to track the frequency of media coverage on education stories, which is important to measure the impact of the campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-5&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2018 election will mark the end of the current Alif Ailaan campaign and present TEP with two challenges: first, achieving the “education election,” where education gets due prominence and the parties compete in their commitments to improve it; and second, achieving sustainability—embedding practices and ownership so the urgent work of transforming Pakistan’s education system can continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TEP has already embedded education issues into the political and social discourse, set a precedent of data-informed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/bulletin&quot;&gt;journalism and reporting&lt;/a&gt; on education, pioneered &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alifailaan.pk/publications&quot;&gt;ground-breaking publications&lt;/a&gt;, and lobbied for the government to research, calculate, and publish a nationally accepted number for out-of-school children. During and following the 2018 election, we believe the government provision of high-quality education for all Pakistani children will remain a top agenda item in manifestos and political party campaigns. Whoever wins the election will have much work to do. We and our partners will play our part in holding them to their commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liberia Moves to Reduce Donor Dependence by Improving its Ability to Invest in Itself</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/liberia-moves-to-reduce-donor-dependence-by-improving-its-ability-to-invest-in-itself</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 19:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/liberia-moves-to-reduce-donor-dependence-by-improving-its-ability-to-invest-in-itself</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Liberia has endured much turmoil in recent decades. Civil wars in the 1990s and 2000s saw the mass destruction of dams, bridges, power lines, and other infrastructure. Many of Liberia&amp;rsquo;s best and brightest citizens emigrated. Suffering from a large budget deficit, its government developed a deeper dependence on foreign aid. Furthermore, the Ebola virus epidemic of 2014–2015 killed more than 4,800 Liberians and terrified the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, after all this, people today in Liberia generally look forward with hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they have reason to do so. Liberia’s donor dependence could increasingly turn to self-reliance—if a second-year program by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) continues its recent success. The program’s goal—improve Liberia&amp;rsquo;s ability to pay for its own development—coincides with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/long-term-fiscal-reform-takes-root-in-el-salvador-and-elsewhere/&quot;&gt;broader movement&lt;/a&gt; by developing countries to mobilize domestic resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its outset in May 2016, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/liberia-revenue-generation-governance-and-growth-rg3&quot;&gt;Revenue Generation for Governance and Growth (RG3)&lt;/a&gt; project engaged the Liberia Revenue Authority (LRA) to jointly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/BENCHMARKING%20THE%20TAX%20SYSTEM%20IN%20LIBERIA.pdf&quot;&gt;benchmark Liberia tax policy and administration&lt;/a&gt; against international good practices. As a result, RG3 identified critical gaps and set the stage for tax reform in Liberia. Just one year in, the LRA has already achieved some impressive results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaps in Liberia&amp;rsquo;s tax practices identified by RG3’s benchmarking activity:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low goods and services, excise, corporate income, and property taxes compared with those of peers (see table below);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No electronic filing or payment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No mobile payments;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No tax payments through commercial banks;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No excise stamps for enforcement;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No tax-return processing center and low data availability as a result;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inability to introduce risk-based audit selection due to the limited data availability;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No automated compliance monitoring;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No risk-based arrears management;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No taxpayer advocate office at LRA;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited role of the LRA call center in promoting taxpayer education; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No regular taxpayer surveys.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Great Progress So Far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand for improved domestic resource mobilization and accountability is arising from both the government and taxpayers. Early on, the LRA and RG3 team ramped up taxpayer engagement by increasing the number of taxpayer inquiries to the LRA call center &lt;em&gt;tenfold&lt;/em&gt; through aggressive mobile text-messaging outreach. LRA and RG3 conducted an innovative text-based taxpayer perception survey as well as a cost-of-compliance survey using computer-assisted telephone interviewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LRA established a centralized data processing center that has already processed information from thousands of tax returns into LRA databases, improving transparency for taxpayers encompassing some 70 percent of revenues and generating crucial information—on topics such as wages, employment, and property ownership—to inform audit selection and improve revenue forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taxpayers gained a strong ally in the form of a newly established Taxpayer Advocate’s Office. Already, the office has repeatedly stood up for taxpayer’s rights—in areas such as customs clearance and verification of tax compliance—thereby reducing opportunities for corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DAI&amp;rsquo;s Tax Benchmarking Approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two decades, DAI has produced tax-benchmarking training and studies for partner governments to assist them in benchmarking tax policy, customs, and tax administration against international good practices. Tax benchmarking helps identify the biggest gaps in tax policy and tax administration, inform tax reform strategy, and prioritize tax reform interventions. DAI is currently implementing fiscal reform and domestic revenue mobilization projects in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/when-tax-reform-leads-to-increased-funding-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;El Salvador&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-state-partnership-accountability-responsiveness-and-capability-sparc&quot;&gt;Nigeria&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates/&quot;&gt;the Philippines&lt;/a&gt;, and elsewhere.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the LRA allowed taxes to be paid for the first time through commercial banks and their branches, as much as $7.3 million in taxes was paid using this method though August 2017—leading to the first electronic tax payments wired to government coffers and the first, albeit rudimentary, email-based electronic filing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LRA and RG3 interventions have also increased compliance. The number of tax payment transactions increased by some 48 percent in March–August 2017 compared with the same period in 2016, which is expected to lead to increased revenues for the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LRA and RG3 are close to launching the first mobile tax payments. And finally, in close cooperation with the Ministry of Finance and Development Planning (MFDP), RG3 has developed a revised draft excise tax legislation that should help pave the way for a significant revenue increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/QBehpEVGpci6ueSMpwHz&quot; title=&quot;Liberia&amp;amp;amp;#39;s Deficit/Revenues vs. GDP&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?ur0&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on a productive first year and the benchmarking exercise, RG3 has established the following objectives for the next phase of the program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve risk-based audit selection so that LRA auditors focus on taxpayer cases that are most likely to yield revenues;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop microsimulation models to forecast revenues and analyze potential policy outcomes;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce e-filing to further reduce cash transactions between tax officers and taxpayers;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch mobile payments;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze pros and cons of decentralizing real estate tax revenues, so local property taxes pay for local services;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate payment reconciliation so compliant taxpayers are certified as such;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate LRA management reports to improve decision making; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce excise stamps to generate revenue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Liberian government has been a positive partner in tax reform, and we are hopeful that will continue for two more years under RG3—and beyond—under the newly elected president, former international soccer star George Weah. The government has great upside in terms of revenue generation and, in turn, expenditure management. While Liberia has suffered a great deal over the past two decades, we believe 4.5 million Liberians are eager to see through the tax reforms that will make government more accountable and productive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Women’s Land Rights and the Problem of Polygamy: A Proposal in Ethiopia</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/womens-land-rights-and-the-problem-of-polygamy-a-proposal-in-ethiopia</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 14:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/womens-land-rights-and-the-problem-of-polygamy-a-proposal-in-ethiopia</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite being illegal, polygamous marriage remains alive and well in Ethiopia, and that poses some obvious challenges when it comes to land rights. Statistics from 2011 reveal that 11 percent of married women in Ethiopia share a husband with one or two other wives. Polygamy affects women’s rights to property and income because it is unclear whose rights take precedence under the law when the husband becomes ill or passes away. Unfortunately, federal and regional land proclamations in Ethiopia don’t address the registration of polygamous families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.K. Department for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/ethiopia-land-investment-transformation-lift&quot;&gt;Land Investment for Transformation (LIFT)&lt;/a&gt; programme consistently runs up against this legal grey area in its work to enhance land rights in rural Ethiopia. But based on our research into the topic, we have come up with a couple of suggestions to clarify and advance women’s rights in cases of plural marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/LIFT%20pic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;LIFT pic&quot; title=&quot;The LIFT team performing research.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different regions of the country handle the registration of polygamous families in different ways: some include all the wives in one certificate; others register wives separately. Also, registration of land holdings is typically led by the husband, who may treat one wife better than others, leaving co-wives at a legal disadvantage. A husband who favors one wife over another can encourage non-eligible wives to register, denying those who are eligible. Many co-wives may not even know whether they are listed as a joint land owner or the extent of their entitlement to land. In regions where photos of co-wives are required for land registration, co-wives often think that this photo ensures joint ownership of land and hence that they do not need to be involved in subsequent stages of land certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other complicated situations include instances where a parcel of land is registered in the name of the first wife, but in practice a co-wife actually cultivates and benefits from the produce. This state of affairs poses a problem upon division of the property, as the land certificate does not reflect the user, and of course a divorce or death of one of the wives or the husband naturally triggers disputes around the division of property and inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Land differs by nature from other kinds of property—perhaps especially in Ethiopia. The country’s land policy posits that land is not owned by individuals but by the State and the people of Ethiopia. When wives in polygamous marriages request land, therefore, it is a demand they are making as a citizen, not merely as a spouse. It is well documented that recognizing and formalising women’s land rights is a key step toward women’s economic and social advancement, as land is the most important social and economic asset in rural Ethiopia. These rights increase women’s economic empowerment and status in the household and community, and help to ensure the health and wellbeing of children. This right should therefore be granted equally, to include women in polygamous households.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_6fdec906-bda6-4fb0-9ab8-eda4cb2aab34&quot; title=&quot;LIFT Pie&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?Fe6&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What to Do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LIFT team is urging Ethiopian policymakers to address this situation and help close a debilitating gap in land governance. Based on our research, we recommend that the following steps be taken:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Endorse the articles on polygamous wives’ registration in the draft federal land proclamation that is currently under review. A study conducted by LIFT identified seven ways to register the land use rights of women in polygamous unions, of which we recommend two, based on their relative advantage in providing better security for all members in a polygamous household while minimising the risk of conflict between children and co-wives (see box). The decision regarding which option to adopt and implement would best be decided by the respective regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align procedures for polygamous households’ land registration with the binding judgement made by the Federal Supreme Court of Cassation, which ruled that although polygamy is illegal, its prevalence in Ethiopia means that all property should be divided equally between the husband and wives. Land certification should conform to this decision. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Align procedures for polygamous households’ land registration with Article 34/4 of the Constitution, which has provision for polygamous marriages on cultural or religious grounds—despite prohibition by the Ethiopian criminal and family codes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrate into the design of land-related programmes a provision to support the registration of women’s land use rights in both monogamous and polygamous households.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Options Proposed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Husband registers his share of the land with one wife. The rest of the wives register their own shares by themselves. First, the land is divided into equal parts, according to the number of wives (and includes the husband). The husband then chooses one wife to register with. The rest of the shares are owned only by the wives. For example, if a husband has three wives, the land is divided by four. The husband and one wife combine their shares to create a joint share. Each of the other wives has sole rights to a ¼ of the land. This option is thought to discourage polygamy, particularly because if the husband decides to take yet another wife, the new wife would become the preferred wife and the husband’s land share would shrink further. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Option 2:&lt;/strong&gt; All wives and the husband register separately. Every wife and the husband get an individual, equal share in their own names. In this option, everyone is separate and each person has rights to his or her own equal share of the land size. This option works when the husband has difficulty in choosing one of the wives as his joint landholder or when rivalry exists among the wives wishing to register with the husband as the joint holder.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polygamy is a challenging topic with cultural implications far beyond the land sector. But equally, LIFT’s work to enhance clarity, consistency, and understanding around women’s land rights in plural marriages offers an opportunity to achieve far-reaching impact. If we can embed good governance practice in all aspects of land rights registration, we will materially advance women’s land rights—with all that implies for women’s social and economic empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gathering the Evidence to Mobilize Domestic Resources for Health Care</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/marshaling-the-evidence-to-better-help-developing-countries-improve-and-afford-their-health-services</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 17:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/marshaling-the-evidence-to-better-help-developing-countries-improve-and-afford-their-health-services</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two key areas of development assistance have been merging quickly: health care and domestic resource mobilization. The goal is to help developing countries &lt;em&gt;afford&lt;/em&gt; to invest in their national health systems and institutions and do so wisely. Many countries &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/long-term-fiscal-reform-takes-root-in-el-salvador-and-elsewhere/&quot;&gt;want to do more&lt;/a&gt; to fund their own development, and donors are on board to assist. But there is little evidence on how to do so effectively in the pursuit of greater health security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This knowledge gap prompted the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-health-finance-and-governance&quot;&gt;Health Finance and Governance&lt;/a&gt; (HFG) project to conduct a four-part study, “Marshalling the Evidence for Health Governance,” funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID). Our technical working group analyzed data on how public financial management (PFM) affects health governance and produced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hfgproject.org/public-financial-management-report/&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; of our findings. Our HFG colleagues concurrently produced reports on the evidence as it applies to policy and regulation, uses of knowledge in health systems, and accountability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----DRM-Health-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----DRM-Health-1&quot; title=&quot;Winnie Koech, nurse, with a client at Tenwek Mission Hospital in Kenya. Koech graduated with assistance from the Afya Elimu Fund, an affordable loan mechanism developed by USAID, IntraHealth International, FUNZOKenya, and local governmental and private-sector partners. Photo by Georgina Goodwin for IntraHealth International.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/when-tax-reform-leads-to-increased-funding-for-health-services/&quot;&gt;experience in El Salvador&lt;/a&gt; confirms that donor assistance in PFM can enable a country to provide more health services. Our HFG technical working group—which includes representatives from the World Health Organization, World Bank, Abt Associates, and DAI—set out to gather more evidence of what works, or not, in helping countries improve their health services; increase patients’ demand for, access to, and utilization of services; increase adoption of healthy behaviors; and protect people from debilitating health costs. In compiling this report, we also learned more about how health governance is evolving at the country level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Care Meets PFM in El Salvador&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three rounds of fiscal reform in El Salvador enabled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out-of-pocket health spending per capita to decrease from nearly $100 in 2003 to $61 in 2013, while government health spending per capita increased from $93 to $142.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Government health spending to increase as a share of total health spending from less than 40 percent in 1995 to 67 percent in 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citizens’ out-of-pocket spending from 1995 to 2013 to decrease from more than 60 percent to less than 30 percent of total health spending.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are the key implications from the HFG report:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Three Ways to Increase Domestic Funding for Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Country policymakers can increase funding for health by 1) increasing tax revenues, 2) prioritizing health funding, and 3) increasing efficiency in health spending:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing tax revenues&lt;/strong&gt; through improved tax policy and collection is a proven winner among donor-funded programs. Our review of the evidence found that, as a proportion of gross domestic product, government tax revenue was significantly below its potential in many low- and middle-income countries. But that is a fixable state of affairs. USAID programs implemented by DAI, for instance, have increased domestic revenues in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/long-term-fiscal-reform-takes-root-in-el-salvador-and-elsewhere/&quot;&gt;El Salvador&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates/&quot;&gt;the Philippines&lt;/a&gt;, and elsewhere. In these countries, PFM assistance led to reducing the cost and increasing the ease of tax compliance, reducing corruption by automating financial systems, and the adoption of enforcement approaches based on targeting areas at high risk for cheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we found not all tax revenues to be equal when it comes to benefitting health funding. One multi-country study showed pro-poor taxes—such as on profits and capital gains—seemed to support expanding health coverage, while consumption taxes—such as on goods and services—reduced the ability of the poor to afford essential health care and were associated with increased rates of post-neonatal, infant, and under-5 mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prioritizing health funding&lt;/strong&gt; helps ensure that increased government revenues lead to improved health care. Policy makers can champion this cause by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advocating for policies that make the economic case for health in terms of impact on educational attainment, employment, and economic growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Producing budget planning and justifications that prioritize health financing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a tax fund specifically for health, such as dedicating a portion of tax revenues to health services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing taxes or fees earmarked for health, such as taxes on mobile phone calls, financial transactions, alcoholic beverages, and tobacco.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decentralizing health spending to increase local pressure and accountability to fund health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the five emerging “BRICS” economies (Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa), total government spending on health is markedly less—from 8.1 to 12.7 percent—than in many countries in the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, which in 2016. The United States, for example, spent 17.2 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence is mixed in some areas of health reform—for example, in decentralization. In Ghana, a survey concluded that only 20 percent of the treasury&amp;rsquo;s non-wage public health expenditure reached frontline facilities. In Senegal, Health Decentralization Funds took 10 months on average to be at the disposal of providers. This suggests great vulnerability for leakage, but current data is woefully slim—the Ghana and Senegal surveys were from 2000 and 2004, respectively, highlighting the need to capture more—and more current—insights on how assistance would be best targeted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leakage of Recurrent Health Expenditures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leakage: theft, corruption, and misallocation or misuse of government/donor money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can occur at any point from the ministry of finance to the facility level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-salary recurrent expenditures include rent, office supplies, medical supplies, pharmaceuticals.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing efficiency in health spending&lt;/strong&gt; requires planning, control, and oversight. The HFG report suggests fiscal reform actions that could help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medium-term expenditure frameworks or multi-year sector budgeting plans can improve predictability in health funding and, consequently, the health sector’s ability to spend more productively and achieve results more predictably. Countries may also consider better yearly planning—looking at gaps in processes for collating and prioritizing health needs and allocating health funding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Automated systems have been shown to improve control of expenditures. By introducing two interventions—an integrated financial management information system (IFMIS) and e-procurement—countries can reduce waste and fraud by increasing transparency and accountability. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procurement is often a source of corruption and ineffective political spending. E-procurement can reduce fraud and waste and save money by reducing transaction costs as well as the cost of drugs, medical supplies, and other commodities. An IFMIS introduces greater control, transparency, and accountability into the expenditure process, reducing human error and corruption through a series of automated checks and controls enforced for all transactions. Although no research has been conducted on IFMIS’ effect on the health sector and health outcomes, it is a proven PFM intervention that raises the budget process to higher levels of transparency and accountability and expedites government operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Counterfeit Drugs (estimated US$75 billion global market)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Counterfeit: illegally imported or manufactured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outside national laboratory or testing regimes; no way to &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what they are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May not be drugs at all, may be expired, have altered formulas, or be genuine drugs illegally imported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can kill if people think they are taking genuine drugs but are not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can contribute to anti-microbial resistance when not strong enough to kill microbes.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----DRM-Health-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----DRM-Health-3&quot; title=&quot;Representatives of Haiti&amp;#39;s Health Directorate analyze data for a data quality workshop under USAID&amp;#39;s Strategic Health Information System Program, implemented by DAI.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Making Health Spending More Accountable and Responsive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stewards of health systems and representatives of civil society, policy makers should take steps to improve oversight and accountability in health spending. To do so, they may also consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving the analysis, visualization, and communication of health financing data to enhance understanding and use of that data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automating reports to increase transparency and accountability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing oversight via audit and reporting for better accountability within health systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decentralizing control of health procurement, services, and funding to local authorities to increase local accountability and responsiveness and create a tighter feedback loop for oversight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----DRM-Health-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----DRM-Health-2&quot; title=&quot;Midwife training in Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Knowledge Gaps That Need to be Filled&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of our technical working group searched 16 databases, websites, and organizations for articles and studies on the role of PFM in health systems and outcomes. We uncovered 165 articles, 46 of which were found to be fully relevant. Team members dissected the articles and extracted useful data for input into a database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research on PFM for health outcomes—especially current research—is lacking in several areas. For example, the team found no data on the role and effects on health systems of parliamentary oversight and the policy environment, of a Supreme Audit Institution, or of budget classification—such as removing duplicate line items, miscoding, and reducing the number of line items and off-budget transactions. More research is also needed on the effects of e-procurement, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://supplier.treasury.go.ke/site/tenders.go/index.php/pages/about&quot;&gt;procure-to-pay tool&lt;/a&gt; used in Kenya. As seen in one study, this tool is a good option for health system managers and procurement agencies to improve PFM and health outcomes simultaneously by increasing transparency and reducing corruption-enabling time lag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When developing countries make improved health outcomes a domestic development priority, they take the first necessary step toward &lt;em&gt;affording&lt;/em&gt; to pursue this goal. The next step—welcoming assistance in health and fiscal reform—puts the onus on the donor and implementer to get the assistance right. Looking ahead, we believe findings from this report and the others from “Marshalling the Evidence for Health Governance” mark a significant step forward in optimizing activities—and results—in health governance assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To Realize the Promise of Renewables, Address the Concerns of Local People</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/to-realize-the-promise-of-renewables-address-the-concerns-of-local-people</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2017 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/to-realize-the-promise-of-renewables-address-the-concerns-of-local-people</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2009, in rural Pennsylvania, as head of the Renewable Energy Center, I attended a community meeting with the Army Corps of Engineers about a proposed wind farm in Ogletown, in Somerset County. I was told that previous meetings on the topic had been heated enough that a police presence was necessary—and welcomed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One by one, members of this small community expressed their fears. Some believed that wind turbines cause cancer. One person was afraid the blades would throw mercury. Another wondered if the turbines would kill local fish. Many believed wind turbines cause anxiety, headaches, cognitive issues, and emotional disturbances. Some stated that wind turbines cause epileptic seizures. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recall this experience to point out that aversion to change, hostility to potentially beneficial technology, and susceptibility to rumor—what we might in the current climate call “fake news”—is far from limited to the developing world. When people are angry, anxious, afraid, it becomes easier for them to believe what would otherwise seem outlandish, whether they live in central Pennsylvania or central America. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there are proven ways to engage and bring on board these communities. Our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/honduras-ProParque-GEMA&quot;&gt;ProParque&lt;/a&gt; project and its experience introducing small hydro power to highland Honduran communities is a case in point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/waterfall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;waterfall&quot; title=&quot;Central Hidroeléctrica Río Blanco. The Pulhapanzak Waterfall is where the water originates.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development from 2011 to 2016, ProParque was designed to conserve biodiversity, create jobs, and strengthen Honduras’ capacity for mitigating and adapting to climate change. As part of its natural resource protection mandate, ProParque began to promote small hydro. Most of the country’s electricity at that time was generated from diesel and oil, which for Honduras meant expensive electricity and exposure to price fluctuations. The Honduran government had pledged to reduce its dependence on imported oil and reverse its electricity generation mix from 60 percent oil and 40 percent renewables to 60 percent renewables and 40 percent oil. Between 2014 and 2015, it made headway toward this goal through a dramatic increase in solar and continued growth in hydro, wind, biomass, and waste. It now plans to have 95 percent of energy supplied from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hydroworld.com/articles/2017/11/honduran-authorities-define-details-of-planned-hydroelectric-plants.html&quot;&gt;renewable sources&lt;/a&gt; by 2027. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is “small hydro”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Honduras, the environmental agency, MiAmbiente, classifies “small hydro” as 15 megawatts (MW)—enough to power a number of small villages—or less in generating capacity. Small hydro can be a dam or a run-of-the-river system that diverts a portion of the water to a generator while leaving the rest in the waterway. A run-of-the-river has significantly less impact on the ecosystem than a dam. Large hydro projects invariably involve at least some resettlement of people. Given its size, small hydro typically means faster construction, easier transport of equipment in remote areas, and less need for civil works construction. However, many Hondurans have failed to distinguish between small and large hydro, not realizing that small hydro projects—done properly—have relatively small environmental impact.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, increasing the proportion of energy generated by renewable sources means taking advantage of wind and hydro resources where they exist, not where it would be convenient for us to have them. And despite the potential for hydropower to support economic development—and the fact that distributed generation increases energy security locally and nationally—we encountered several barriers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important was local opposition. Communities were afraid of large hydropower projects, and it was commonly believed that hydropower causes cancer and even abortions—concerns that extended even to smaller hydropower projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, two projects that would have provided 2.7 MW of power in the buffer zone of Nombre de Dios National Park were stopped because people in the communities in the watershed expected the project to pay them 40 percent of the plant revenue, even though they were only run-of-the-river and no resettlements were required. Two projects in the buffer zone of Sierra de Agalta National Park, that would have provided 8.9 MW, were stalled due to conflicts between the community and developers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_f26c52a1-1c54-4d7b-bd12-7bf1be0b8a0c&quot; title=&quot;ProParque Results&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?qmS&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Informing the Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community acceptance of renewable energy plants is critical. Indeed, in most countries, including Honduras, consultations with local communities are not just good practice, they are legally required. Local involvement in the project development stage can result in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301421508003121&quot;&gt;greater acceptance&lt;/a&gt; and acceptance is easier when the communities are better informed. Especially in developing countries, communities often lack understanding of the technology, financing, or viability of electric power options, limiting their ability to negotiate with developers. ProParque tackled this constraint head on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, to improve the ability of civil society organizations to advocate and negotiate on their own behalf, ProParque produced a flip chart template and guide for teachers to develop educational campaigns about renewable energy. In addition, the team held workshops for 33 municipalities, seven government offices, three educational centers, and co-managers of national parks; and held 26 seminars on community education about renewable energy for 517 participants—196 of them women. Explaining hydro technology and projects in clear and simple terms, these materials equipped local schools and municipalities to lead their own educational programs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Spreading the Word&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with the U.S. Forestry Service, local nongovernmental groups, MiAmbiente, and the Honduran Association of Renewable Energy Producers, ProParque developed other materials that are beginning to gain traction in Honduras and beyond, including a Good Practices Guide, Lessons Learned in the Socialization Process, and Lessons Learned in the Socialization of Hydroelectric Projects—the latter building on the experience of several projects around protected areas. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The International Centre for Hydropower asked ProParque to share these materials and help the Nicaraguan Ministry of Energy and MiAmbiente develop a course on “Water Governance and Socio-Environmental Management for Hydroelectric Development in Latin America.” Held in Managua, the course attracted participants from Nicaragua and from neighboring Colombia, Costa Rica, El Salvador, Guatemala, and Peru. These materials have now been shared with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/Nepal-Program-for-Aquatic-Natural-Resources-Improvement-PANI&quot;&gt;Program for Aquatic Natural Resources Improvement (PANI)&lt;/a&gt;, another USAID program that is building the capacity of community groups to serve as watchdogs and ensure compliance with environmental and social obligations in Nepal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Community Benefits Are Key&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies in the United States, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0264837709000039&quot;&gt;Scotland&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0301421511001972&quot;&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt; have shown that attitudes toward wind power are more positive among people who derive financial benefit from the projects and in areas with some degree of community ownership of them. It is logical to assume that the same principle would apply to small hydro projects in Honduras and other developing countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, local communities benefit from power plant development through payments for land or land use, local direct employment, local indirect employment through supply chains, and an increased tax base. These benefits are harder to realize in countries where indigenous people lack clear title to land or the skills needed by project developers and operators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is increasingly common for renewable energy projects to offer an explicit social benefit to communities to obtain their cooperation or at least mitigate their opposition. These separate and additional economic benefits range from ad hoc gifts—such as contributions to local sports programs—to legally binding annual payments. Social payments may in some countries be legally required to gain access to a resource. In Honduras, financial institutions will not lend to renewable energy projects absent such a social element. But developers recognize that these payments mitigate risk by encouraging local acceptance. Especially in projects that involve dams instead of run-of-the-river operations, communities perceive that adverse effects have been acknowledged and compensation provided. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another approach gaining ground internationally is to give local community members an ownership stake in the projects. Projects that pay only those people with title to affected property tend to run into difficulties from aggrieved residents who didn’t receive such compensation. Projects that provide a one-time give away, such as a sports field, find that two years later their contribution is no longer remembered or valued. However, if a broader swathe of local people owns part of the development, those owners have a long-term interest in its success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/water%20tunnel.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;water tunnel&quot; title=&quot;The local community has an ownership stake in Central Hidroeléctrica Río Blanco.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value transferred in the collective local ownership varies from project to project, of course, but it might be the equivalent of what a developer could spend on a donated sports field. The difference is that this stake represents a salable asset, perhaps one of the few assets local men and women have ever had. Perhaps this ownership stake increases their resilience in difficult times. If they receive dividends once the project hits profitability, they will have a small but additional income stream that will help offset any negative emotions about the development. 
Certifying the ownership stake individually, rather than by household, helps ensure that women benefit as well as men. 
Furthermore, making the community benefit an ownership stake instead of an initial gift aids the developer by postponing social payments from the risky, capital-intensive initial stage to the point when the plant is bringing in revenue in excess of its expenses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Administering the benefits of such small ownership stakes may cost more than the benefits themselves, but the payback in community cooperation is worth it. Ongoing payments, even if small, generate trust and maintain a positive relationship between the community and the power plant which can head off or reduce potential confrontations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Collaboration and Integration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many countries, including Honduras and Nepal, forest areas are menaced by illegal logging, mining, and the expansion of agriculture. Small, sustainably managed renewable energy projects present an alternative that can improve the quality of life and bring new opportunities to local people, while preserving the watershed. But to deliver on this promise we need ongoing collaboration between developers and communities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ogletown, I regret to say, the wind farm still has not been built. The sponsoring company cancelled it in 2012. Over the course of the ProParque project, hydropower in Honduras increased from 149 MW in 2011 to 252 MW in &lt;a href=&quot;http://global-climatescope.org/en/country/honduras/#/enabling-framework&quot;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt;. The project worked directly with 21 stalled projects to get them through approvals by MiAmbiente. This success is due in large part to ProParque’s integrated  approach: informing communities, educating developers and government officials in best socialization practices, and delivering lasting benefits to local people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Orangutan Species Discovered in Forest  Supported by USAID Conservation Program</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-orangutan-species-discovered-in-forest-block-saved-by-usaid-conservation-program</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 16:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-orangutan-species-discovered-in-forest-block-saved-by-usaid-conservation-program</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More than eight years ago, DAI staff tromped through the Batang Toru forest of North Sumatra, Indonesia, counting nests, observing behavior, and collecting field evidence on one of the oldest members of the great ape family—the orangutan. What they did not realize was that this group of orangutans was an entirely unrecognized species—the Tapanuli orangutan—that we now know is endemic to 475 square miles of upland forest in the Batang Toru Ecosystem south of Lake Toba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cell.com/current-biology/fulltext/S0960-9822(17)31245-9&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; in the November 2, 2017, journal of &lt;em&gt;Current Biology&lt;/em&gt;, the Tapanuli orangutan is thought to have been isolated from the Bornean and Sumatran species for 10,000 to 20,000 years and is genetically and behaviorally distinct from both species. With a population of fewer than 800 individuals, the Tapanuli is considered the most endangered of all great apes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe allowfullscreen width=&#39;640&#39; height=&#39;360&#39; src=&#39;//assets.nationalgeographic.com/modules-video/latest/assets/ngsEmbeddedVideo.html?guid=0000015f-7e0d-d63a-addf-fe9f93130000&#39; frameborder=&#39;0&#39; scrolling=&#39;no&#39;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, DAI was implementing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/indonesia-orangutan-conservation-services-program-ocsp&quot;&gt;Orangutan Conservation Services Program (OCSP)&lt;/a&gt; funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)—a program designed to address, reduce, or eliminate threats to orangutan survival in selected sites in Sumatra and Kalimantan (Indonesian Borneo). The primary threat to orangutans is loss of habitat—over the past 20 years, 80 percent of suitable orangutan habitat &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.orangutans.com.au/Orangutans-Survival-Information/Loss-of-habitat.aspx&quot;&gt;has been lost&lt;/a&gt;. A decade ago, USAID recognized the imminent danger of orangutan species extinction and pledged to work with the government of Indonesia to address the primary drivers of habitat loss—illegal logging and the conversion of forest to produce oil palm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Balancing Conservation and Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting in 2007, the OCSP team worked in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.batangtoru.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/Location_20171101_ENG_NoOU_B.jpg&quot;&gt;West Batang Toru Forest Block (WBTFB)&lt;/a&gt;—covering the South, Central, and North Tapanuli districts—to bring together district officials, local nongovernmental organizations (NGOs), and community leaders and develop an &lt;em&gt;action plan&lt;/em&gt; to preserve orangutan habitat. DAI used techniques including integrated spatial planning and weaving together “multifunctional landscapes” that balance economic land use—such as production forestry and oil palm plantations—with maintaining corridors of intact orangutan habitat. As part of the design, the OCSP Sumatra regional office—led by Darrell Kitchener and Pahrian Siregar—surveyed a population of around 380 orangutan individuals in WBTFB, the remote group that was recently identified as the Tapanuli species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----OCSP-4-closeup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----OCSP-4-closeup&quot; title=&quot;Photo by Andrew Watson/DAI.&quot;&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OCSP also worked with local NGOs to develop a spatial plan to restore forest corridors and reduce tree removal from water catchment zones critical for maintaining ecological flows and supporting local communities in and around the orangutan habitat. With support from all three district governments, OCSP and local NGOs successfully petitioned the government to reclassify WBTFB as watershed protection forest, a critical first step in protecting this vital orangutan habitat. Work continues today to limit the forest fragmentation in the ecosystem and reestablish corridors for the Tapanuli orangutans, which rely on continuous forest canopy to survive. Today approximately 800 Tapanuli orangutan live in the Batang Forest ecosystem, and without continued and careful conservation management, per the studies’ authors, we could see the extinction of the species in our lifetime. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Orangutan Conservation Services Program Select Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implemented conservation activities in 3.5 million hectares, covering 40 percent of Indonesia’s orangutan habitat, and improving the management of 1.3 million hectares critical for orangutans and other globally important species.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convened key actors to provide input into the Ministry of Forestry’s National Orangutan Strategy and Action Plan 2007–2017, which was announced by the Indonesian President at the United Nations Climate Change Conference in Bali in 2007, and commits the Indonesian government to stabilizing all orangutan populations by 2017.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A key victory in East Kalimantan, photo below, saw the indigenous Dayak people of Wehea awarded Indonesia’s highest environmental honor for protecting and managing 38,000 hectares of rainforest from lowland to mountain. The area—an important water and medicinal plant source for the Wehea people and home to 500 to 750 orangutans—was declared protected by the local government, which helped fund its management while private firms helped fund infrastructure.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----OCSP2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----OCSP2&quot; title=&quot;In East Kalimantan, the indigenous Dayak people of Wehea were awarded Indonesia’s highest environmental honor for protecting and managing 38,000 hectares of rainforest, home to 500 to 750 orangutans.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Investing Time to Ensure Local Ownership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We suspected that the orangutan inhabiting the Batang Toru forests might be a different sub-species than those in the Leuser ecosystem to the north,” said former OCSP Chief of Party Paul Hartman. “But that this has been found to be an entirely new species is both surprising and exciting. With this extraordinary find it is now critical to ensure the survival of this most threatened orangutan species.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent article in Current Biology brought a sense of pride and excitement to DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/environment-and-energy&quot;&gt;Environment&lt;/a&gt; team. “Our work often fits within three- to five-year contracts, yet generating results often takes time beyond the end of the project cycle,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/andrew-watson&quot;&gt;Andrew Watson&lt;/a&gt;, the team’s managing director. “When work that began with OCSP in 2007 has contributed to a major scientific discovery in 2017, we realize that the time and patience our teams invest in ensuring local ownership of conservation programming is all worth it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key members of our OCSP team are now on the frontlines of orangutan conservation in the region. DAI’s Sumatra Regional Coordinator Pahrian Siregar went on to earn his Ph.D. in environmental science with a focus on landscape management of orangutan habitat; Field Scientist Dr. Suci Atmoko is a candidate for the 2018 Indianapolis Prize for animal conservation; and our Deputy Chief of Party, Dr. Jamartin Sihite, currently serves as the CEO for the Borneo Orangutan Survival Foundation, one of the most prominent international NGOs focused on orangutan rehabilitation and forest release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this new species discovery is a landmark event for the 21st century, it is also a call to action to protect the high-elevation forest in Batang Toru. Plans to develop a hydropower dam on the nearby Batang Toru river and encroachment by palm oil plantations continue to threaten this critical orangutan habitat. DAI is confident that leading Indonesian conservation experts, including our project alumni, will continue to champion orangutan habitat protection so that our generation is not responsible for the extinction of one of our oldest ancestors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EU Funds Totaling €4.1 Billion Aim to Boost Investment, Private Sector Engagement in Africa and European Neighbourhood Countries</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/eu-launches-26-billion-fund-to-attract-investment-in-the-european-neighbourhood-and-africas-fragile-states</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 19:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/eu-launches-26-billion-fund-to-attract-investment-in-the-european-neighbourhood-and-africas-fragile-states</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nowhere do entrepreneurs and investors face more risk than in fragile states where jobs and economic growth are most needed. To mitigate this risk, the EU is launching the European Fund for Sustainable Development (EFSD), part of the External Investment Plan (EIP). The EFSD brings together €2.6 billion from the existing &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/europeaid/policies/innovative-financial-instruments-blending/blending-operations_en&quot;&gt;blended-finance operations&lt;/a&gt; in Africa and the European Neighbourhood region and the new guarantee for €1.5 billion. The EIP will be formally announced at the 6th African-EU Business Forum 27–28 November in Abidjan, Ivory Coast. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EIP represents a new approach to development aid. Funds will be managed through partner lending institutions in target countries, overseen by the Brussels-based Secretariat of the EIP. This reduced-risk financing is projected to generate &lt;em&gt;tens of billions&lt;/em&gt; of euros in additional public and private capital investment and guarantees from businesses and EU Member States in the coming years. DAI is assisting in key areas of the investment strategy through its management of the EU-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-trade-private-sector-development-and-engagement-and-regional-integration-facility&quot;&gt;Trade, Private Sector Development and Engagement (TPSD/E) Facility&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----EIP-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----EIP-4&quot; title=&quot;Port of Mombasa, Kenya.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fund aims to stimulate growth in some of the world’s most investment-starved markets, such as the Central African Republic, Mali, Somalia, Sudan, and other countries in sub-Saharan Africa, as well as in the EU Neighbourhood countries. Along with their chronic instability, these and other fragile states have something else in common: growing populations that need goods, services, and jobs. The EIP will make it easier for local businesspeople to show their entrepreneurial energy, and for external parties to invest in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to local financing, the EIP will support risk-reduced, market-targeted investments in these countries. With more than half the world’s foreign assistance provided by the EU and its Member States, the EIP has enormous potential to generate growth in developing economies and influence new approaches by assistance donors, including in the emerging area of &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-development-assistance-to-catalyze-sound-investments-in-emerging-and-developing-markets/&quot;&gt;blended finance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/wT6B85nAU0m924g72Gmx&quot; title=&quot;TSPD EIP Final&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?KmO&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Serving Africa&amp;rsquo;s, EU Neighbourhood&amp;rsquo;s Hungry Markets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite strong economic gains in certain countries, the African continent has seen minimal job growth in recent years due largely to poor business-enabling environments, limited financing opportunities, and the fragility that tends to deter investors. The resulting high unemployment drives further instability and migration within Africa and to Europe and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This downward investment trend is derived in part from a global decline in foreign direct investment (FDI) following the 2008 financial crisis. Coupled with simmering conflict in multiple African countries, this dip has led to decelerating economic growth across the continent. While African gross domestic product grew at an average of 5.4 percent annually from 2000 to 2015, it has since slowed to 3.3 percent. The stagnation in FDI has disproportionately affected Africa’s fragile states, which face the additional disadvantage of higher costs to establish a business—it is three times more costly to set up a business in Somalia and the Democratic Republic of the Congo, for example, than in more developed African nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the lack of viable employment opportunities in many African countries has driven an unprecedented number of migrants to attempt dangerous journeys to Europe by sea and land. In the long term, the population on the African continent is expected to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/development/desa/publications/world-population-prospects-the-2017-revision.html&quot;&gt;double by 2050&lt;/a&gt; and fuel increasing demand for jobs, goods, and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, many European Neighbourhood countries suffer from sluggish growth, high unemployment (especially among young people), low employment participation by women and young people, below-average FDI, and rising public debt. Some countries have endured periods of civil unrest or conflicts that have damaged the region’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EU Neighbourhood countries also face underdeveloped infrastructure, poor human capital development, weak competition in internal goods and services markets, lagging digital economy development, and above all, weak business environments that present obstacles to growth and job creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EIP-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EIP-3&quot; title=&quot;Young men in Morocco awaiting a ride to their agricultural jobs.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New Approach to Market Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address Africa’s growing population as well as market needs in the European Neighbourhood, the EU recognizes that it needs to look beyond traditional development grants. The EIP represents a new approach—an overarching framework that seeks to bring together international financial institutions, donor agencies, and the private sector in a coherent market systems strategy. The strategy will be driven by demand for reduced-risk financing and investing to fill growing demand in fragile states. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EIP comprises three pillars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobilizing Investments&lt;/strong&gt;—the guarantee and blended-finance operations will de-risk investments and attract public and private investors;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Providing Technical Assistance&lt;/strong&gt;—support to develop new investment projects and local investment climate reform projects; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving Investment Climate&lt;/strong&gt;—engaging with the private sector and improving policies around local business environments should lead to a favourable and conducive investment climate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since early 2017, DAI has assisted the European Commission’s International Development Cooperation Directorate through the TPSD/E Facility, which delivers thematic support, policy advice, knowledge management, and communications expertise on issues related to trade and private sector development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To support the EU Delegations in the implementation of this new investment-focused approach, the TPSD/E Facility will assist in identifying country-specific opportunities for business reform. EU Delegations may request Investment Climate Reform diagnostics toolkits and related training, which will initially address five investment windows: access to finance, renewable energy, agribusiness, smart cities, and digitalisation. To promote the availability of funds and enhance awareness of the EIP, the TPSD/E team have created an online learning module, “EIP in Practice,” on the EU’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://europa.eu/capacity4dev/&quot;&gt;Capacity4Dev platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EIP-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EIP-2&quot; title=&quot;mPesa branchless banking started in 2007 in Kenya and Tanzania and has expanded abroad.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TPSD/E facility will also advise EU Delegations on how best to implement the EIP. For example, it will help Delegations identify investment opportunities that support small businesses and sole proprietors, which provide most of the jobs in Africa yet often have no access to financing to grow their operations. The EIP is the EU’s first investment plan outside Europe to tackle investment constraints on such a wide scale. With its focus on investment and guarantees, the EIP can target sectors conducive to development—such as infrastructure, energy, water, and information technology—and support specific Sustainable Development Goals, such as jobs for women and youth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this type of private-sector engagement may be new to many EU Delegation staff, the TPSD/E team will support public-private structured dialogue within the context of investment climate reform. The team has already mapped out the major business intermediary organisations in 49 African countries. This support and mapping will assist both local companies seeking new market linkages and European companies seeking to enter new and emerging markets. Delegations will also help advocate for business and investment reform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EIP-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EIP-5&quot; title=&quot;Sub-Saharan Africa is becoming a key sourcing destination for global apparel buyers. This includes Kenyan apparel producer UAL, which has received assistance from the USAID East Africa Trade and Investment Hub, implemented by DAI.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Providing One-Stop Shop Services&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EIP Secretariat in Brussels will provide one-stop shop services to those seeking to invest in sub-Saharan Africa and in the Eastern and Southern European Neighbourhoods, especially the fragile states. In bolstering small and growing businesses in these countries, the aim is to stimulate additional investment by the EU, local businesses, and financial institutions as part of an integrated financial value chain. DAI looks forward to playing an instrumental role in supporting the implementation of the EIP.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Q&amp;A with DAI’s Susan Scribner: Preparedness, Response, and Global Health Security</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-with-dais-susan-scribner-about-preparedness-response-and-global-health-security</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2017 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/qa-with-dais-susan-scribner-about-preparedness-response-and-global-health-security</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pandemics begin with a single case but don’t stay that way: since 2000, avian influenza has killed 440 people in 14 countries, Ebola more than 11,000 people in 10 countries, and severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) 770 people in 37 countries. The first deaths were reported locally in Hong Kong (1997), Guinea (2013), and China (2002), respectively. HIV/AIDS was first contracted by a human from a primate in West Africa—since 1981, AIDS has killed 35 million people, including 675,000 in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These crises galvanized the U.S. government to enact programs to help at-risk countries contain emerging diseases, and these programs are working. For example, programs funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and implemented by DAI, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-stamping-out-pandemic-and-avian-influenza-stop-ai&quot;&gt;STOP AI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-respond&quot;&gt;RESPOND&lt;/a&gt; programs, were credited with limiting the spread of avian influenza and substantially strengthening outbreak response capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, USAID doubled down on this work in global health security, launching the Emerging Pandemic Threats-2 suite of programs. The EPT-2 suite includes the DAI-led &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-preparedness-and-response-pr&quot;&gt;Preparedness &amp;amp; Response (P&amp;amp;R)&lt;/a&gt; program team, working in target countries to strengthen national systems in the prevention, detection, and response to emerging pandemic threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project uses the One Health approach—the combined efforts of the human health, animal health, and environmental sectors—to reduce time to detection and confirmation of public health events. Developments asked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/susan-scribner&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DAI’s Susan Scribner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, below, P&amp;amp;R’s Project Director and Vice President of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/health&quot;&gt;DAI Global Health&lt;/a&gt;, about this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-pic-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-pic-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AIDS, Ebola, others … what causes a pandemic-threat disease and what factors cause them to spread?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were zoonotic diseases—diseases that happen when a pathogen from an animal spreads to humans. Increasingly, we’re finding human intrusion into animal ecosystems, increased animal-based food production, growing international trade, and expanding international travel have increased the opportunity for “spillover” into human populations. There are 7.5 billion people on this planet, with increasing global travel. Human beings are more mobile than ever—which means pathogens are, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P&amp;amp;R works with international partners to help governments in 15 countries—why were these countries targeted for USAID investment preventing, detecting, responding to, and containing emerging pandemic threats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are countries at high risk. They have a history of disease outbreaks, warm climates, and growing human populations that have been encroaching on wildlife areas. Some countries may also lack a health-systems infrastructure, which makes them more vulnerable to these threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was the tipping point that prompted this response—both the global health security effort and the Preparedness &amp;amp; Response program in particular?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The international community has spent an enormous amount of time and money over the years reacting to HIV, Ebola virus disease, and avian influenza, to name a few. When it comes to health security, loss of lives, and economic and societal disruption, an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot afford to just respond to pandemic threats anymore; we need to be proactive about preventing them. That means working to improve country government systems and planning for preparedness and response, which is where P&amp;amp;R sits. By focusing on systems and planning, the P&amp;amp;R program helps bridge the gap between traditional health-systems strengthening activities and specific global health security needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P&amp;amp;R Target Countries:&lt;/strong&gt; Bangladesh, Cameroon, Cote D&amp;#39; Ivoire, Ethiopia, Guinea, Indonesia, Kenya, Laos, Liberia, Mali, Sierra Leone, Tanzania, Thailand, Uganda, Vietnam.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does the &lt;a href=&quot;http://preparednessandresponse.org/&quot;&gt;P&amp;amp;R project&lt;/a&gt; strengthen systems and planning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project uses the One Health approach to ensure that national systems and plans bring the right resources to the table. That means medical doctors working with veterinarians, local health care providers working with emergency responders, the private sector working with the public sector. The multisectoral coordination mechanism that makes this possible is what we call a One Health platform, which we are developing in each of the 15 countries where we work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A One Health platform coordinates implementation of a variety of prevention, detection, and response activities to pandemic threats for the country government—everything from prioritizing zoonotic diseases or drafting a One Health strategy with the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, to integrating disease surveillance, to multisectoral planning and rapid response training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P&amp;amp;R helps launch and strengthen One Health platforms. We also work with established platforms, local stakeholders, and multilateral partners to help them implement preparedness and response activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-4-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-4-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Ebola countries—Liberia and Sierra Leone, where 8,700 people died—recently “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontpageafricaonline.com/index.php/health/5758-liberia-partners-institutionalize-one-health-approach-in-liberia&quot;&gt;launched&lt;/a&gt;” their One Health platforms. What does that mean in practical terms?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means the country is committed to supporting the One Health approach and addressing global health security, and they’ve put the systems and people in place to do it. But formalizing their One Health platforms is just the first step. These countries need to review and test their plans and the specific protocols and operating procedures that outline how the human, animal, and environmental health sectors will work together in different scenarios. They need to strengthen the relevant workforce, surveillance systems, and laboratory capacity to prevent, detect, and respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been great examples of the power of the One Health platforms already, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://bdnews24.com/health/2017/09/17/one-health-concept-important-for-bangladesh-who-representative&quot;&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/a&gt;’s and Uganda’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/globalhealth/healthprotection/fieldupdates/summer-2017/uganda-avian-influenza.html&quot;&gt;avian influenza responses&lt;/a&gt; and Uganda’s recent Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever response. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did the Ebola outbreak of 2014—the same year P&amp;amp;R was launched—teach us anything?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it taught us the importance of building a strong preparedness and response infrastructure during “peace time,” before the next outbreak strikes. It also highlighted the need to broaden the One Health community to include stakeholders in immigration, security, education, commerce, and the private sector—which can be a particularly important partner for mobilizing resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are typical challenges to creating One Health platforms?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many countries, health ministries are stronger and better resourced than the other sectors. This inequity extends beyond funding—animal health and environment sectors also tend to have weaker surveillance data and human resource capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working with the platforms to address some of these limitations, by improving the practice of One Health—coordinating advocacy, resource mobilization, strategy, planning, training, data sharing, surveillance, and rapid response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Scribner-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Scribner-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are next steps for P&amp;amp;R—and for global health security—in continuing to improve prevention, detection, and response?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our project and the One Health platforms we support move closer to accomplishing their planning and strategy objectives, training and guidance will take on a larger role in effective implementation. So we are looking at developing planning guidance for provincial and district implementation, as we’ve done in Indonesia. Recently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/one-health-workforce/one-health-central-and-eastern-africa-network-officially-launched-in-cameroon-29eec092a774&quot;&gt;in Cameroon&lt;/a&gt;, we supported platform training for district-level emergency operations centers; we have also trained Rapid Response Teams for the West African Health Organization (WAHO) at the regional level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because so many improvements will need to be made at the subnational level, it is essential to build a network of One Health technical specialists. This is the network of doctors, epidemiologists, public health specialists, veterinarians, and environmental experts that DAI has spent the past 20 years developing, not just on P&amp;amp;R but also on the Stop AI and RESPOND projects before it, and several earlier bilateral projects in Indonesia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, P&amp;amp;R has also spent significant time in defining and simplifying technical guidance to the One Health approach. Our upcoming project technical guide includes a series of activity toolkits—toolkits the project is developing with feedback from both international and country government partners—that will make it easier for country platforms to implement these activities themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the global health security community has made so much progress in the past 10 years. But we are going to have to continue to do more to leverage the resources we have from both international and country government partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sourcing the Wadi: How Palestinian Workers Are Filling Niche Needs in Israel’s IT Sector</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/sourcing-the-wadi-training-palestinian-workers-to-fill-niche-need-in-israel-it</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 18:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/sourcing-the-wadi-training-palestinian-workers-to-fill-niche-need-in-israel-it</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Middle East hosts one of the fastest-growing high-tech industries in the world: Israel’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2017/05/15/israels-high-tech-sector-is-thriving-and-now-china-wants-in-on-the-action.html&quot;&gt;Silicon Wadi&lt;/a&gt;. But the very speed of this growth means Israel’s tech sector also faces a shortage of skilled engineers. To deal with this shortage, Israel has turned largely to Eastern Europe as a source for IT workers. Though there is plenty of talent in Eastern Europe, the time difference is not ideal for collaborating and that talent is becoming costlier as global demand increases. This combination of circumstances means opportunities for Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/palestinian-market-development-programme-pmdp&quot;&gt;Palestinian Market Development Programme (PMDP)&lt;/a&gt; has seized upon this need by shifting Silicon Wadi’s sourcing focus close to home—to Palestinian IT firms. Funded by the U.K. Department for International Development and the European Commission, and in partnership with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portlandtrust.org/&quot;&gt;Portland Trust&lt;/a&gt;, PMDP identified the verification of software for microchips—or design verification—as a niche area of demand that fits wells with emerging Palestinian service capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Mira-Nasser-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Mira-Nasser-3&quot; title=&quot;The software engineer team at ProGineer in Ramallah that won a subcontract to provide design verification.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on business and workforce development, PMDP&amp;rsquo;s approach is beginning to pay off. A team of five software engineers at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.progineer.net/&quot;&gt;ProGineer&lt;/a&gt; in Ramallah recently won a subcontract to provide design verification for a multinational firm. The competitive award is a breakthrough for the Palestinian IT sector and showcases its ability to provide services to international clients. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is Design Verification?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global advances in computer hardware have forced semiconductor design to become more sophisticated. Higher-performing microchips utilize increasingly complex semiconductor designs, and this has spawned an entire industry specializing in design testing to increase performance and production efficiency. Israel—home to companies such as Intel, Cadence, Mellannox—is a world leader in design verification technology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About Palestinian Market Development Programme (PMDP)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PMDP improves market systems and competitiveness in the Palestinian private sector through technical assistance and matching grants. It addresses market system failures in specific sectors through market analysis and facilitation, and strengthens trade and investment linkages in collaboration with key commercial representatives. In the West Bank, the program has assisted more than 360 businesses (including 98 women-owned) with targeted grants, developing or enhancing more than 460 new products while helping nearly 200 businesses and increasing sales by £33 million. In Gaza, PMDP has assisted more than 260 businesses and helped develop or enhance 130 new products, increasing sales by £55.7 million and creating more than 1,600 jobs.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why Choose Palestinian Companies?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A closer look at the market opportunity revealed certain factors advantageous to Palestinian firms, including physical proximity to clients in Tel Aviv and Jerusalem (allowing for same time-zone operation and local travel), lower costs than in Israel, and similar costs to Eastern Europe. While the market opportunity was clear, the Palestinian market  remained undertested for design and verification services; prior to this engagement, only one service contract was being implemented by a Palestinian IT firm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian IT firms have two factors working against them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weak links and lack of awareness of business opportunities with multinational companies in the region; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limited local opportunities to gain experience and professional training in design verification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----Mira-Nasser-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----Mira-Nasser-2&quot; title=&quot;Design-verification training under the Palestinian Market Development Programme included technical and practical components.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Palestinian value proposition was presented to Israel-based multinational companies, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cadence.com/&quot;&gt;Cadence&lt;/a&gt;, a provider of system design tools and software, expressed strong interest. Based upon this reaction, PMDP and The Portland Trust teams designed a three-stage intervention—applying DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/new-primer-market-systems-development-available&quot;&gt;principles of market systems development&lt;/a&gt;—aimed at stimulating commercial transactions between Cadence and Palestinian providers: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testing the waters:&lt;/strong&gt; Portland Trust asked Cadence to outline its service requirements and agree to a three-month “mock project” to test Palestinian capabilities. Four local Palestinian firms—Exalt, Progineer, Unit One, Appstown—put together teams of five members each to complete the test project. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training time:&lt;/strong&gt; A one-month, in-classroom training in system-design skills and testing software was delivered by a leading provider, Variest. The four Palestinian companies nominated 18 staff members to be trained. Feedback from the training was encouraging, with most of the participants scoring well on the end-of-course exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mock projects:&lt;/strong&gt; Following evaluation of the training, Cadence invited two teams to enroll in mock projects involving a live design-verification challenge. Eleven engineers from two shortlisted teams participated in the projects remotely over three months, with weekly visits to the Cadence campus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Deal is Struck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impressed by the mock project performance, Cadence extended its agreement to Progineer, creating five high-quality, full-time jobs—one team leader and four junior programmers—in Ramallah. This purely commercial engagement is a breakthrough for the Palestinian IT outsourcing industry. It proves the business value that Palestinian service providers can deliver to international clients, and showcases a model for how IT outsourcing can grow through effective structuring of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Mira-Nasser-IT-PMDP-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Mira-Nasser-IT-PMDP-1&quot; title=&quot;Group photo of the design-verification trainees under the Palestinian Market Development Programme.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable growth of the design-verification service line hinges upon Progineer successfully delivering results to Cadence and expanding to serve additional clients. Meanwhile, the other Palestinian firms—Exalt, Unit One, and Appstown—also have potential to tap market opportunities after taking design-verification training. “As awareness of Palestinian design-verification capabilities grows, there will be more interest from buyers, and local business development capabilities will grow stronger,” said PMDP Team Leader Maher Hamdan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PMDP plans to nuture this interest by supporting the growth of existing services, fostering additional business connections, and making design-verification training locally available. The team also plans to work with Palestinian universities to introduce design-verification courses to the IT curricula to further stimulate a generation of marketable IT employees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning Restrictive Social Norms in the Middle East into Job Opportunities for Women</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/turning-social-norms-in-the-middle-east-into-job-opportunities-for-women</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 10:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/turning-social-norms-in-the-middle-east-into-job-opportunities-for-women</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When deep-rooted social norms appear to limit the roles of women, one of the best tactics we can take in development assistance is to look for opportunities to turn those norms to women&amp;rsquo;s advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent example is in the Middle East, where our U.K. Department for International Development-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-egypt-and-palestine-arab-women-enterprise-fund&quot;&gt;Arab Women’s Enterprise Fund&lt;/a&gt; (AWEF) is assisting female-led value chains. In Palestine, AWEF is working with female sheep herders in rural areas to train these women as paraveterinary workers. A paravet functions like a veterinary assistant, nurse, or animal technician by providing basic but important treatment and testing for herds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestine has approximately 30,000 sheep herds, with an estimated 25,000 women playing active roles in their operation, especially among small herds of 35 or fewer animals. But AWEF’s analysis shows that the women-led herds suffer close to 30 percent productivity loss due to poor vaccinations and inadequate animal health care. Because most veterinarians are male, and gender mixing is discouraged, female herders cannot partake in veterinary services provided by men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_0039.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_0039&quot; title=&quot;A female paravet tending to her herd in Palestine.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Training a Cadre of Female Paravets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seizing the opportunity inherent in this restricted market, AWEF and its partners are training a cadre of 20 female paravets to provide much-needed services. These services improve the health of female-led herds as well as the incomes of the herders. Additionally, the female paravets are gaining the respect of their communities, earning more money for their families, and acting as role models for other women. By interacting directly with female paravets, Palestine’s women herders are learning about animal health care and improving their skills, instead of relying on their husbands or other men in their families who are too often ill-informed on herd health needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, women rarely held authority to make decisions around this family business. Social norms constrained their interactions with veterinarians, traders, and the male-dominant herding community. But as women paravets increase their services, it is anticipated that female herders will assume a greater sense of ownership and commitment to their traditionally unpaid work. Eventually, female herders will increase their capacity to manage herds and improve women’s overall role in livestock management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men in these communities will also benefit because female paravets’ services will add to household incomes while reducing or eliminating the expense of seeking assistance from veterinarians, whose clinics are often located far away from small villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AWEF Disadvantaged Assessment Tool&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWEF is the only market systems development project in the region with women’s economic empowerment as its core objective. The AWEF team developed and is now rolling out a gender-sensitive poverty mapping tool called the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.seepnetwork.org/empowerment-forward-poverty-measurement--real-time-learning-from-the-arab-women---s-enterprise-fund---s-disadvantage-assessment-resources-1778.php&quot;&gt;Disadvantaged Assessment&lt;/a&gt;, designed to identify areas in market systems where women’s disadvantages hinder their ability to find jobs or develop livelihoods. While the tool has yet to be fully implemented, its early findings in Palestine reveal that women are disadvantaged due to their high amount of time spent performing unpaid work, lack of decision-making authority around mobility, poor economic standing, and exposure to physical violence. In the coming months, the AWEF team will begin performing Disadvantaged Assessments on target locales and sectors.&lt;/aside&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Extending Herd-Care Services in Afghanistan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training women as paravets is also bearing fruit in other DAI-led projects. The U.S. Agency for International Development-funded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-regional-agricultural-development-program-radp-north&quot;&gt;Regional Agricultural Development Program-North&lt;/a&gt; (RADP-North), for example, trained 15 paravets (10 men, five women) in 2016, filling an important need for livestock owners. Trainees were equipped with tools and equipment to establish veterinary field units in the communities they now serve. RADP-North is on schedule to train another 20 paravets through 2017. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of RADP-North’s female trainees, Fatima, provides veterinary services to more than 500 farmers in 12 surrounding villages—encompassing more than 2,000 animals—while earning AFN 600 to 800 per day. “Recently, a woman called me and said that she had a newborn calf that was sick,” Fatima said. “I traveled to the area, checked the calf, and found that the calf was highly dehydrated due to acute diarrhea. The woman was so concerned about losing the calf, but I medicated the calf by injecting some vitamins, and within an hour, the calf began to improve. The woman was so happy and thanked me for saving her calf.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/IMG_8165.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_8165&quot; title=&quot;Aya Mletat started her sheep farm when she was just 20.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Earning Acceptance Among Men&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Palestine, Aya Mletat, a 30-year-old mother of two, established her own sheep farm at age 20. Today, Mletat trains and mentors both male and female herders in her community. According to Mletat, men who refused to deal with her at first have now accepted her consultations after seeing her paraveterinary skills in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWEF is finding opportunities within a culture of “constraints” in other Middle Eastern countries. In Jordan, AWEF is training women who run dairy-processing outfits to meet the standards required for local regulatory certification of their dried yogurt. This training helps these female-led small businesses to improve the quality of their products and increase sales in male-dominated markets. In Egypt, AWEF is teaching large businesses in the garment and citrus sectors to recruit women for positions—including senior and management roles—where the work and interactions would be culturally permissable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/nandi-hall&quot;&gt;Nandi Hall&lt;/a&gt;, the AWEF project director, said the team’s underlying goal is to identify social norms that open windows of opportunities for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“AWEF believes that social norms can shift when people begin to experience the economic benefits of new behaviours,” Hall said. “We hope to provide the opportunity for other women in traditional roles to be more encouraged to explore new roles by viewing social norms in a new light.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helping Eastern Partnership Countries Meet Their Commitments to Address Climate Change</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/helping-eastern-partnership-countries-meet-their-voluntary-commitments-to-reduce-emissions-address-climate-change</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2017 14:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/helping-eastern-partnership-countries-meet-their-voluntary-commitments-to-reduce-emissions-address-climate-change</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The economies of Eastern Europe have grown in recent decades largely on the backs of heavy industry, mechanisation, and agriculture. In many countries, this has led to significant greenhouse gas emissions, a reliance on inefficient technologies, and a policy environment that did not support green growth. As part of their commitments to global climate change agreements, signatory countries pledged to reduce emissions. After committing to cleaner ways, however, these countries faced a common challenge: where to start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the six countries of the European Union’s Eastern Partnership now has a plan. Under Clima East, a 4½-year programme funded by the European Commission and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/russian-federation-clima-east-support-climate-change-mitigation-and-adaptation&quot;&gt;implemented by DAI&lt;/a&gt;, the countries—Armenia, Azerbaijan, Belarus, Georgia, Moldova, and Ukraine—assessed how to best reduce emissions and adapt their industries, agriculture, and households to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, this planning was well timed. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.climaeast.eu/&quot;&gt;Clima East&lt;/a&gt; originally launched in 2012 to continue support of the Kyoto climate agreements from 15 years earlier. But the Clima East team pivoted when the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) announced that participants of the 2016 Paris Conference would need to draft and submit, in advance, their Intended Nationally Determined Contributions (INDCs). The team was well placed to support the development of these INDCs and ensure they were technically sound and suitably ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-2&quot; title=&quot;In Azerbaijan, Clima East introduced techniques that reduce emissions of carbon and incentivize farmers to control animal numbers for better soil conditions and biodiversity. Credit: Clima East.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the Eastern Partnership nations are prepared to address and, over time, meet their Paris commitments to consume less energy, reduce emissions, and increase use of energy from renewable sources. They are also prepared to put strategies in place to support adaptation to a changing climate across a range of core economic sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clima East’s holistic approach to supporting these partner nations produced an array of results for each country. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Armenia&lt;/strong&gt;, the country’s Environmental Project Implementation Unit was accredited to access and implement funding from a major source—the global Adaptation Fund.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Azerbaijan&lt;/strong&gt;, gaps in the country’s land use, land-use change, and forestry inventory were identified and recommendations made on steps to improve local stakeholders’ capacities in this key area of greenhouse gas reporting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Belarus&lt;/strong&gt;, more than 200 people across 20 ministries, agencies, and other organisations were engaged and informed about international climate adaptation and mitigation best practices, including for planning agriculture adaptation and for obligations and opportunities under the Paris Agreement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Georgia&lt;/strong&gt;, roadmaps were produced to align with EU legislation in fluorinated gases, such as hydrofluorocarbons, and other ozone-depleting substances.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Moldova&lt;/strong&gt;, civil society organisations were engaged in the crucial policy processes under way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;Ukraine&lt;/strong&gt;, backlogged requests for improvements made by UNFCCC reviewers were addressed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brochure describing Clima East&amp;rsquo;s broader results is available here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1067656943.n159491.test.prositehosting.co.uk/wp-content-sec/uploads/2013/08/Clima-East-Final-Brochure-2017-PDF.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Supporting Preparations to Honor Commitments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe and its eastern neighbors are increasingly affected by rising global temperatures related to climate change. The World Bank, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://documents.worldbank.org/curated/en/676601468249642651/pdf/761840PUB0EPI00LIC00pubdate03015013.pdf&quot;&gt;forecasts&lt;/a&gt; fluctuations in crop growing conditions by 2050 that will be especially difficult for small, poorer farms in the region to address. More frequent, more severe floods, droughts, and heatwaves are expected to affect industry, agriculture, and, ultimately, public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern Partnership nations acknowledged their increasing emissions of greenhouse gases in signing the Paris Agreement and resolved to significantly reduce their own emissions from 2020 forward. Before they signed the agreement, Clima East assisted Eastern Partnership countries in developing their INDCs. Equipped with these feasible goals, policy makers set out to develop plans on where and how their country could cut emissions, but the region’s climate scientists and lawmakers lacked the data and analytical tools needed to create accurate models of how to meet their commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clima East team and their ministerial counterparts analyzed leading emitters of greenhouse gases and identified ways to reduce emissions in sectors such as energy, agriculture, forestry, transport, waste, construction, and manufacturing. In Azerbaijan, for example, the counterparts achieved consensus on projections and created scenarios covering industrial processes, urban planning, and reforestation of degraded land. As a result, the government of Azerbaijan was able to submit its INDC ahead of Paris and set a target to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 65 percent from the country’s 1990 level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, policy makers in Belarus identified the need for specialized advice, and with Clima East&amp;rsquo;s assistance they were able to examine data and create a model that revealed untapped options for reducing greenhouse gases. With these new insights, Belarus increased its INDC emission-reduction goal from 25 percent to 28 percent of 1990 levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-4&quot; title=&quot;Regional workshop in Baku, Azerbaijan, about modelling tools for vulnerability assessments in the water and agriculture sectors. Credit: Clima East.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Using Data to Plan for Change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major long-term changes in temperatures and rainfall will affect which crops and varieties grow best and where. Clima East experts worked with local counterparts to assess and adapt to the impacts of climate change on their country’s agriculture sectors. These climate-smart agriculture approaches adapt farming and markets to anticipated changes. If ministries can better understand and plan for the implementation of climate-smart policies, farmers and others associated with agriculture value chains—including consumers—will benefit from increased security in food and livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clima East team knew that training specialists from partner countries was critical to promoting the long-term use of climate data in guiding policy. Clima East conducted regional events where climate specialists shared challenges and solutions in preparing their countries’ INDCs. These specialists also traveled to Germany and Poland to learn how these countries operate effective measuring and reporting mechanisms to track emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clima East supported specialists across the region to create complex emissions models and forecast impacts. For example, a 2014 workshop convened specialists from the six partner countries to train on an emissions modelling tool called Long-Range Energy Alternatives Planning. Participants received national data starter packs to begin emission assessments, which some countries immediately put to use in developing their INDCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Clima-East-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Clima-East-3&quot; title=&quot;Strategy roundtable in Belarus to adapt agriculture to climate change, organized and supported by Belarus&amp;#39; Ministry of Natural Resources and Environmental Protection. Credit: Clima East.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Readily Replicable Programme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In five years, Clima East engaged 40 national government institutions and hosted more than 50 groups from civil society, academia, the private sector, and local government. These efforts collectively prepared six Eastern Partnership countries to develop and implement INDC emission-reduction plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme is readily replicable to other countries and regions. One hundred and sixty countries have ratified the Paris Agreement and another 35 are in the process of doing so. Clima East has shown that if their policy makers and climate specialists are brought together and equipped with the right tools and information, they, too, can work out a path toward green growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Messe Frankfurt’s Purchase of Source Africa Trade Show Exemplifies the Potential of Market Systems Development</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/messe-frankfurts-purchase-of-source-africa-trade-show-exemplifies-the-potential-of-market-systems-development</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 20:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/messe-frankfurts-purchase-of-source-africa-trade-show-exemplifies-the-potential-of-market-systems-development</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, DAI began implementing the value chain portion of Southern Africa Trade Hub (SATH), a project funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID). SATH&amp;rsquo;s goal was to promote economic growth by fostering intraregional trade between select member states of the Southern African Development Community (SADC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During DAI’s initial work planning session, Mark Bennett, our textiles and garments specialist, was tasked with commercializing a business-to-business (B2B) trade event that previous USAID projects had been funding to the tune of about $150,000 per year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI&amp;rsquo;s value chain team found that a good deal of business was being transacted at these B2B events, so why should USAID continue to foot the bill by annually engaging a consultant to pull the event together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was there a better way to ensure that trade in textiles and apparels was conducted on a commercially sustained basis, driven by the industry itself, rather than relying on donors like USAID to make it happen? DAI had previously commercialized donor-driven business matchmaking activities using private operators in Serbia and South Africa, so we knew it could be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Source-Africa-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Source-Africa-2&quot; title=&quot;The 2017 Source Africa trade show featured 151 exhibitors from 17 countries as well as five fashion shows. Credit: Source Africa&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took nine months, but DAI found a South African trade show company, LTE, and convinced its leaders that this event in their own country could be good business. It then took another six months to get all parties to agree to a cooperation framework going forward. Finally, Bennett and value chain component lead Don Greenberg, with support from SATH’s leadership, mobilized funding support to complement LTE’s investment, and together the parties established the Source Africa trade show. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Source Africa, organized by LTE with some support from SATH, took place in 2013 in Cape Town, now the home of the show every year. In its first year, Source Africa attracted about 100 exhibitors; by 2016, LTE sold 183 booths to exhibitors from 14 countries, with about 1,500 people attending the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Why%20Trade%20Shows%20May%202015.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Source-Africa-graphic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Source-Africa-graphic&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each show, LTE incurs most of the risk—paying for the venue, engaging the stand builders, hiring staff, designing logos and web sites, and so on. While development-oriented donors have continued to support Source Africa—including the USAID-funded, DAI-led &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa&lt;/a&gt; trade and investment hubs—direct donor support of LTE has fallen to extremely low levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having built up a nice profitable business creating linkages across Southern and Eastern Africa’s textile and garment industry, LTE helped achieve the purpose of our various trade hubs, but without USAID in the middle—a clear case of a donor working its way out of a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Source-Africa-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Source-Africa-1&quot; title=&quot;Nearly 1,400 attendees from 16 countries came to the 2017 Source Africa trade show. Credit: Source Africa&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month, the now highly successful Source Africa trade show was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fin24.com/Economy/messe-frankfurt-ready-to-take-sa-clothing-expos-to-next-level-20170908&quot;&gt;sold&lt;/a&gt; to Germany&amp;rsquo;s Messe Frankfurt group, the third-largest trade show organizer in the world. Messe Frankfurt runs 134 trade fairs and exhibitions worldwide. Approximately 90,000 exhibitors and 3.5 million visitors attend its exhibitions each year. Under Messe’s umbrella, Source Africa will surely soar to even greater heights. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breakthroughs in trade require time, effort, and persistence—in any region of the world—but the result for developing nations is sustainable, inclusive economic growth that creates jobs and new wealth. The privatizing of Source Africa is one such breakthrough. It’s the kind of success—building local capacity to commercially fill market gaps by providing information and linking traders—that the global development community should be talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
