<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>DAI Online Publications</title>
    <link>http://dai-global-developments.com</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 21:37:30 -0000</pubDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demand for Private Capital Draws USAID Units to INVEST Program</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/demand-for-private-capital-draws-usaid-units-to-invest-program</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 13:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/demand-for-private-capital-draws-usaid-units-to-invest-program</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) units around the world are increasingly asking for specialized support to mobilize private capital—requests now being met by the agency’s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-the-invest-project&quot;&gt;INVEST&lt;/a&gt; program. In less than one year, USAID missions, bureaus, and other operating units have hired the INVEST team to support 17 initiatives to develop market opportunities. These initiatives—to address demand for energy, food, health care, water, and other global needs—are under way or already completed in Afghanistan, Asia, Haiti, India, and North and Sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combined commitments of $37 million by USAID units to pursue these initiatives represent 40 percent of the INVEST goal set by USAID. A two-year project with three option years, INVEST’s success has already spurred USAID to green-light a third year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based in Washington, D.C., the INVEST team facilitates the expertise in finance and investment, technical subjects, and local knowledge required to generate investment pipelines and mobilize investment capital. INVEST orchestrates a network of specialists—more than 130 firms so far—that fill various niches to help USAID explore these opportunities. This network includes strategy advisory firms such as Tideline and Dalberg, transaction advisory firms including CrossBoundary and Open Capital Advisors, and innovative finance firms such as Kois Invest and Third Sector. These and other partners provide the appropriate mix of financial rigor and technical specialization required to tailor assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“[USAID is] embracing the ingenuity and the entrepreneurship that private enterprise offers and harnessing the efficiencies and effectiveness that private-sector competition and market forces can unlock. And this is something private enterprise is eager to do alongside us.”&lt;strong&gt;—USAID Administrator Mark Green&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreign.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/062018_Green_Testimony.pdf&quot;&gt;June 20, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent “buy-ins” by USAID units for market assessments and pipeline development, design and structuring support, and transaction advisors exemplify the early demand for INVEST’s services. They include initiatives to: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Facilitate trade between Afghanistan and India;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a first-of-its-kind investment mobilization platform in Haiti for sectors such as agriculture, housing, sanitation, and water;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze capital opportunities that benefit women in Ghana, Kenya, Nigeria, Senegal, and South Africa (USAID’s Office of Gender Equality and Women’s Empowerment); and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accelerate the solar off-grid energy marketplace in Uganda, building on the accomplishments of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-center-development-innovation-professional-management-services&quot;&gt;Center for Development Innovation&lt;/a&gt; project under the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scalingoffgrid.org/&quot;&gt;Scaling Off-Grid Energy Grand Challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These and other USAID investments reflect &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/blended-finance-in-actionhow-usaid-leveraged-100-million-in-east-africa/&quot;&gt;growing determination&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/eu-launches-26-billion-fund-to-attract-investment-in-the-european-neighbourhood-and-africas-fragile-states/&quot;&gt;donor community&lt;/a&gt; to enhance development impact by means of “blended finance”—blending private capital with donor-funded local expertise and risk-mitigation measures. The goal is to achieve development objectives by creating profitable partnerships while advancing countries on their journeys to self-reliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----INVEST-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----INVEST-2&quot; title=&quot;The USAID East Africa Trade and Investment Hub has facilitated $59 million in private sector investments in sectors such as food warehousing and logistics.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bull Market for Global Needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in mid-2017, INVEST has grown from a lean start-up to managing a growing portfolio of partners and activities. As manager of the INVEST network platform, DAI convenes and facilitates buy-ins by helping USAID units refine their “ask,” identify and engage the appropriate advisors through competitive procurements, and support implementation, including monitoring, evaluation, learning, and thought leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;INVEST is designed to operate in locales that have less-than-ideal investment climates yet have growing populations that require products and services. In addition to the initiatives cited above, the INVEST team is pursuing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health-Focused Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID missions in India, Liberia, and Tanzania worked with INVEST to deploy an investment roadmap and guidance tool to address high-priority health objectives in areas such as community and maternal health, nutrition, and tuberculosis. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The USAID Global Health Center for Innovation and Impact engaged INVEST to assess and recommend financial models for tackling cholera in Haiti.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Investment Platforms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/India engaged INVEST to assess the energy, health, tuberculosis, and WASH sectors and design a new, blended finance-focused funding vehicle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID’s Office of Private Capital and Microenterprise, Bureau for Food Security, and USAID/Tunisia have partnered to better understand and leverage the strategic corporate investment trend, including: favorable models and structures in agriculture, energy, and water; appropriate support for these models; structures to attract investors and ensure replicability and additionality; and suitable corporate investment and partnership opportunities already in existence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Initiatives in Energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/Haiti and the Government of Haiti are pursuing a public-private partnership for Caracol Power Utility’s operations, maintenance, and management; INVEST is providing transaction advice, including due diligence and transaction structuring, transaction implementation, and bidding. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/Kenya and Power Africa are working with INVEST to help household solar systems and off-grid companies attract investment and expand connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agricultural Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID/Democratic Republic of the Congo engaged INVEST to explore opportunities and constraints associated with blended finance and the approaches and tools available to support investment in agricultural value chains and responsible mining in Eastern Congo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training and Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;USAID’s Office of Private Capital and Microenterprise and Center for Transformational Partnerships are developing a learning strategy on private sector engagement to deepen USAID’s capacity in market-based solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----INVEST%203Finette-QA-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----INVEST 3Finette-QA-1&quot; title=&quot;Digital health products are among those that the INVEST team are helping USAID units to explore.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Developed for Business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Capitalizing on unexplored economic opportunities in developing countries &lt;em&gt;requires partners&lt;/em&gt;—ones with local knowledge, financial resources, and entrepreneurial spirit, just for starters. The co-creation team that conceived INVEST in 2017 sought a long-term solution that will enable USAID to quickly engage new partners and mobilize private capital. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses and investors seek capital supply, investment-ready projects, access to affordable and appropriate risk-mitigation instruments, and reasonable firm-level transaction costs. Locally, however, capital mobilization can be inhibited by a lack of skills among and imperfect information from financial intermediaries and advisors, immature market conditions, and lack of connective tissue among market actors, even where demand is strong for necessities such as energy, food, health care, and water, not to mention the jobs these sectors create. Meeting these demands can increase economic activity at scale and deliver the benefits that come with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it enters year two, INVEST is testing and scaling up approaches to blended finance, creating value for its USAID clients while using inclusive procurement and contracting mechanisms adapted for private sector partners. Meanwhile, INVEST’s Washington-based team is aggregating the experts, experiences, data, and best practices on blended finance that were previously scattered around the world. Together, these successes and activities are positioning USAID for the long term to facilitate the blended finance solutions necessary for sustainable, inclusive economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afghan Women Re-Enter the Economy as Workers, Business Owners</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-women-re-enter-the-economy-as-workers-business-owners</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2018 14:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/afghan-women-re-enter-the-economy-as-workers-business-owners</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Afghanistan transitions toward a market-driven economy and away from one supported by foreign assistance, jobs will inevitably be lost. The Afghan Ministry of Labor, Social Affairs, Martyred, and Disabled predicts that 4 million jobs will be needed over the next five years to replace lost jobs and absorb the rising generation of graduates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demand is increasing for entrepreneurial energy and new thinking to address these market needs, and women are essential to helping fill this void. After three decades of low employment for Afghan women—mostly in the agricultural sector—the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/afghanistan-women-in-the-economy&quot;&gt;Promote: Women in the Economy (WIE)&lt;/a&gt; program is opening doors for women-led enterprises to grow and for women to enter the workforce and launch startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results so far have been encouraging. Since its 2015 launch, WIE has:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Placed almost 7,000 women in internships and apprenticeships, especially in fields such as teaching and healthcare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awarded another 1,300 women scholarships to train in areas such as finance and banking, information technology, and retail sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enabled more than 3,000 of these women to be hired full time. Another 54,000 women have registered for WIE services. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/WIE----Devs-2018-8.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WIE----Devs-2018-8&quot; title=&quot;Ultrasound training in Kabul.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As importantly, more than 300 businesses that are either women-owned or with 30 percent women employment have obtained WIE technical assistance, industry-specific business skills training, and increased access to finance and markets. Of those benefitting from two years of WIE assistance, half reported at least a 40 percent increase in revenue, and 22 percent reported growing from a small to a medium-sized enterprise (more than 50 employees).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“During our first outreach, the goal was to attract 50 applicants; we were shocked when we received 250 inquiries. Facts like this prove the willingness of women toward entrepreneurship; with a little incubation support, women entrepreneurship can be the next boom in our country.”&lt;/strong&gt; — Fahim Didar, founder of Startup Valley, Afghanistan’s first private business incubator for female entrepreneurs, which operates with a grant from WIE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-1&quot; title=&quot;Massoma Husseini, owner of Frogh Event Management, presents findings for the Access to Markets Panel at the Forward Together: National Businesswomen&amp;#39;s Summit.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Business Summit Inspires New Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2018 in Kabul, 140 businesswomen from 21 Afghan provinces convened for the Forward Together: National Business Women’s Summit, organized by WIE. They discussed operational, marketing, and management issues and business environment challenges, including accessing finance and new markets, registering and licensing businesses, managing taxes, developing skills among women in the workforce, packaging products, and improving business services and the business enabling environment for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-3&quot; title=&quot;Dr. Abdullah Abdullah, Chief Executive of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, after speaking at the National Business Women’s Summit.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deputy Ministers from the ministries of Women’s Affairs and Commerce and Industry attended the VIP closing session, where H.E. Dr. Abdullah Abdullah, the Chief Executive of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usaid.gov/afghanistan/news-information/press-releases/Apr-19-2018-USAID-Supports-Afghan-Women-owned-Businesses&quot;&gt;emphasized full government support&lt;/a&gt; for the long-term strategies and reforms needed to assist Afghan businesswomen. The summit yielded a blueprint for action that WIE and others are acting on today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI incorporated participants’ feedback into the final year of WIE programming, which ends in June 2019. One new initiative is the Finance Corps, which will help women-led businesses improve their financial literacy and management, bookkeeping systems, inventory and pricing, investment decisions, and operational efficiency. In addition, WIE is planning a product development service that will teach Afghan MBA graduates, consultants, and service providers to assist women’s businesses in improving product quality, packaging, and regulatory compliance. The service will initially focus on the food processing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/WIE----2018-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WIE----2018-11&quot; title=&quot;MBA Corps assisting commercial garment retailer.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Women Lenders Spark New Lending&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summit highlighted how women who own businesses or are self-employed need better access to financing. One way to tackle this long-term problem is for more women to serve in mid- and senior-level positions in banking, microfinance, and commercial lending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 100 young women in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif have completed WIE’s Microfinance Training Program, 53 of whom have been hired full-time within the microfinance institutions where they apprenticed or at a similar institution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing the number of women in the finance sector, particularly in decision-making and lending roles, will make it more comfortable for other women to seek out financial services, many for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the Microfinance Training Program inspired WIE to design the Women in Commercial Banking activity, which aims to increase the presence and roles of women in banking, first in Kabul and then in other regions. Comprehensive classroom training will be followed by placement in three-month internships in commercial banks, where WIE anticipates 20 percent of these women will be retained as full-time employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----wie-2018-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----wie-2018-2&quot; title=&quot;Access to Finance Matchmaking Roundtable in Mazar-i-Sharif.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WIE’s Access to Finance (A2F) Matchmaking Roundtables have helped businesses learn about borrowing and facilitated mutually beneficial relationships between their representatives and lenders. Through June 2018, WIE had hosted 30 A2F awareness-raising events in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif, leading to 157 small loans, which combined with WIE’s direct-loan facilitation services are worth approximately US$170,000. These loans are typically used to buy the fixed assets needed to help a business grow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small-business lending is catching on—according to the Afghanistan Microfinance Association, a WIE grantee, as of December 2017 more than 77,000 women held active loans with financial institutions in 18 provinces of Afghanistan, representing 39 percent of the microfinance sector.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-7&quot; title=&quot;Regional trade fair in Mazar-i-Sharif.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Promoting Sales and Familiarity Through Trade Fairs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regional trade fairs have proven effective at introducing Afghan women to the private sector and formal economy. These exhibitions have helped WIE clients find customers, suppliers, and contractors and improve their understanding of doing business. Over the past year, WIE organized five Forward Together: Women in Business Regional Trade Fairs—one each in the regional hubs of Kandahar, Jalalabad, Mazar-i-Sharif, Herat, and Kabul. Each event featured 25 to 30 women-owned or -managed businesses, with each representative first mentored in best practices for trade fair business and sales, followed by the actual experience and chance to network with buyers, distributors, and agents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best-performing businesses earned a trip to the First Women Power Expo, held in June 2018 in Kabul. Nearly 100 WIE client businesses participated in the four-day national trade fair, held prior to the Eid holidays, Afghanistan’s busiest retail season. These included enterprises in jewelry/gemstones, garment and handicraft manufacture, dairy and food processing, business service providers, ICT and mobile app providers, and education—sectors where women are particularly active. Many of these businesses were participating in a national trade event for the first time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On-site sales by WIE client businesses topped US$50,000 at the national event and $125,700 for all events combined. More significantly, they also signed 1,500+ wholesale or supply contracts, representing future transactions of approximately US$5.5 million, with another 3,000+ potential contracts in negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----WIE-2018-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----WIE-2018-6&quot; title=&quot;Startup Valley Business Incubator graduating class in May 2018.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Professionalizing Women-Led Startups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any economy, fresh business energy and thinking can forge new avenues for growth. WIE’s entrepreneurial workshops and learning programs have introduced aspiring entrepreneurs to experienced counterparts who have successfully navigated the startup process.
In Kabul, two business incubators—Startup Valley (a WIE grantee) and Founder Institute—have graduated nearly 50 startups, many of which are woman-owned or -led, creating more than 200 jobs. These include startups in mobile applications and other IT solutions, online retail sales, graphic design, legal services, agricultural consulting, dairy and food processing, and light manufacturing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These and other emerging businesses have benefited from WIE’s MBA Corps program, which demonstrates the value of trained managers to owners of small and medium-sized women’s enterprises, some of which cling to traditional practices of retaining family or clan members instead of employing professional managers. WIE has matched MBA graduates with 58 client businesses in Kabul, Herat, and Mazar-i-Sharif. Under a six-month agreement, a WIE mentor, the MBA graduate, and the business owner work to ensure each brings value to the respective enterprise and each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----WIE-2018-9.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----WIE-2018-9&quot; title=&quot;Women in Herat participate in an exercise to assess their professional strengths and weaknesses.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Sustainable, Generational Economic Growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustaining the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/out-of-hiding-assisting-young-educated-women-in-afghanistan-to-finally-enter-the-workforce/&quot;&gt;participation of women in Afghanistan’s mainstream economy&lt;/a&gt; requires a long-term, holistic approach. WIE incorporates youth into training programs so older and younger businesswomen and trainees learn from one another. As businesses owned or managed by women become more confident and vocal, and enter the forefront of Afghanistan’s business community, this movement will pave the way for more women with a business idea to step forward or seek skills training. Many of WIE’s client businesses start as small, home-based ventures, become viable with strategic assistance, and, in turn, create jobs. WIE considers no venture too small to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time has come to change the mindsets of Afghans—especially young ones—from being observers of government-sponsored programs to becoming employers and job creators through their own efforts. Afghanistan’s government, through its Women’s Economic Empowerment National Priority Program, is on board, though translating that commitment into practice requires practical assistance. By enabling more women to enter the formal economy and start and grow businesses, USAID’s Promote: Women in the Economy is laying a foundation for Afghanistan to sustainably create jobs, grow its economy, and deliver stability and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jordan Embraces Renewables to Fuel its Economy</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/jordan-embraces-renewables-to-fuel-its-economy</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/jordan-embraces-renewables-to-fuel-its-economy</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jordan needs to grow its economy. More than 700,000 of its young people—&lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/%20SL.UEM.1524.ZS&quot;&gt;39 percent&lt;/a&gt; of the available labor force ages 15 to 24—are without a job. Many have good educations and are &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/addressing-jordans-youth-unemployment-bubble-usaid-program-aligns-workforce-with-emerging-opportunities/&quot;&gt;holding out for high-quality employment&lt;/a&gt;. Jordan is also hosting an enormous influx of Syrian refugees, which has helped swell its population from 7.5 million in 2011 to 10 million today. Many of these newcomers are also seeking work. But Jordan is almost completely reliant on imported oil and gas for its energy, limiting its ability to grow the economy and create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-competitiveness-program-jcp&quot;&gt;Jordan Competitiveness Program (JCP)&lt;/a&gt; analyzed Jordan’s energy potential as part of the U.S. Agency for International Development’s support for the Kingdom. The analysis found that improving energy self-sufficiency alone could create 13,300 jobs in Jordan—4,200 in centralized renewable energy such as wind- and solar-power farms, 3,900 in decentralized (local) renewable energy generation, and 5,200 in supporting efficient energy use through insulation, better windows and lighting, and improved systems and machinery. Creating these renewable energy sources is projected to save the country 3.1 million barrels annually in imported oil. The analysis also documented a 25 percent average annual increase in demand for engineers and technicians to design, install, and maintain solar- and wind-powered systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The JCP team has since assisted Jordan in putting these recommendations to work. Today, Jordan is leading the Middle East and North Africa in &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.bnef.com/new-energy-outlook/&quot;&gt;renewable energy growth&lt;/a&gt; according to &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg New Energy Finance&lt;/em&gt;, and is ranked &lt;a href=&quot;http://global-climatescope.org/en/country/jordan/#/enabling-framework&quot;&gt;third out of 71 countries worldwide&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-4&quot; title=&quot;The Oasis500 CleanTech bootcamp assisted by the USAID Jordan Competitiveness Program promoted startups and facilitated access to investors.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Clean Tech Emerges as an Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan possesses scant natural resources. As a result, it imports 96 percent of its oil and gas. While this makes the country’s economy highly vulnerable to market and geopolitical forces, Jordan is blessed with one of the world’s highest solar irradiance levels—necessary for producing solar energy at scale. Jordan also has substantial potential in hilly areas for wind-generated power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assist Jordan down this path, the JCP team, which began its work in 2013, has helped mobilize US$3.2 million in private sector and government spending for solar panels and associated needs such as metering. JCP has helped 18 factories conduct detailed energy audits, which produced the information they required to finance energy efficiency upgrades, using loans made through institutions such as Jordan Ahli Bank, where JCP trained loan officers on the responsible financing of clean-tech projects, which takes into account energy savings and other factors. JCP also supported the Wasateia Municipality and Irbid Speciality hospitals as they made solar-energy investments that have now achieved financial closure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy audits that made these and other financing transactions possible were conducted through Jordan’s Energy and Environmental Sustainability (EES) unit that was established with JCP support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-wind.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-wind&quot; title=&quot;The Tafila Wind Farm was built with International Finance Corporation support and inaugurated by the Kingdom of Jordan in 2015. It produces enough energy to power 80,000 homes. Photo: Dominic Chavez/IFC.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Helping Jordan Meet New Demand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To meet Jordan’s increasing demand for renewable energy engineers, JCP partnered with EDAMA, a Jordanian business association, to launch energy training courses certified by the Association of Energy Engineers. This initiative helped certify more than 200 Jordanian professionals through programs such as the Renewable Energy Professional curriculum. Notably, JCP sponsored two waves of female engineers to acquire the international certification—64 women in all—in sought-after courses such as Certified Energy Manager, the world’s most recognized energy certification. These certifications have improved young Jordanians’ chances for getting hired in this growing sector, and their certifications are expected to help employers compete for international and regional contracts. Strengthening Jordan’s clean energy workforce has helped improve the country’s reputation as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://oxfordbusinessgroup.com/news/jordan-sees-rising-investment-clean-technology&quot;&gt;investment destination for clean tech projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-1&quot; title=&quot;The first electric vehicle charging station in Jordan was unveiled at the King Hussein Business Park.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pioneering Use of Electric Vehicles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years, the JCP team helped Jordan &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0DKmx1WV33o&quot;&gt;usher its electric vehicle industry&lt;/a&gt; from the drawing room to the showroom. JCP has &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/plugging-in-to-jordans-rising-demand-for-electric-cars/&quot;&gt;promoted electric vehicle charging stations&lt;/a&gt; by developing new regulations that enable private citizens or businesses to establish, own, or operate electric vehicle charging stations. With charging stations about to pop up at more locations, such as shopping malls, consumers are freer to consider electric vehicles. JCP &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/1.%20USAID%20JCP%20Competitiveness%20Brief%20-%20Building%20a%20New%20Electric%20Vehicle%20Industry%20-%20FINAL%20(Branded)%5B1%5D.pdf&quot;&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; that the industry can attract $3 billion in investment in the next decade to develop charging stations and infrastructure, electric vehicle dealerships, and the related support services needed to maintain the thousands of electric vehicles on Jordan’s roads. In fact, BMW and Tesla have already established related operations in Jordan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0__/M9rxRCfGfQANrLXKqrS4&quot; title=&quot;Jordan Electric Vehicles&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?7zI&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Energy Self-Reliance is Transformational&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to energy—and thus electricity—can dramatically improve people’s lives. Being able to turn on a reading lamp, for example, light up a town center, or power up enterprises small and large. While some of DAI’s work specifically addresses energy—notably our work in &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/polseff-legacy-lower-energy-bills-for-businesses-across-poland-a-financing-model-to-scale-and-replicate/&quot;&gt;energy finance&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/helping-eastern-partnership-countries-meet-their-voluntary-commitments-to-reduce-emissions-address-climate-change/&quot;&gt;reducing emissions&lt;/a&gt;—all developing countries can benefit from better energy availability and more efficient use, including in sectors such as farming and agribusiness, water and sanitation, health, and, in Jordan’s case, job creation, post-conflict transition, and refugee integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-Energy-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-Energy-2&quot; title=&quot;Green Job Fair at the Landmark Hotel linked companies that work in the green technology sector with professionals and graduates who have relevant skills.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to its own unemployed, Jordan since 2011 has seen 1.4 million refugees cross its border from neighboring Syria. Half are registered and living mostly in encampments, while the other half have been absorbed by Jordan’s cities and communities. While this influx has &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/calculating-syrian-refugee-crisis-fiscal-crisis/&quot;&gt;strained Jordan’s resources&lt;/a&gt;, the country has been working with international donors and investors to recast this situation into an economic development opportunity. To do so, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-we-keep-the-promisemobilizing-business-on-the-refugee-frontline-in-jordan/&quot;&gt;Jordan Compact was created&lt;/a&gt; to support the Jordanian private sector in industries such as garment manufacture, plastics, and agriculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of its assistance to the Compact, DAI identified these sectors of potential competitive advantage and the barriers—including legal, policy, and regulatory—to developing them, one of which is the availability of energy. Jordan has fully embraced its need to develop its clean energy sector and take the journey to energy self-reliance. We believe the country will eventually achieve its clean-energy potential. And in time, it may even be able to export solar- and wind-powered electricity to neighbors in need such as Lebanon, Palestine, and Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keep Up the Fight for High-Quality Education for All in Pakistan</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/keep-up-the-fight</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 19:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/keep-up-the-fight</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After more than five years of campaigning for the right of every Pakistani child to receive a quality education, &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; ended on August 31. Before we go, we should explain why the campaign is ending, and more importantly, we should thank the people that made this campaign as effective as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we began this journey on February 13, 2013, we had one overarching objective: to make education a more meaningful part of the political discourse in Pakistan. We promised DFID, the U.K. government department that funded &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;, that everything the campaign will do will serve the end of ensuring that education grows in importance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, there have been several changes in how education is perceived and treated in Pakistan. In the budget for fiscal year 2013/2014, all four provinces and the federal government allocated a total of just under PKR580 billion (GBP3.6 billion). In the fiscal year 2017/2018, total allocations increased to more than Rs. 900 billion (GBP5.6 billion). Over 4 million children have been added to the school rolls across the country since 2013. Teacher absenteeism has decreased dramatically in many parts of the country. And no teacher anywhere in Pakistan is hired without a test of their basic cognitive abilities through either the National Testing Service or a similar standardized metric. But these changes are a small start of a longer journey.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;’s role was to change the conversation about education for the better. We began tracking coverage of education in the print media in 2013 and tracked it until June 2018. In 2013, there were an average of 133 newspaper stories every month. The average number of stories per month so far in 2018 has been 1,016. This represents a nearly eight times increase in coverage of education. Our key objective to make education a more meaningful part of the political discourse in Pakistan has been met. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pursued this objective by working with you, by trying to inform you, by trying to engage you, sometimes by trying to provoke you, and sometimes trying to inspire you. You were the head and the feet, and the mind and heart of the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign. You were &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-2-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-2-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great campaigns have a clear start date, and a clear end date: Ours has arrived. But great causes never cease being important. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you believe that all Pakistani children should have the same opportunity as the luckiest children anywhere on the planet. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you believe that every Pakistani parent should be able to have full color, true black, 4k dreams for their children—and that no parent’s dream for her child should be limited by the lack of a decent education. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you believe that real reform in education starts with government schools and ends with them, too. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because 25 million children out of school was unacceptable in 2014, and 22.8 million is unacceptable in 2018. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because television channels used to think that nobody watches TV shows about education, but YOU watched them. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign because you forced the two biggest political parties in our country to fight each other on the issue of education—something that had never happened before. You were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign, in 2013, when you wrote more than 10,000 letters to politicians asking them to do more for education, and you were the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign in 2018, when the winning party’s leader made children a central part of his first address to the nation. You were &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; this whole time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----TEP-1-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----TEP-1-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many nonprofit and nongovernmental organizations have been on this journey with us. They will continue to do amazing work. Many government officials, especially in the provincial capitals, made education a matter of personal pride. They will not stop serving our great country. Many politicians took on the issue of education as one that was important to them and their constituents. They will not stop working to serve the people. Perhaps most of all, every news channel, every reporter, every anchor, and every channel owner that we ever approached to make education a more important part of their coverage obliged. They will not stop informing, provoking and inspiring. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout all of this, our digital footprint has been among the most carefully curated spaces we have engaged with. Our Facebook page, with more than 3 million followers, is the place that motivated us every day: young Pakistanis, engaging with serious content, in a serious manner. Our &lt;em&gt;Taleem Do&lt;/em&gt; website and application for the 2018 election were the final pushes for the campaign to try—as one government was going out, and another was coming in—to ensure that education remained an important part of the conversation. As we hand over our Facebook page and other digital assets to DFID, we are humbled by how impactful these platforms have been in engaging you, informing you, and once in a while, provoking and inspiring you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DEVS----4%20(1)-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DEVS----4 (1)-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; campaign ends, new narratives in the struggle to ensure quality education for all Pakistani children are emerging. &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; incubated the Pak Alliance for Maths and Science, a collective of more than 50 civil society organizations, businesses and government bodies—so that Pakistani children are provided with more and better opportunities to learn 21st century cognitive skills. We have also worked with almost two dozen local campaigns, originally initiated by &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt;, and now coming into their own. They will take forward the important conversations about access to school at the middle and high school levels, about the link between nutrition and cognition, about better utilization and better use of public funds for education, and most of all, about quality and learning outcomes in the weeks, months and years to come. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing gives us more confidence about the future of education reforms in Pakistan than knowing this one simple truth: since you were &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; all along, you will continue to argue and fight for every Pakistani child’s right to a high-quality education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your voice has made a big difference, and it needs to continue to do so. Please don’t ever stop demanding a better future for Pakistani children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Mosharraf Zaidi and the entire &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/pakistan-transforming-education-pakistan-tep&quot;&gt;Transforming Education in Pakistan (TEP)&lt;/a&gt; programme was launched in 2013 to address a severe problem: 25 million school-aged children in Pakistan were not attending school, due in part to &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-elections-looming-can-pakistan-fulfill-its-education-promise-to-unschooled-children/&quot;&gt;complacency in government&lt;/a&gt; regarding education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past five years, TEP amassed an impressive following for its political advocacy and media campaign: &lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan.&lt;/em&gt; The campaign focused on prompting parents and communities in Pakistan to demand &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6nciO3A-MhI&quot;&gt;high-quality education&lt;/a&gt; and urging elected and appointed officials to take tangible steps toward its provision for children ages 5 through 16, as Pakistani law requires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alif Ailaan&lt;/em&gt; succeeded in elevating education issues into the political discourse, promoting data-informed journalism on education, pioneering ground-breaking publications, and lobbying the Pakistani government to research, calculate, and publish a nationally accepted number for out-of-school children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID)-funded programme wound down in August, its champion, Team Leader Mosharraf Zaidi, wrote this farewell letter to the people of Pakistan documenting the movement’s impact.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Placing Women at the Center of Water Supply Management in Kenya</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/placing-women-at-the-center-of-water-supply-management-in-kenya</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 13:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/placing-women-at-the-center-of-water-supply-management-in-kenya</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As Christine Kanini checks water meters on her weekly rounds, she recalls that 18 months earlier she could not aspire to this job. “We had mainly male meter readers,” Kanini said. “Then I was promoted to this position from gate keeping. I am happy with the work.” Over the past year, the Wote Water and Sewerage Company (WOWASCO), which serves the small city of Wote in south-central Kenya, has opened up opportunities for women such as Kanini in fields that were previously deemed suited for men only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes are part of gender initiatives supported by the U.S. Agency for International Development’s Kenya Integrated Water, Sanitation and Health (KIWASH) project. To improve the lives and health of 1 million Kenyans across nine counties, the five-year project (2015–2020) focuses on developing and managing sustainable water, sanitation, and hygiene (WASH) services. Central to this objective is ensuring that everyone—especially women—has equal access to the opportunities created through improved WASH services, including jobs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-2&quot; title=&quot;Christine Kanini, right, speaking with a customer in Makueni County, Kenya. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Water Services Affect Women&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men and women benefit from water differently—both as users and water services providers. As users, given their conventional primary role in child care, domestic work, and water collection, women and girls are most disadvantaged and even put at risk when they must travel several kilometers or queue for many hours at local kiosks to gather the water they need to complete daily chores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these adverse conditions have become widely known, women’s potential roles in water services are less understood. Specifically, women’s lack of engagement and voice in providing water services has detrimentally affected their economic opportunity in the sector—especially their ability to get jobs—and limited their influence on investment and service decisions. Kenya typifies this sectoral imbalance. Despite women’s heavy role in water use, men in Kenya have dominated almost every water utility and related decision authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationally, Kenya has made significant progress toward improving these inequities: its new constitution from 2010 lists access to water and sanitation as a basic human right and mandates equal gender representation in these public sectors. Likewise, the government’s Vision 2030 plan recognizes that gender equality will play a critical role in achieving the country’s development goals. 
Despite these stipulations, however, progress has been slow. To help the country increase gender equity, KIWASH analyzed 13 water utilities across the nine counties where we work to determine the barriers women face as both employees and customers and to identify areas for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-6&quot; title=&quot;Cooperative Bank of Kenya staff received training on water sector financing and ways to improve loan quality and reduce risk. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Improving the Gender Ratio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH’s assessment found that none of the 13 water utilities met the minimum requirement of 30 percent female representation—whether on the Board of Directors or in corporate or technical management roles. None were led by women or had in place approved gender or sexual harassment policies. In addition, utility employees generally perceived that discrimination existed in recruitment, job placement, and advancement, and in the treatment of pregnant or lactating women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH worked with each utility to develop Gender Equity Action Plans; these plans established improvement goals, training on gender equality awareness, and policies and recruitment strategies to attract female leaders and employees. Several of these utilities have now drafted or implemented new recruitment policies that stipulate gender ratios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Nairobi City Water and Sewerage Company (NCWSC) employs 3,000 people. One year ago, only two of eight of the company’s leadership positions were held by women; today, men and women are equally represented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vicky Maiyo, the Donor Project Officer with NCWSC, described the progress she is starting to see. “Initially, leadership in the utility company was a male affair,” Maiyo said. “After the trainings, we have four women heading the regions and three of our six managers are women. And with technical work, like those operating water tankers, excavators, or driving heavy commercial vehicles, there is [increased female] representation where before those jobs were dominantly male.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-4&quot; title=&quot;Water company staff in Mbooni, Makueni County, received training to reduce revenue losses caused by leaks, theft, poor billing systems, and weak metering policies. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Women Doing a Great Job&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The KIWASH team has heard reports that women water staffers take more time to explain service delivery issues to customers and are particularly effective in collecting revenue, where customer relations are key. In one striking example, the best performer at NCWSC was a female staff member who collected KES120 million (US$1.2 million) in one month, setting a company record for monthly collection. Some water company staff have noted that women leaders have helped improve discipline among staff through closer monitoring and engagement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wote, WOWASCO did not meet the 30 percent female representation required by law. WOWASCO is now encouraging and seeking out qualified women to apply for vacant board positions and lobbying the county government to consider recruiting women to its Public Service Board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two female WOWASCO staff were recently allowed to join the formerly all-male meter-reading team. They received on-the-job training and are now enjoying interacting with customers and learning more about the water delivery part of the business. “I like this job,” Kanini said as she drove from one house to the next in Wote Town, speaking with customers and reading meters. WOWASCO Managing Director Joseph Kuti is also pleased with the changes he is seeing. “We thought these were men’s jobs,” Kuti said. “Yet Christine performs well in her job. Her zone has the least complaints.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Addressing Sexual Harassment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH carries out quarterly assessments of water services providers to track improvements in gender equality mainstreaming. These assessments are premised on short- and medium-term action plans developed during KIWASH trainings. As sexual harassment affects women’s dignity as well as water provider performance and utility/customer relations, sexual harassment needs to be tackled head on. KIWASH worked with the utilities to conduct 11 training sessions and develop action plans that raise awareness of what constitutes sexual harassment and how it harms people and job performance. KIWASH is now advising water companies on how to develop sexual harassment policies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-1&quot; title=&quot;Vicky Maiyo, seated center, and women officers from the biggest water company in Kenya after gender mainstreaming training in Nairobi. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Reaching More Female Customers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KIWASH’s gender assessment revealed another barrier women face: 85 percent of the utilities required a title deed to apply for a water connection. In a highly patriarchal society such as Kenya, men tend to hold such deeds. As a result, many widows and single mothers—especially in poor households—are unable to apply for water connections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With support from KIWASH, two water companies have addressed this challenge. The Kitui Water and Sanitation Company no longer requires a title deed to apply for a water connection. Since the change, the connections officer noted that most new applicants are women without title deeds; dropping this requirement has helped hundreds of households to access water. WOWASCO also changed its application requirements and now only asks for an identification card. Kuti, the managing director, is at the forefront of promoting gender equity in service provision. “Our next step is to develop a gender policy for generations to come, so that the changes we are making last forever,” Kuti said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tailoring some of its key communications to women has also led to increased engagement from female customers. Maiyo recollects how NCWSC did not have a direct gender policy for customer outreach. “The company used to hold joint community meetings with men and women during feasibility studies,” Maiyo said. “Men would dominate the meetings. However, we have learned that in some communities it is better to hold separate meetings for men and women. As a result, women express themselves freely and this is a good step for the company as we obtain inclusive feedback from the community.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----KIWASH-Women-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----KIWASH-Women-5&quot; title=&quot;Demonstration garden in Kisumu County where local suppliers provide seed and fertilizer to showcase production of nutrient-dense, high-value crops using efficient irrigation and water management. Photo: USAID KIWASH.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Removing Barriers, Strengthening Society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender equality is a fundamental human right but also necessary to fuel a prosperous and sustainable economic future in Kenya. With KIWASH support, Kenya’s water utility sector is increasing gender equity, providing more and better job opportunities for women, improving the workplace environment, and increasing access to water services for thousands of women. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the office to conduct field work, Kanini smiled and reflected on the opportunities now available to her. “My future at this company is bright; I have hope that I can be promoted to another position in the office,” she said. “Thanks to KIWASH, I have more opportunity and flexibility to organize my work, and my life will be better because of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Market-Driven Strategies to Reduce Poverty and Human Trafficking in Nigeria</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-market-driven-strategies-to-reduce-poverty-and-human-trafficking-in-nigeria</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 19:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/using-market-driven-strategies-to-reduce-poverty-and-human-trafficking-in-nigeria</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite having the largest economy in Africa, around half of Nigeria’s population still lives in extreme poverty. A few hundred miles east of the new skyscrapers and shopping malls of Nigeria’s commercial capital of Lagos, the Niger Delta—made up of nine oil-producing states and home to more than 31 million people—defines the country’s stark contrast in living conditions. Even though it is a major oil-producing region, much of the Delta’s population lives in remote villages and survives on subsistence farming. Exacerbating this poverty is a lack of modern agricultural equipment and supplies that farmers need to improve crop yields, as well as limited access to markets in which to sell their harvests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, development practitioners may have viewed subsidizing agricultural supplies as the solution to such predicaments. While these programs had some success in the short term, the models were often unsustainable after projects closed and subsidies ended. When the U.K. Department for International Development launched the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/nigeria-market-development-programme-made&quot;&gt;Market Development in the Niger Delta&lt;/a&gt; (MADE) project in 2013, it took a different tack and sought to address the root causes of rural poverty. Utilizing a Making Markets Work for the Poor (M4P) approach, MADE helped leading agribusinesses to see the business value in providing technologies, inputs, and services directly to small farmers and training farmers to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/MADE_article_1-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MADE_article_1-1&quot; title=&quot;Cassava farmers increased productivity thanks to quality agricultural inputs and improved practices. Photo Credit: U.K. Department for International Development MADE.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of implementing this M4P approach in the Niger Delta have been encouraging. The recently completed first phase of MADE helped more than 150,000 small farmers increase their incomes. A second phase, MADE II, will continue applying these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/economic-growth-solutions/value-chain-and-market-systems-development&quot;&gt;market-driven strategies&lt;/a&gt; toward a new goal: to reduce the growing number of Nigerians caught up in modern slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Making Connections to Improve Agricultural Profitability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most small farms in the Niger Delta produce below their potential due to poor soil and limited access to fertilizer, good seeds, and other farming inputs. The major agricultural supply wholesalers and retailers that sell these products and services are concentrated in city centers and do not see small farmers in far-off villages as a profitable audience. In turn, rural farmers are often unaware of how spending a little more on better agricultural inputs could help them increase their productivity and incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MADE identified six value chains with high potential to benefit small farmers—poultry, cassava, palm oil, fisheries, finished leather goods, and agricultural inputs—by remedying this disconnect between input suppliers and farmers. The project partnered with 25 leading agribusinesses and 488 retailers in these value chains to help them understand the potential profit to be gained from targeting rural farmers with affordable products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MADE worked with these companies to reach new rural markets to promote their products and to change attitudes and practices of smallholder farmers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/MADE_article_2-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MADE_article_2-1&quot; title=&quot;Farmers purchasing chicken vaccines for the first time reduced flock mortality and increase profitability for poultry keeping. Photo: U.K. Department for International Development MADE.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To promote the use of crop protection products, MADE assisted companies to organize and co-sponsor product demonstrations on trial plots and at field day events, as well as helping companies to develop their distribution channels. The project also brought lead firms together with nongovernmental organizations working in agriculture to train farmers (especially women) how to use new products or improve their practices. Together, these supply companies and NGOs developed 800 demonstration plots across the nine Delta states.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MADE piloted and scaled commercially sustainable services, including developing a network of fee-based trainers focused on aquaculture productivity and business skills. More than 4,300 fish farmers purchased the training, which helped them increase their production by up to 65 percent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To promote the adoption of productivity-enhancing technologies, such as palm oil processors and fish smoking kilns, MADE provided small cost-sharing grants that made new equipment accessible for entrepreneurs in rural villages. This approach helped increase farmers’ incomes while allowing them to launch self-sustaining processing businesses in their villages, which in turn inspired neighbors to purchase new technologies as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A prime example of MADE’s M4P approach was the project’s work in the cassava value chain. Nigeria is the world’s largest producer of cassava, an important food staple and cash crop. However, most cassava farmers do not use high-quality seeds (stems), fertilizer, or modern farming methods. In addition, rural businesses that process cassava products do not have contacts in large markets that could help expand their sales. MADE facilitated linkages between small cassava processors and major buyers, and worked with agricultural supply companies to target sales and promotions at cassava farmers in distant villages. These activities reached more than 79,000 smallholder farmers, improving crop yields and market sales and helping to generate an additional £7 million in income across the cassava value chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, MADE worked with farmers and business partners to improve earnings from poultry, particularly for women who raised chickens. Seeing that disease and inefficient feeding and watering were contributing to high mortality rates for chickens, the project helped veterinary service providers understand a business case for targeting small poultry farmers with vaccination services, high-quality feed, and other products. MADE also co-sponsored product demonstrations in rural areas, motivating 36,000 farmers to purchase vaccination services for the first time. As a result of farmers learning about and buying new veterinary products and services, chicken mortality rates were reduced and poultry farmers experienced a collective £2 million increase in incomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across all six of its target value chains, MADE’s market systems approach generated an additional £14 million in incomes for farmers and small businesses and helped 155,000 Nigerians increase their incomes by an average of 15 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_f639a853-dac7-4a24-839d-cd1974f32c73&quot; title=&quot;MADE I Results&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?B7m&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Roots of Human Trafficking in Nigeria&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While MADE was assisting farmers in the Niger Delta to improve their livelihoods, new challenges shook the economic foundations of the country. With oil making up 75 percent of the country’s exports, a dramatic fall in oil prices starting in late 2014 led to the Nigerian naira losing 70 percent of its value compared to the dollar over two and a half years. Beyond causing a deep recession and widespread unemployment, the sharp currency devaluation indirectly resulted in thousands of Nigerians migrating out of the country through informal channels and being lured into modern-day slavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, farmers living in villages where MADE worked were able to weather this economic downturn due to their mix of subsistence and cash crops. They even saw increased demand and higher prices for the food staples they produced—such as rice, cassava, and palm oil—when the products became too expensive to import. However, others in the Niger Delta—young people in particular—still did not see farming as a profitable future and were drawn to seemingly more lucrative livelihood opportunities in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Edo state in the Niger Delta in particular has long been a major feeder of these economic migrants,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/bill-grant&quot;&gt;Bill Grant&lt;/a&gt;, Global Practice Lead for Market Systems Development at DAI and an adviser to MADE. “For decades, women from Edo had been moving to Europe, intending to work in legitimate businesses and send money home. However, many of them were compelled or coerced into commercial sex work, with some women establishing their own, lucrative operations. In turn, they used traffickers to lure young girls from their communities back in Nigeria. In Edo, this business became socially recognized and accepted as a means to increase household income, creating a well-established ‘value chain’ of human trafficking from Edo to Europe.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This steady stream of recruits would turn into a flood once the naira deflated. With the now highly uneven exchange rate, the euros earned by Nigerians abroad are worth more than twice as many naira as before, creating a veritable gold rush for jobs in Europe. While at one time mostly females were trafficked from Edo, this new wave of migration was made up primarily of men. Unfortunately, once migrants leave the familiarity of Nigeria on the overland journey through Niger and Libya, they become easy prey for traffickers and most are extorted for additional money or sexually abused in exchange for passage to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After arriving in Libya, or on shore in Italy or Spain, victims find out too late that their traffickers’ promises of well-paying jobs turn out to be bonded labor or sexual exploitation accompanied by coercion, isolation, and physical abuse. The brutality of these traffickers and the sheer number of emigrating Nigerians caught up in modern slavery has received attention from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2017/12/04/africa/nigeria-benin-city-sex-trafficking/index.html&quot;&gt;CNN&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/04/10/the-desperate-journey-of-a-trafficked-girl&quot;&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/a&gt;, and other international media. In 2016 and 2017, an estimated 58,000 Nigerians made it across the Mediterranean into Italy, while more than 20,000 Nigerians are thought to be trapped in Libya. While no exact number exists to quantify these people, Nigeria is thought to be the leading source of trafficking victims in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creating Jobs at Home to Reduce Slavery Abroad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newly launched MADE II project will continue supporting farmers in the Niger Delta while also addressing the economic push factors in Edo that lead to human trafficking, as part of the U.K. Government’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/defeating-modern-slavery-theresa-may-article&quot;&gt;campaign to end modern slavery&lt;/a&gt; around the world. While many young people in the Niger Delta do not see farming as an aspirational path out of poverty, they lack knowledge about other career fields and the skills needed to enter them. Taking a market systems approach similar to the project’s first phase, MADE II will work with companies and professional associations to present value propositions for investing in Edo state’s workforce. The project will also partner with NGOs and education centers that currently provide job skills training to help them tailor their curricula to market demands and connect with populations susceptible to trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through an in-depth market analysis, MADE identified six sectors well positioned to create appealing job opportunities in Edo: high-end agribusiness, information and communication technology (ICT), renewable energy, wholesale and retail, cosmetics, and the entertainment industry. While there is evident potential for growth in these industries, connecting rural populations with jobs that exist primarily in major metropolitan areas will take vision, creativity, and unique partnerships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s television and film industry, for example, known as “Nollywood,” is the third largest in the world. The industry generates US$800 million a year in revenue while employing more than 1 million people. Nollywood movies and TV shows are popular around the African continent and are increasing in demand due to new satellite and streaming services. In the coming years, the industry is forecasted to hire a large number of skilled workers, such as set designers, production assistants, lighting and sound technicians, and make-up artists. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To connect job seekers in Edo with opportunities in Nollywood, MADE will work with industry professionals and associations, such as the Nollywood Association of Hair and Makeup Artists, to create online and in-person training courses for in-demand production skills, as well as establishing internship programs. In an effort to bring entertainment industry jobs closer to home, MADE will also explore a public-private partnership to develop a mini film village in Edo state, offering producers an affordable shooting location with cost-effective labor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/MADE_article_3-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MADE_article_3-1&quot; title=&quot;MADE II will facilitate trainings to give jobseekers skills needed to work in Nigeria&amp;#39;s growing entertainment industry. Photo: Partnership Initiatives in the Niger Delta.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s ICT industry presents another promising opportunity to make job connections in Edo. With more than 92 million internet users in Nigeria, demand is high for ICT products and services and the sector has been growing by 30 percent a year. As Google, Dell, IBM, and other multinational tech companies plan to expand into Nigeria, demand for skilled ICT workers will soon outpace the supply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most ICT jobs are based in Lagos, MADE II will work with companies to demonstrate how they can benefit from supporting the development of an ICT workforce in Edo or setting up operations in the state. Edo is already home to five universities and offers the market advantage of a lower cost of living and affordable labor. The project is already supporting a new technology hub in Edo, and will partner with companies and local organizations to hold ICT trainings and career fairs, offer mentorship programs, and expand the reach of a new coding academy in Edo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next two years, MADE II will apply this market-driven, partnership-based approach across other targeted sectors in Edo, while continuing to improve productivity and profitability for small farmers. The project aims to raise the incomes of 155,000 Nigerians, 30,000 of whom are in Edo, alleviating poverty in Nigeria and furthering the U.K. Government’s vision of a world without slavery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health System in Haiti Takes Key Step by Launching National Tuberculosis Tracker</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/health-system-in-haiti-takes-key-step-by-launching-national-tuberculosis-tracker</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/health-system-in-haiti-takes-key-step-by-launching-national-tuberculosis-tracker</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Haiti’s government this year launched a national electronic platform for reporting and tracking tuberculosis (TB), a key step in its efforts to capture, monitor, and report all patient-level data across the country. Information on cases of TB—a contagious and often deadly disease plaguing the Caribbean nation—is being prepared for aggregation into the System d’Information Sanitaire Nationale Unique, or SISNU, which uses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hisp.org/aboutus/&quot;&gt;DHIS2&lt;/a&gt; open-source software platform for reporting, analyzing, and disseminating national health data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Development of the TB tracker and related work is being led by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/haiti-strategic-health-information-system-his-program&quot;&gt;Haiti Strategic Health Information System (HIS) Program&lt;/a&gt;. Launched in 2017, HIS is funded by the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) and implemented by DAI in partnership with Haiti’s Ministry of Health (MSPP). Data on TB cases and treatment regimens is being captured electronically—and soon through a mobile application that will better serves remote locales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuberculosis in Haiti (2016)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11 million: country population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15,302: new/relapse cases of tuberculosis reported&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,700: estimated deaths from tuberculosis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://extranet.who.int/sree/Reports?op=Replet&amp;amp;name=%2FWHO_HQ_Reports%2FG2%2FPROD%2FEXT%2FTBCountryProfile&amp;amp;ISO2=HT&amp;amp;LAN=EN&amp;amp;outtype=html&quot;&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the three-month TB pilot phase, the HIS team trained health professionals at nine facilities from four of Haiti’s departments—Artibonite, Centre, North, and West. This area includes nearly half of all health facilities in Haiti that provide TB care and covers more than 70 percent of Haiti’s reported TB cases. Once the pilot was completed in April 2018, the HIS team and its partners deployed the platform to the rest of the country’s 10 departments, their health offices, and select health care facilities. Our goal was to capture data on 5,000 TB patients—through July 2018, we had captured data on more than 12,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Haiti-TB-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Haiti-TB-1&quot; title=&quot;Training health workers to operate Haiti&amp;#39;s national tuberculosis tracker.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Improving TB Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TB bacteria is typically spread by coughing, and the bacteria can become resistant to most drug cures if patients go untreated or their treatment is mismanaged. Haiti perpetually suffers the &lt;a href=&quot;http://apps.who.int/medicinedocs/documents/s23098en/s23098en.pdf&quot;&gt;highest incidence of TB in the Americas&lt;/a&gt;, with an estimated 21,000 cases in 2015. Solutions to control drug-resistant TB, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/features/qa/79/en/&quot;&gt;prescribed&lt;/a&gt; by the World Health Organization, are to cure the TB patient the first time around, provide access to diagnosis, control infection in facilities where patients are treated, and ensure appropriate use of recommended second-line drugs. Implementing these solutions on a national scale requires data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TB tracker digitizes previously paperbound patient details registered by health care providers at local facilities. These registries previously had to be manually collected and then transported and entered by hand at the department and national levels. The tracker will eventually include four case-specific modules—for routine cases, outset cases, multi-drug resistant cases, and HIV cases (which can be a precursor to TB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TB and future trackers will improve data quality and inform decision making; for instance, helping the government decide where to invest in clinics and staff. The tracker can be adapted to capture and integrate data on other diseases—such as HIV/AIDS, cholera, flu, and non-communicable diseases. It is already capturing patient-level immunization data for migration to SISNU and being used to develop community-based mobile health information apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five-year HIS program ultimately aims to build the capacity of the Ministry of Health to take ownership and optimize the use of SISNU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Haiti-TB-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Haiti-TB-2&quot; title=&quot;Haiti HIS Field Officer Pouchy Dacière trains Northeastern Health Directorate representatives to insert data on SISNU.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting Health Systems in Good Order&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haiti’s health reporting platforms need to be shored up to better serve citizens, especially given the country’s history of contagious disease and natural disaster. The January 2010 earthquake demolished 50 health centers, part of Haiti’s primary teaching hospital, and the Ministry of Health. The country still heavily relies on international funding to provide Haitians access to health care services. The government itself could help fund and manage these services if armed with improved aggregated data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Haiti and other developing countries can benefit greatly now and well into the future simply by getting their health information systems in good order,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/bobby-jefferson&quot;&gt;Bobby Jefferson&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Technology Officer for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/solutions/global-health&quot;&gt;DAI Global Health&lt;/a&gt;. “By applying health informatics with discipline, countries such as Haiti will be far better prepared to reap good value from investments in health care planning and delivery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lack of ongoing collection of reliable health data has harmed the Haitian government’s ability to plan for and respond efficiently to public health needs. Launching the TB data platform marks an important step for the country in its goal to become better prepared to respond to both health crises and the daily needs of its 11 million people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaboration is Essential to Improving Maternal and Newborn Health in Indonesia</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lets-work-together-to-improve-maternal-and-newborn-health</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 14:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/lets-work-together-to-improve-maternal-and-newborn-health</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This opinion piece was first published in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thejakartapost.com/&quot;&gt;Jakarta Post&lt;/a&gt; on August 15, 2018.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Indonesia celebrates its 73rd year of independence, most people are aware of the country’s impressive economic development over the past few years. But perhaps fewer are aware that, every hour, across this massive archipelago, two mothers and eight newborns die. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country still faces unacceptably high levels of maternal and newborn mortality. This is a multi-faceted and complex issue, which requires collaboration between all elements of society to ensure effective measures are taken to improve maternal and newborn wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Intercensal Survey of 2015 estimated that the maternal mortality is 305 per 100,000 live births. The Indonesia Demographic and Health Survey 2017 data suggests newborn deaths are 15 per 1,000 live births. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite less maternal and newborn mortality between 1990 and 2015, Indonesia fell short of the Millennium Development Goals that require countries to reduce mortality rates by three quarters. In Asia, Indonesia ranks behind Bangladesh, Cambodia, and Myanmar on this front. Reducing maternal and newborn deaths is part of the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), a United Nations-led agenda guiding countries worldwide to work together to tackle global challenges over the next 15 years. Under Goal 3, countries agree to ensure healthy lives and promote well-being for all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve this goal, Indonesia plans to increase access to high-quality health services and implement universal health coverage. The country aims to reduce the maternal mortality ratio to less than 70 per 100,000 live births, and to reduce neonatal mortality rates to as low as 12 per 1,000 by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Indonesia, pre-eclampsia or eclampsia, which is a pregnancy-induced hypertension; post-partum hemorrhage; and other infection-related obstetric emergencies; are the leading causes of maternal mortality. Complications from preterm birth, asphyxia—the condition when the body is deprived of oxygen—and low birth weight are the major causes of newborn deaths. These deaths are preventable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/ibubayi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 40%; float: left;  margin-right: 1em;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A critical way to prevent these deaths is to improve the quality of maternal and newborn care. Improving quality of care is a multidimensional effort, and requires partnerships between health care providers, managers, communities, and policy makers. According to a recent World Bank report on private sector supply-side readiness, as well as reports from the U.S. Agency for International Development’s Expanding Maternal and Neonatal Survival project, primary maternal health services across public and private facilities face major quality challenges in service readiness, in terms of medicine, basic obstetric care, and referrals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public and private health providers can work together to provide pregnant women and newborns with high-quality care. This means access to skilled care with evidence-based practices delivered in a humane, respectful, and supportive environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring high-quality care means paying attention to health facilities’ physical infrastructure, human resources, skills, and capacity to manage both normal pregnancies and complications. Part of high-quality care is a better referral system so that when an emergency arises, families, midwives, and facilities can ensure pregnant women have access to advanced emergency services, including emergency transport as well as high-quality health facilities ready to manage difficult pregnancies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality care is also an opportunity for communities. Communities play a critical role to create demand for, and access to, high-quality maternal and newborn services. Families and midwives can empower and increase the knowledge of pregnant women and their families so that they understand the importance of good care, as well as their rights under key programs such as the national health insurance progam. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, pregnant women should be aware of the Ministry of Health’s recommendation for an expectant mother to receive four antenatal care visits during pregnancy, high-quality services during labor, delivery with a skilled professional, and three post-partum visits for mothers and their newborns after delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say it takes a village to raise a healthy child. But it will take a nation to ensure every pregnant woman and newborn can access high-quality care. The time is now to come together and use evidence to improve quality of care and reduce preventable maternal and newborn deaths—contributing to a healthier Indonesia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agriculture Finance with a Climate Lens Takes Off in Kenya</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/agriculture-finance-with-a-climate-lens-takes-off-in-kenya</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/agriculture-finance-with-a-climate-lens-takes-off-in-kenya</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The effects of climate change in the already arid lands of Kenya are particularly tough on its economy. Think: tourism, arable agriculture, horticulture, floriculture, and livestock—all vulnerable to extreme changes in weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.K. Department for International Department (DFID) is known for approaching climate change in innovative ways. Its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-hunger-safety-net-programme-phase-2-hsnp2&quot;&gt;Hunger Safety Net Programme&lt;/a&gt;, for example, uses digital cash transfers to help the very poorest Kenyan households in times of drought and flood. Now, DFID is supporting a new path-breaking approach, the Finance Innovation for Climate Change Fund (FICCF), an initiative to promote the commercialization of climate-resilient commodities by on-lending to Kenyan smallholder farmers in the sorghum, cassava, dairy, and indigenous chicken value chains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2014 by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/kenya-strengthening-adaptation-and-resilience-climate-change-kenya-plus-starck&quot;&gt;Strengthening Adaptation and Resilience to Climate Change in Kenya Plus (StARCK+)&lt;/a&gt; programme, the FICCF, implemented by DAI, will be run by the Kenya Markets Trust as StARCK+ winds down this month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How Does the Fund Work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, Kenya’s financial institutions have been reluctant to lend to smallholder farmers. Not only has it been nearly impossible for small agribusinesses and farmers to get loans, but the financial institutions themselves had limited knowledge of the agriculture sector. The uncertainty brought on by climate change compounds the risky nature of lending to smallholder farmers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against this backdrop, the FICCF brings together a novel mix of partners that don’t typically work together: four microfinance institutions, 16 agribusiness aggregators, one climate information service provider, an insurance company, and an information and communications technology service provider, in addition to the technical and extension service providers contracted by the microfinance institutions to build farmer capacity through adaptive technologies and practices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working through the FICCF, these partners have created a mechanism where climate finance can flow through existing commercial financial institutions to smallholders and aggregators, while at the same time de-risking investments by providing hybrid insurance products and weather advisories. This combination of financial inclusion initiatives and market linkages within a climate lens is at the heart of the innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/MFI.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MFI&quot; title=&quot;The financial institutions market their services to smallholder farmers.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The £2 million fund started as a pilot in 2014. To date, loans have been extended for such things as improved cow breeds, cow housing, fodder production, and seed for sorghum and cassava cuttings. The loans also enable aggregators to pay farmers promptly once they hand over their product, rather than have farmers waiting months until aggregators are paid by end buyers. So far, more than 5,000 farmers across 18 counties have received loans. When the long rainy season hits (March to June), the microfinance institutions provide loans for sorghum production and input financing. Another 4,000 farmers have taken advantage of the sorghum loans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Appealing to the Banks and Farmers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To bring in the microfinance institutions, FICCF uses “returnable capital”—a revolving fund model to kickstart forward lending to aggregators and smallholders along the selected value chains. Returnable capital is essentially a pot of money that FICCF makes available to the microfinance institutions for three to four years; the institutions on-lend that money for six to 12 months, and when it is repaid the money is returned for further lending to farmers or aggregators.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to loan financing, the FICCF offers microfinance institutions a 20 percent matching grant to fund technical assistance on climate-smart approaches for farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most FICCF clients are smallholders and small to medium-sized enterprises with no credit history, little collateral, and limited (although diverse) resources. Smallholders have only small areas of land for cropping and rearing, very low incomes, and limited access to inputs, assets, and infrastructure. Without irrigation or affordable water collection options, farmers rely on increasingly erratic seasonal rainfall. These limitations often make it difficult for farmers to subsist on what they cultivate or rear, and nearly impossible to produce enough to sell for income. FICCF’s financial inclusion model enables smallholders to access loans for farm inputs, with the goal of facilitating a transformational leap to a rural economy beyond subsistence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increased productivity at the farm translates into overall improved livelihoods, a greater ability to borrow and invest. Ann Maina, Managing Director of Inuka Microfinance Institution, said, “We are projecting longer relationships with these farmers and developing other products for them.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four selected commodities—sorghum, cassava, dairy, and chicken—while climate-resilient, are generally bought and sold in unstructured markets exploited by middlemen. Cassava and sorghum are considered subsistence crops by local Kenyans, sold largely in informal markets. Kienyieji chicken is an indigenous variety that is mostly reared in backyards. While a structured market for dairy products exists, producers struggle to achieve sustainable practices and adequate productivity. FICCF’s capacity building support up and down the four value chains has helped to establish scalable and sustainable formal commodity markets where previously there were none. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Sorghum%20drying2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sorghum drying2&quot; title=&quot;Sorgum is proving to be more climate-resilient than maize because it is naturally drought- and heat-tolerant.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of these more structured markets, the microfinance institutions are now seeking additional investments through which to scale up their lending potential, and DAI is working to attract agricultural and social investors and other forms of capital to expand the approach to additional countries and value chains. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Applying Climate-Smart Agriculture Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FICCF hits three climate-smart agriculture principles—demonstrating productivity, adaptation, and mitigation benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Productivity: Dairy farmers who adopted zero-grazing systems and improved fodder production have increased their yield from 5 liters to 10-12 liters of milk per cow per day. Cassava and sorghum farmers who access improved seeds through aggregators and apply the guidance received from extension, demonstration, and climate advisories are also generating higher yields. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adaptation: Dairy farmers gained knowledge on fodder conservation techniques for dry season feeding and lactation planning to help stabilize production throughout the year, making them less vulnerable to seasonal climate variability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mitigation: Compared with extensive grazing systems, the fodder mix promoted by the FICCF will reduce greenhouse gas emissions per liter of milk by increasing total milk production per cow. The FICCF’s aim has been to contribute to reducing herd size while increasing milk yield per herd. Other new practices made possible by FICCF include the adoption of energy efficiency (solar and treadle pumps), renewable energy (biogas), and energy audits for agribusinesses. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FICCF catalyzed a gradual switch to more resilient crops: from maize to more drought-resistant and early-maturing sorghum varieties and intercropping with legumes. It also tested a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dfid-project-trials-sorghum-insurance-to-support-climate-resilient-farming-in-kenya&quot;&gt;hybrid insurance&lt;/a&gt; with weather index and multi-peril cover for disease and pests with 150 farmers. In the 2017 season, 35 percent of farmers received a compensation payout. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/FICCF%20Value%20Chain%20Poster%201.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Screen%20Shot%202018-08-14%20at%202.02.22%20PM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screen Shot 2018-08-14 at 2.02.22 PM&quot;&gt; Click on graphic for expanded view.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Filling in the Gap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past two years, the FICCF climate-smart agriculture intervention has reached more than 5,000 small farmers, contributing—in our estimation—to 12 of the 17 &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/?menu=1300&quot;&gt;Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broad range of expertise needed to apply this climate lens to agriculture—encompassing agronomy, veterinary services, energy audits, market linkages, institutional strengthening, and so forth—requires orchestrating a mix of private and public service providers, depending on the nature of the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Working%20biogas%20unit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Working biogas unit&quot; title=&quot;Farmers are adopting more sustainable cooking habits, such as using biogas units.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this work should have long-term benefits. Smallholders who plant drought-resistant crops and practice sustainable farming will better secure rural food sources and build their resilience to climate shocks. Microfinanciers and agripreneurs are now better able to deal with the effects of increased climate variability in farming. And the farmers we have reached will in turn demand relevant climate information as they seek to adopt adaptive and resilient practices and utilize climate-smart technologies on their land.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zambia Pilot Demonstrates How to Save Lives, Scale Relief for Children Suffering from Malaria</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/zambia-pilot-shows-how-to-scale-relief-for-children-suffering-from-malaria</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 18:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/zambia-pilot-shows-how-to-scale-relief-for-children-suffering-from-malaria</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of infants and children in rural Zambia suffer or die unnecessarily from malaria each year because they lack access to high-quality medicines and proper medical care. But a recent pilot program shows how trained local volunteers administering crucial medicine can keep a child well enough to be transported to a health care facility for further, potentially lifesaving treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With technical and financial support from the Switzerland-based Medicines for Malaria Venture, the program—named &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/zambia-mamaz-against-malaria&quot;&gt;MAMaZ Against Malaria&lt;/a&gt; or MAM—was built on two earlier projects: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/zambia-moblising-access-to-maternal-health-services-mamaz&quot;&gt;Mobilising Access to Maternal Health Services in Zambia (MAMaZ)&lt;/a&gt;, funded by the U.K. Department for International Development; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/zambia-more-mobilising-access-to-maternal-health-services&quot;&gt;MORE MAMaZ&lt;/a&gt;, funded by Comic Relief. MAM introduced the medicine rectal artesunate (RAS) into severe malaria case management and trained community health volunteers in 45 rural locales in Serenje District, Central Province.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MAM produced encouraging results. In its intervention area from November 2017 to March 2018 (peak malaria season), the team identified 1,215 cases of children ages 5 and under with severe malaria danger signs, with three children dying; this compares with only 224 cases identified during the baseline period one year before, when 18 children died. This indicates the work increased the intervention communities’ ability to identify danger signs, provide pre-referral treatment to children with RAS, and refer them to health facilities without delay. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Zambia-2-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Zambia-2-1&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Toby Madden/Transaid&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When confronted with patients with severe malaria, the trained volunteers administered RAS 100 percent of the time, sent patients to the nearest health facility, and achieved strong compliance on following up with patients when they returned home. At the same time, residents increased their recognition of key symptoms of severe malaria, such as “not being able to eat or drink,” from 29 percent to 86 percent, leading to improved case management and care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MAM results were presented in an &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Evidence%20brief%20FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;evidence brief&lt;/a&gt; July 27 at the National Malaria Elimination Centre (NMEC) in Lusaka. Attendees included officials from the Serenje District Health Management Team, Central Province Health Department, USAID/President’s Malaria Initiative, the Global Fund, PATH, and MMV. The results are expected to inform the Zambian government’s planning and funding of programs to meet their ambitious goals for malaria elimination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“We had one month where 10 children died from severe malaria. But since MAMaZ Against Malaria started working [in my community], not a single child has died, and the community are aware of the danger signs of severe malaria.”&lt;/strong&gt;—Josephine Mupeta, Community Health Volunteer and Emergency Transport System, Chief Serenje&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Implementing the Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implemented by Transaid, local partners Development Data and Disacare, and DAI—a consortium selected through a rigorous review process—and in close collaboration with NMEC, MAM addressed the factors affecting communities&amp;#39; access to child health services; this work included building on the work of MAMaZ and MORE MAMaZ to increase access to emergency obstetric and neonatal care. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI led the pilot&amp;rsquo;s process to engage communities, including designing approaches specific to each community, ensuring alignment with national strategies and systems as well as international good practice for management of severe malaria, and supporting monitoring and evaluation of the work. Our approach aims to build wide social approval for improved behaviors and assist communities to develop and lead their own emergency response systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MAM launched in June 2017 in partnership with NMEC and the Serenje District Health Management Team. Quality-approved RAS 100-milligram suppositories were procured for use in the 45 communities, with NMEC ensuring that Serenje District had an uninterrupted supply of severe malaria drugs and basic medical supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MAM team trained health care providers at the district’s eight intervention health facilities in severe malaria case management and trained the local community health volunteers around a severe malaria and broader child-health agenda. A community monitoring system maintained by the volunteers generated data on children with suspected severe malaria and other common illnesses. These communities further rose to the occasion by providing safety nets for families with sick children, including savings schemes and food banks. The program also provided emergency transport in the form of bicycle ambulances to communities without the means to reach health facilities; the bicycles addressed the growing demand for referring patients to health care facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Close partnering with the District Health Management Team and NMEC ensured that key activities were led and supported by the Zambian government, helping pave the way for scaled-up services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Zambia-malaria1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Zambia-malaria1&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Toby Madden/Transaid.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key lessons learned from the pilot program, detailed in the evidence brief, include the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivated and well-trained community health volunteers in rural locales are effective at identifying and managing severe malaria cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These trained volunteers increased the reach of project activities but also created for themselves a support group that improved motivation and sustainability. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A “whole community” approach that reaches out to all community members is required to improve how individuals recognize stricken children, report the illness, and seek treatment for them; this outcome cannot be achieved in locales where there are only one or two trained volunteers per community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the project’s hard-to-reach sites, the average distance to a health facility was nearly 14 kilometers; community-managed emergency transport systems such as bicycle ambulances can significantly reduce travel times to health facilities and encourage prompt referral of very sick children. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increasing demand for severe malaria services must be met with a reliable supply of drugs and medical consumables as well as health facilities that are accessible around the clock and capable of managing severe malaria cases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Zambia-Malaria3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Zambia-Malaria3&quot; title=&quot;Photo: Toby Madden/Transaid.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Scaling Up the Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zambia’s NMEC wants to roll out the use of RAS across the country. Should it do so, the government should consider adopting the MAM approach by training significant numbers of community health volunteers in the case management of severe malaria. These local volunteer forces would build on existing health system structures, promote fair access to severe malaria services, and be cost effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MAM’s evidence-based training approach could be adapted for national community health volunteer training manuals, including those for integrated community case management of malaria volunteers and for Zambia&amp;rsquo;s Safe Motherhood Action Groups. As quality-assured RAS is distributed broadly, it will be important to ensure an uninterrupted supply of injectable artesunate and malaria commodities (such as rapid diagnostic tests and disposal gloves) at rural health facilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, community-managed bicycle ambulances have been shown to ensure patients get to health care facilities to receive  appropriate and sometimes lifesaving care. Ideally, these bicycle transport systems can be successfully budgeted for, managed, and maintained locally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/world-malaria-report-2017/en/&quot;&gt;estimated 70 percent&lt;/a&gt; of the world’s burden of severe and fatal malaria falls on young children. Severe malaria can be recognized in children at the community level by observing danger signs—fever, inability to eat or drink, repeated vomiting, convulsions, unusual sleepiness, or unconsciousness. In practice, however, many cases are missed and children suffer and die as a result. Many barriers and delays at household and community levels hinder the prompt uptake of malaria services. We are confident that the work of MAMaZ and MAM, combined with the Government of Zambia’s commitment to thwarting malaria, will lead to thousands fewer children suffering unnecessarily from this disease.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DFID Programme Helps Establish Business Equipment Leasing in Sub-Saharan Africa’s Largest Country</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/dfid-programme-establishes-business-equipment-leasing-in-sub-saharan-africas-largest-country</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2018 22:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/dfid-programme-establishes-business-equipment-leasing-in-sub-saharan-africas-largest-country</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Leasing equipment—instead of finding the cash to buy it—is fundamental to the growth of small and growing businesses, yet small-business owners in Sub-Saharan Africa’s largest nation have been unable to do so, because the regulatory framework that underpins leasing transactions didn’t exist. Until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC) recently launched business equipment leasing thanks to legal and financial frameworks established with assistance from the U.K. Department for International Development (DFID)’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/democratic-republic-of-the-congo-essor-for-an-environment-conducive-to-investment&quot;&gt;Essor programme&lt;/a&gt;, which DAI helps to implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, businesspeople in this country of 85 million can finally lease the equipment they need to grow their micro, small, and medium-sized enterprises (MSMEs) and larger businesses. This productivity-enhancing equipment includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motor vehicles of all types—passenger autos, utility vehicles and vans, light and heavy trucks, buses, specialized vehicles such as ambulances and refrigerated trucks, and off-road vehicles for mining and forestry;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agricultural and farming equipment, such as tractors and harvesters;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agro-industrial and food processing equipment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy equipment, such as generators and solar panels;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Medical equipment for hospitals and clinics;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Office equipment, such as printers, furniture, and computers;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Construction and mining equipment;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restaurant equipment, such as ovens and refrigerators; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard light manufacturing machinery such as packaging and bottling equipment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2016 survey of potential lessees and equipment suppliers—conducted by the DAI-led Essor Access to Finance team (Essor A2F)—confirmed strong demand for leasing, or &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; in French, and the types of equipment that &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; could finance. With this data in hand, Essor A2F went to work alongside DRC institutions to craft frameworks that will enable this new source of financing for the DRC’s businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Essor Programme Workstreams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five-year Essor Programme was launched in 2015 under a consortium headed by Pricewaterhouse. Essor’s workstreams in the DRC have focused on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementing the Organisation of the Harmonisation of the Business Law in Africa (OHADA), an initiative that comprises 17 countries;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combatting corruption;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving access to electricity at the provincial level; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding access to finance, the workstream implemented by DAI.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workstreams were linked to the World Bank’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doingbusiness.org/reports/global-reports/doing-business-2018&quot;&gt;Doing Business&lt;/a&gt; indicators—including access to finance—and aim to improve incomes by promoting the development of MSMEs, including women- and youth-owned and rural enterprises, through reforms to the country’s investment climate and policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Ddvs----Essor-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ddvs----Essor-2&quot; title=&quot;Leasing forum with supervision directors from the Banque Centrale du Congo.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Preparing the Country for Leasing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essor A2F’s first step was to help develop an MSME-specific chapter within the Ministry of Finance&amp;rsquo;s National Financial Inclusion Strategy, formalizing the national mission to support small businesses. At the same time, the team began designing financial literacy modules for the National Financial Education Programme to train potential lessors and lessees in the DRC on how debt, credit, and leasing works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Essor A2F team is now developing a collateral registry that will enable financial institutions to gather, share, and manage data on borrowers&amp;#39; collateral. This IT tool will remove obstacles to finance by allowing financial institutions to access information on assets pledged as collateral, improving risk management and encouraging loans and leasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Supporting the Central Bank&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essor A2F began assisting the Banque Centrale du Congo (BCC) on the leasing issue in 2016, when the team provided detailed comments and recommendations on the bank’s draft “Instruction,” or implementing measures, to financial institutions. After the BCC produced its second draft Instruction in November 2017, A2F again gave comments, which the BCC adopted to clarify accounting and fiscal procedures, among other needs, and make &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; consistent with international standards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The BCC issued its definitive Instruction on March 9, 2018, after a final round of internal work sessions assisted by Essor A2F. &lt;em&gt;Crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; was then officially placed in the hands of the country’s banks and microfinance institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Leasing Finally Begins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, banks will be expected to offer &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; to the market, primarily to mid-sized enterprises that are leasing large vehicles and productive equipment on contracts ranging from US$20,000 to $50,000. Soon after, microfinance institutions will likely begin to offer micro-leases in transactions as small as $2,000 to small restaurants, tailors, hairdressers, and other enterprises. In the future, we expect to see companies leasing big-ticket equipment such as mining machinery, which could involve transactions as large as $1 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that the law limits leasing equipment to business use only, and that &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; cannot yet be offered to individuals seeking to finance private vehicles, for example, or other consumer items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Essor-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Essor-1&quot; title=&quot;Essor A2F workshop with bank officials.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Key Issues Emerge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essor A2F has identified various remaining issues that lessors see as critical, and will work with banks, microfinance institutions, and the relevant DRC government agencies to resolve these outstanding issues. Looking ahead, in its next phase Essor A2F will seek to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarify the fiscal treatment of &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt;, including defining its accounting treatment under international accounting standards (for example, determining for tax purposes who “owns” leased equipment.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clarify court procedures related to the recovery of leased equipment in the event of default (non-payment) by a lessee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broaden awareness of &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; and its benefits to MSMEs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide technical assistance, training, and guidance to the BCC regarding control and supervision of the &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; sector. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommend procedures for registering &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; transactions in the Commercial Registry, another tool for protecting lessors against undue risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coordinate with the business association for microfinance institutions to encourage them to develop lease products, because microfinance institutions are more likely than banks to offer &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; to MSMEs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Leasing Benefits in Emerging Economies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leasing is well-known to have major benefits to emerging economies. For equipment suppliers, leasing spurs additional sales of products to a reliable buyer (the financial institution providing leasing). For MSMEs, leasing offers a form of financing more accessible than normal bank credit, since the equipment itself serves as collateral. For financial institutions, offering a new, low-risk financial product broadens their portfolio of products and their customer base. The economy benefits and the tax base increases through the added production capacity of MSMEs, new jobs created, and additional taxes payable by increasingly profitable businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Essor A2F team is proud to have contributed to the DRC’s achievement in establishing &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt;, but now it is time to push forward on making &lt;em&gt;crédit-bail&lt;/em&gt; a vibrant contributor to the country’s economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liberia Launches Mobile Tax Payments, Opening Doors to Increased Revenue for Domestic Development</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/liberia-launches-mobile-tax-payments-opening-doors-to-increased-revenue-for-domestic-development</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 15:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/liberia-launches-mobile-tax-payments-opening-doors-to-increased-revenue-for-domestic-development</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine if you could pay taxes only by traveling to the capital and paying in person—or, by paying in cash at a tax office to a “middleman.” Until recently, this is how taxes were paid in Liberia. Additionally, due to failures by the internet, power supply, or information technology systems, taxpayers often required &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/BENCHMARKING%20THE%20TAX%20SYSTEM%20IN%20LIBERIA.pdf&quot;&gt;four trips on average&lt;/a&gt; to tax offices to fulfill their obligations. Even basic transactions such as paying for a birth certificate required making a trip to the capital, Monrovia. As a result, many citizens and businesses simply did not comply, depriving the government of revenues needed for services as well as of valuable data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is good news on this front. Liberians’ ability to pay taxes and fees has improved dramatically thanks to assistance from the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID).
In March, Liberia President George Weah officially launched the country’s mobile payment system, developed with assistance from USAID’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/liberia-revenue-generation-governance-and-growth-rg3&quot;&gt;Revenue Generation for Governance and Growth (RG3)&lt;/a&gt; team. Today, citizens and business owners can readily pay taxes and fees by using mobile payments and the recently developed payment options at select bank branches. This means they no longer need travel to Monrovia and stand in line at one of the two windows designated for this purpose. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_d84abe0a-7392-4db7-a41d-ebfdb78fb652&quot; title=&quot;Liberia Test&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?IkY&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Easy Payments, Increased Revenues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberians can now pay most taxes using their mobile phones, including corporate income, personal income, real estate, business, excise, goods and services, and withholding. They can also pay most of their fees, including for birth certificates, marriage certificates, travel clearances, fire safety certificates, and business registration renewals. In a small, poor country such as Liberia, these additional revenues can help finance schools, hospitals, important infrastructure, and other needs while reducing its dependency on donors. Based on results from similar USAID e-pay programs in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/philippines-increases-tax-collections-by-11-billion-year-over-yearwithout-raising-rates/&quot;&gt;Philippines&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/long-term-fiscal-reform-takes-root-in-el-salvador-and-elsewhere/&quot;&gt;El Salvador&lt;/a&gt;, and elsewhere, the Government of Liberia can conservatively expect to generate .5 percent more revenue as a percentage of gross domestic product, or approximately $20 million each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our roads can be paved, but we must pay our taxes so we can develop our country,” Weah said at an April &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.liberianobserver.com/news/pay-your-taxes-to-develop-our-country/&quot;&gt;ceremony&lt;/a&gt; at Monrovia City Hall, where Weah used his phone to demonstrate paying his own real estate taxes. “We do not chase people to pay taxes; we [create] mechanisms for collection so it is easier.” Weah encouraged citizens to use the mobile-payment option to help finance his administration’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mfdp.gov.lr/index.php/media-center/press-releases/545-government-expands-consultations-for-pro-poor-development-agenda-as-minister-tweah-and-team-hold-talks-in-us-with-liberian-community&quot;&gt;pro-poor development agenda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are happy that through the [Liberia Revenue Authority] our government is making use of information and communication technology to promote good governance and clean governance. E-government helps improve efficiency, improve services … it helps to build trust between government and its citizens. It enhances transparency and accountability.”
—Liberia President George Weah &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Liberia-Mobile-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Liberia-Mobile-1&quot; title=&quot;Liberia President George Weah, left, shakes hands with DAI&amp;#39;s Alexander Kitain during the mobile payments launch event.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creating the Public-Private Partnership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since launching in 2016, RG3 has assisted the Liberia Revenue Authority (LRA) to enable payment of taxes through nine commercial bank branches, greatly increasing taxpayers’ options. Today, up to 50 percent of the country’s taxes are paid this way, most often with a click of a button through the banks’ online portals. But this solution only helped taxpayers who lived near one of these locations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To establish the mobile option, the LRA and RG3 teams identified two phone companies—Orange Telecom and Lonestar Telecom—to compete to become Liberia’s first pay-by-mobile services provider. The telecoms chose the United Bank of Africa for partnering due to the bank’s technical agility and aspirations. Together with the LRA, the telecoms and the bank began developing the mobile platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RG3 helped design the electronic architecture; develop payment, reporting, and reconciliation procedures; build ongoing consensus to move forward; and draft the pilot agreement between the LRA, Orange Telecom, Lonestar Telecom, and United Bank for Africa. Orange Telecom won the race to become the first telecom to launch mobile tax payments; Lonestar Telecom recently launched its service. LRA and RG3 are now working together to support back-end reconciliation, such as the synchronized confirmation and recording of payments between the telecoms, bank, and LRA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/ckx1J2EkusoSwc&quot; width=&quot;595&quot; height=&quot;485&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Liberia Poised to Promote Domestic Growth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the April launch, Liberians can now pay taxes and fees wherever they have telephone reception. This capability especially benefits small-business owners who will not be required to close their businesses for days so they can travel to pay taxes. 
At the launch event, LRA Commissioner General Elfrieda Stewart Tamba thanked the USAID Mission and RG3 for facilitating the achievement. “They supported us from the first step of this journey,” she said. Liberia joins Burkina Faso, Kenya, Rwanda, South Africa, Tanzania, and Uganda as African countries utilizing mobile tax payments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of unsuccessful attempts, the mobile solution came about because RG3 and LRA designed a simplified, cloud-based solution suitable for a developing country with low internet penetration. While there is a daily transaction limit of US$2,000, up to 90 percent of all tax and non-tax payment transactions fall under this threshold. While not all Liberians have a nearby participating bank branch or internet connection, more than 90 percent have mobile phones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Liberia-Mobile-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Liberia-Mobile-4&quot; title=&quot;Liberia President George Weah, right, demonstrates using his mobile phone to pay property taxes. U.S. Agency for International Development Liberia Mission Director Tony Chan is seated right.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefits of Mobile Payments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduces taxpayer’s time in lines and traffic; reduces time away from business.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increases transparency of tax collection, improving risk management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improves efficiency of reconciliation between taxes owed and paid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduces cost of printing and processing paper returns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decongests tax offices and reduces need and cost of extra staff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduces frequency of audits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increases pace and timeliness of tax refunds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cuts down on opportunities for corruption by reducing cash payments to tax officers, especially in rural areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is available to taxpayers 24 hours a day, seven days a week.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USAID Liberia Mission Director Tony Chan said the mobile payment system exemplifies an initiative that seeks to mobilize domestic resources in the countries where USAID works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because of the close working relationship we have with both former and current Government of Liberia officials, Liberia is [launching] implementation of this very important USAID initative,” Chan said. “[USAID] Adminstrator Mark Green firmly believes effective and increased domestic resource mobilization is a necessary condition on the journey to self-reliance.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Africa Trading: Five Takeaways on Trade-Based Solutions for Food Security</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/africa-trading-five-takeaways-on-trade-based-solutions-for-food-security</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 16:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/africa-trading-five-takeaways-on-trade-based-solutions-for-food-security</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we harness market forces in developing countries, great things can happen—such as countries with surplus food selling to countries that need food. Over the past 15 months, teams from the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-africa-trade-and-investment-hub-tih&quot;&gt;East Africa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-trade-and-investment-hub&quot;&gt;Southern Africa&lt;/a&gt; Trade and Investment Hubs together facilitated three regional trade forums—in Ethiopia, Rwanda, and Zambia. This convening of sellers and buyers generated impressive results: signed contracts to sell 1.21 million metric tons of staple grains, with an estimated value of $402 million. When delivered, the grains will be enough to feed 14.4 million people for 12 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/DAI-News----EATIH-grain-pic-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;DAI-News----EATIH-grain-pic-3&quot; title=&quot;Grain traders negotiating sales at the regional grain forum in Ethiopia in 2017.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My colleagues and I helped facilitate these forums. In January, Gerald Masila from the Eastern Africa Grain Council (EAGC), Scott Cameron from the USAID/Kenya and East Africa Office for Integration, and I shared our trade forum experiences in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://microlinks.org/sites/default/files/resource/files/Trade-Based_Solutions_to_Food_Insecurity_Presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;webinar&lt;/a&gt; presented by the USAID knowledge management platforms &lt;a href=&quot;https://microlinks.org/&quot;&gt;Marketlinks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.agrilinks.org/agrilinks-events/past?page=1&quot;&gt;Agrilinks&lt;/a&gt;. Interest ran high among our participants from across the globe. We offer anyone interested in agriculture, food security, trade, and investment on the African continent these five key takeaways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) East and Southern Africa has enough agricultural base to feed itself and cease reliance on food aid.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;East and Southern Africa have endured records droughts since 2011, affecting food security across the entire region.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yet the region features vast amounts of arable land and variances in agro-ecological zones; if food grown in one area can flow readily via free trade to deficit countries, the region can &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/83-million-grain-deal-between-east-african-countries-demonstrates-how-east-africa-can-feed-itself/&quot;&gt;wean itself from chronic dependence&lt;/a&gt; on emergency food assistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Production cycles across the region are complementary; grain surpluses can balance deficits during every season.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;East and Southern Africa have staggered planting/harvesting cycles; countries could be at surplus or deficit positions at different times of the year for any given grain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, Ethiopia, Kenya, and Uganda have the same maize crop calendar, while Burundi, Malawi, Rwanda, Tanzania, and Zambia have a different calendar. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In 2016–2017, surpluses in the region met or exceeded deficits. For example, Ethiopia had a surplus of 1 million metric tons of maize while neighboring Kenya had a similar deficit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By selling surplus maize to Kenya, Ethiopian farmers and traders earned income to buy nutritious foods and pay for household expenses such as school needs.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Trade forums enable the private sector to drive value chain growth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trade linkage forums do not distort the market the way emergency assistance can by depressing crop prices and other effects; in fact, these forums strengthen private sector involvement in areas such as seed and fertilizer, labor, transport, cold storage, and food processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our forums have brought together millers, traders, logistics companies, and banks in one place, people who traditionally do not do business with each other despite being neighbors. For example, our Ethiopian grain sellers are well versed in exporting grain to China and Italy for industrial use, but had never explored selling surplus to Kenya, despite that country’s chronic maize shortages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The forums demonstrated to governments that food shortages can be solved by business and functioning markets, if those governments craft and enact trade-friendly policies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4) Challenges persist to regional trade of food staples; we must keep working to bring down the barriers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main challenges include logistics, lack of trade finance, lack of harmonized grain standards, export bans, and other non-tariff barriers. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The East and Southern Africa hubs worked with EAGC and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/east-and-southern-africa-foodtrade-esa&quot;&gt;Food Trade East and Southern Africa&lt;/a&gt; to successfully lobby for lifting export bans in Tanzania and Zambia and to support trade-friendly reforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5) Regional grain trade must be self-sustaining.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The East Africa Hub developed and implemented forums in partnership with the EAGC, national grain traders associations, and chambers of commerce. We are currently supporting the Nairobi-based EAGC in opening an office in Addis Ababa to further facilitate sustainable grain trade between Kenya, Ethiopia, and other countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The East Africa Hub recently helped establish the East African Community (EAC)’s Cross Border Traders Association to facilitate small cross-border trades, which currently make up 60 percent of grain trade in the six-nation EAC. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Involving governments helps mobilize support for the regional trading of locally grown grain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marketlinks.org/sites/default/files/resource/files/Trade-Based_Solutions_to_Food_Insecurity_Presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Trade-Webinar-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Trade-Webinar-1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In bringing together these forums, we also absorbed some takeaways, such as the importance of trade finance for participants, the need for deep knowledge of logistics costs and transport routes for sold grains, and the effects of well-intentioned but ill-advised policy interventions, such as subsidies, that distort regional grain markets. But with $402 million in contracts generated in just the first year, the long-term market opportunity is obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the January webinar, our online participants posed good questions: on the role of lenders in African trade, on how trade can improve livelihoods in post-conflict zones, on how farmers (as opposed to traders) could make more money via increased cross-border trade, and more. We did not have time to get to all the questions, but these queries will inform our work as we pursue commercial solutions to feeding Africa’s hungry while putting more money in the pockets of farmers and others in agricultural value chains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Health and Tech Thinkers Come Together at SwitchPoint</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/global-health-and-tech-thinkers-come-together-at-switchpoint</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 15:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/global-health-and-tech-thinkers-come-together-at-switchpoint</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/&quot;&gt;SwitchPoint&lt;/a&gt;, a two-day conference organized by Intrahealth International—a DAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/dai-and-intrahealth-join-forces-to-amplify-global-health-impact&quot;&gt;strategic affiliate&lt;/a&gt;—400 global health and technology devotees came together in the North Carolina countryside to share ideas and seed partnerships for solving global health challenges, especially by using technology. The seventh annual event, held April 26–27, featured 30-plus stage speakers and 20-plus microlabs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These talks and microlabs covered a host of topics, from pandemic preparedness and the value of community health workers to how health innovators can best engage with investors—and much more. Here are just a few of the stand-out moments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-13.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-13&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving Sex a Good Name:&lt;/strong&gt; Youth in India—&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/view/articles/2017-09-08/india-s-youth-are-the-world-s-future&quot;&gt;home&lt;/a&gt; to 229 million people between ages 15–24—are interested in sex, and the internet is their top source of information, notes &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/vithika-yadav&quot;&gt;Vithika Yadav&lt;/a&gt;, co-founder and head of &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.in/en&quot;&gt;Love Matters India&lt;/a&gt;. Of India’s youth with internet access, she said, 83 percent of those surveyed have watched pornography, which paints an unreal and irresponsible picture of sex. “We have to invest in young people’s health; we need to use technology to give sex a good name,” Yadav said, adding that it is difficult for India’s young to find information on relationships, abstinence, and contraception. “Young people are looking for information about sex online,” she said. “We need to know what is youth-friendly information on sex, and how to help young people find material that resonates with them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start-Ups—Get Funding, Win Prize Money:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/our-team/bobby-jefferson&quot;&gt;Bobby Jefferson&lt;/a&gt;, pictured above, Chief Technology Officer for DAI Global Health, broke down the many avenues available for people with ideas to pursue financing. Jefferson told the audience that even well-known brands—brands not normally associated with social investment—are investing in people who show promise for delivering breakthrough ideas and thinking. He warned, though, that social investing to date has been heavily skewed and we need more women, people of color, and underserved communities to be recipients of investment funding. “Large companies and other investors increasingly realize they do not have all the answers,” Jefferson said. “Many organizations and individuals are now investing money to unearth new ideas and new energy by sponsoring contests, prizes, and innovation investment funds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow (Attract?) the Money:&lt;/strong&gt;  This microlab, photo above, featured investors, including DAI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/who-we-are/leadership/christopher-legrand&quot;&gt;Chris LeGrand&lt;/a&gt;, taking questions from people with business concepts and proposals. “Nonprofits are getting less funding—we need to learn how to raise funding differently, and this is not a bad thing,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/kafui-prebbie&quot;&gt;Kafui Prebbie&lt;/a&gt;, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://techaide.global/&quot;&gt;TechAide&lt;/a&gt; in Ghana. TechAide is seeking funding for its latest project, called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.myasanka.com/&quot;&gt;ASANKA&lt;/a&gt;, a device that collects and distributes digital content communally between wireless devices without internet access. “Investors want to see traction—impact and business results to date,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/diana-ayton-shenker&quot;&gt;Diana Ayton-Shenker&lt;/a&gt; of The New School. Added &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medtronic.com/us-en/about/foundation.html&quot;&gt;Anne Katharine Wales&lt;/a&gt; of Medtronic Foundation, “How are you going to build a shared vision so it is not just your thing?” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-5&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The One-Dollar, Bacteria-Discovering Microscope:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/jim-cybulski&quot;&gt;Jim Cybulski&lt;/a&gt; and Foldscope Instruments “want communities everywhere in the world to experience science.” The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foldscope.com/&quot;&gt;foldable microscope&lt;/a&gt; made mostly from paper and $1 in parts zooms to 140X, plus 10X digital zoom with a smart phone. More than 300,000 are deployed throughout the world, enabling schoolchildren to see micro-organisms and serving social purposes such as identifying fake drugs and currency, detecting bacteria in milk and water, and finding the microscopic eggs of agricultural pests. By bringing scientific capabilities to everyday life in remote locales, the foldscope creates openings for mentoring, opportunities for community networking, and platforms for local research and development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-7&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching Next-Gen:&lt;/strong&gt; “Teachers are force multipliers, impacting every student they teach,” said Julie Keane of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.participate.com/&quot;&gt;Participate&lt;/a&gt;, which works to add global views into U.S. curriculum and proposes educating teachers on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/sdgs&quot;&gt;Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;. “When teachers fight for what’s right, kids fight for what’s right. Let’s find a way to make teachers comfortable with [these goals], with education skills that makes sense.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-11&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knowing What People Will Do:&lt;/strong&gt; It is not true that “the future belongs to crowds,” as author Don DeLillo wrote in 1991—instead, “it belongs to those who can predict and know what crowds will do,” and is used for both development and destruction, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://hhi.harvard.edu/people/nathaniel-raymond&quot;&gt;Nathaniel Raymond&lt;/a&gt; of the Harvard Humanitarian Initiative. “We are interested in when and where you do things,” he said, but in light of the recent scrutiny of Facebook, we have to remember the privacy dimension. “Data is about how we establish trust,” he said. “Data is people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-6&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Competitors Unite for Community Health:&lt;/strong&gt; “Community health worker programs … remain a good investment, since the alternative in reality is no care at all for the poor living in geographically peripheral areas.” The finding comes from a heralded 1998 World Health Organization &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.who.int/hrh/documents/community_health_workers.pdf&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;, “and we are writing the same sentence today,” said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/madeleine-ballard&quot;&gt;Madeleine Ballard&lt;/a&gt; of the Community Health Impact Coalition. “[Yet] about 1 billion people in the world have never seen a health worker.” Ballard and a team of six organizations that frequently compete against each other recently collaborated to produce a report &lt;a href=&quot;https://chwimpact.org/&quot;&gt;distilling the secret sauce&lt;/a&gt; to optimizing community-led health systems. To summarize, successful community-led systems are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accredited.&lt;/strong&gt; Local health workers need that are tested and certified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accessible.&lt;/strong&gt; Avoid point-of-care user fees. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proactive.&lt;/strong&gt; Workers go door to door seeking out the ill and surveilling for outbreaks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuously trained.&lt;/strong&gt; Medical education, not one-shot training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dedicated supervisor.&lt;/strong&gt; To assess work and coach one on one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data feedback loops.&lt;/strong&gt; Integrate info into public data systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paid.&lt;/strong&gt; Poor health workers should not be forced to work for free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part of a strong system.&lt;/strong&gt; Not operating in a vacuum but joined to a primary care facility and pharmacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-4&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring the Invisible:&lt;/strong&gt; A rural mother who cooks, cleans, raises children, cares for elders, collects firewood, and more stands a good chance of going unseen and uncounted even if we’re looking for her, said &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/nina-rabinovitch-blecker&quot;&gt;Nina Rabinovich Blecker&lt;/a&gt; of the United Nations Foundation’s Data2X project. Instead, fathers speak for daughters and husbands for wives. “We have a significant gap in data about women and girls,” Blecker told SwitchPoint. “We cannot improve something we are not measuring,” she said, which makes it harder to assist victims of violence, people with special needs, and those who do unpaid work, for example. But high-quality data collection and national debate can drive change, she said, citing the case of Uruguay, which in 2016 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.data2x.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/UruguayCaseStudy_OECDDCR2017.pdf&quot;&gt;launched&lt;/a&gt; its National Care Plan. “Unbiased data collection is the goal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----SwitchPoint-12.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----SwitchPoint-12&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ugh–Development Selfies:&lt;/strong&gt; Photojournalist &lt;a href=&quot;https://event.switchpointideas.com/trevor-snapp&quot;&gt;Trevor Snapp&lt;/a&gt; thinks selfies send the wrong message. “We all do these selfies with people from across the tracks,” Snapp said. “It is not accurate. It is becoming, honestly, a kind of embarrassment.” Instead, he suggests supporting local storytellers and learning from them. Supporting events such as the April 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;https://nairobitechweek.com/&quot;&gt;Nairobi Tech Week&lt;/a&gt; and hackathon, for example, gives Africans an opportunity to be creative and embrace communication technology. “There needs to be collaboration all the time—there is no room for just one person telling the story,” Snapp said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Switchpoint-10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Switchpoint-10&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Softer Collaboration That Points Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only thing being sold at SwitchPoint were T-shirts, healthy food and beverages, ideas, and partnering. Event organizer and lead sponsor IntraHealth displayed no signage. Attendees in casual dress enjoyed intergenerational collaboration and intellectual stimulation against a backdrop of performance art and live music. Packed comfortably into an old cotton mill-turned-concert-hall attached to a general store and microbrewery along the Haw River—SwitchPoint attendees and presenters shared ideas freely between activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SwitchPoint effect can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://dai-global-digital.com/a-do-no-harm-framework-for-ict4d-inspiration-from-switchpoint-2018.html&quot;&gt;inspiring&lt;/a&gt;. The ultimate results, let’s hope, will be inspiration turned into action.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four Recommendations for Strengthening Seed Systems</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/four-recommendations-for-strengthening-seed-systems</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 18:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/four-recommendations-for-strengthening-seed-systems</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most people living in rural communities in developing countries depend on crops. While donor-funded seed development programs for staple crops have improved the capacity of seed companies, as well as their market connections and distribution systems, high-quality seeds of improved varieties are simply not reaching enough smallholder farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 80 percent of these smallholders save seed from their crop production or barter and buy it from neighbors, village markets, or market-day traders. This seed tends to be of old varieties and varies in quality from poor to fair to good. Self-sustaining, market-based systems that deliver a sufficient quantity of improved varieties are necessary to strengthen agriculture-dependent populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Seed-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Seed-7&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working with formal and informal seed system actors to identify and address systemic failures, we can align their incentives to farmer demand for seed that improves productivity, resilience, and inclusivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe concentrated efforts in the following four areas will improve seed systems to benefit millions of smallholder farmers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Develop Varieties That Smallholder Farmers Want&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crop variety&amp;rsquo;s performance influences how much land, other inputs, and labor farmers can justify using, which in turn influences other farmers. Yields are fundamental to farmers and to research, but public and private plant breeders need to shift toward more market-driven, participatory varietal development. Breeders, farmers, and crop buyers must engage in the joint ranking and weighting of the traits that drive farmers’ adoption rates—such as length of crop cycle, drought tolerance, storability, cooking time, and other traits that farmers and consumers prefer. For example, Itai Makanda, Chief of Party of the U.S. Agency for International Development’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/southern-africa-feed-future-southern-africa-seed-trade-project&quot;&gt;Feed the Future Southern Africa Seed Trade Project&lt;/a&gt;, points to a case where plant breeders focused on improving white maize while poultry farmers only wanted to buy yellow maize. “When variety development is driven by markets, scarce resources can achieve real results, not just improved varieties that farmers don’t want to use,” Makanda said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New genomic analysis tools identify the genes behind desirable seed traits so breeders can increase the rate of crop variety development with less trial-and-error iteration and provide markers for better quality control of seed multiplication and varietal maintenance after commercial release. DNA fingerprinting is now affordable, costing approximately $2 per sample for routine marker analysis. DNA fingerprinting can confirm varietal identity in seed distribution channels, on the farm, and in the aggregation and marketing channels. More sampling and fingerprinting would improve accurate descriptions of the varietal demand structure, the transfer of favorable traits to new varieties, and provide timely (before planting) evidence on which seed supply channels are trustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DNA fingerprinting supports the description and release of local “landraces,” or effective local varieties, helping to realize the promise of the 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbd.int/abs/&quot;&gt;Nagoya Protocol on Access and Benefit Sharing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Seed-11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Seed-11&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Include Smallholder Farmers in Planning Seed Production&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seed companies need accurate sales forecasts to accurately multiply varieties and package saleable, certified products. The process of moving from breeder to foundation to certified seed takes three to four years: underforecasting can make it impossible to meet demand and overforecasting can result in wasted time and investment. Seed producers rely on sales history, land cultivation trends, and government programming to predict demand. These forecasts are dynamic and data collection and analysis is time sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smallholder seed purchases from formal channels varies greatly, from 5 percent (for common beans in Zambia) to 80 percent (hybrid maize in Kenya), a range that is reflected across Africa. Demand by smallholders is difficult to quantify, and it is easy to understand how seed producers play it safe by underestimating this demand and, consequently, the market potential of smallholders and investment needed to meet their demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve sales to smallholder farmers, seed systems need strengthened relationships between seed producers and sellers and farmer groups. Seed companies can develop their seed brand and build market share through careful attention to farmer input in areas such as crop timing, package sizes, price points, and preferred varieties. Demonstration plots can be improved to provide better two-way information exchange with farming communities on key micro-climate and management variables that drive crop variety adoption through seed sales. Online brochures of available seed varieties would contribute, as would timely public release of national performance trial and comparative demonstration data prior to the next planting season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Seed-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Seed-2&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Realign Retail Distribution Networks to be More Inclusive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing customers with timely, demand-driven products requires a clear focus on the customer. This customer focus is critical to seed distribution networks in developing countries. Instead, many activities today focus on a single-channel model: the improvement of agro-dealer record-keeping, financial capacity, and supplier linkages. Development assistance can realign seed systems to be multi-channel and customer-oriented, shifting from profit-maximizing practices such as high margins to inclusive practices that boost sales volume. To put this in practice, seed companies and their distributors need to modify branding activities and improve merchandizing, inventory management, and retailer network expansion practices to bring high-quality seed closer to farmers and inspire farmers to make wiser seed decisions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Seed-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Seed-1&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Put Improved Policies and Regulations Into Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bangladesh’s and Turkey’s implementation of their reformed varietal release programs quickly improved national average crop yields of staple food crops. Similar reform and implementation are needed in most low- and low-middle-income countries, including to: increase focus on implementation of seed certification and quality testing; bridge the divide between formal and informal seed markets; increase the speed of commercial release of and trade in varieties in regional seed catalogues; and improve research and commercialization licensing to transfer germplasm between companies and countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fill a major gap, policy makers and national seed authorities must review and customize seed indicator frameworks, with a focus on assessing the effects on stakeholders of seed-law implementation. Stakeholders, including seed trade associations, need to prioritize and operationalize their advocacy to improve seed-system performance indicators, such as those included in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tasai.org/&quot;&gt;African Seed Access Index (TASAI)&lt;/a&gt; and the World Bank’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://eba.worldbank.org/&quot;&gt;Enabling the Business of Agriculture&lt;/a&gt;. These indicators track regulatory changes and their effect on crop varietal development and release, seed quality assurance and fraud suppression, seed costs relative to commodity prices, and the efficiency of seed trade. On the private-sector side, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.accesstoseeds.org/&quot;&gt;Access to Seed Index&lt;/a&gt; evaluates and compares seed companies on how well they improve smallholder farmer access to quality seeds of improved varieties, a barometer for self-improvement by participating seed companies, of which there are only 23 currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Seed-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Seed-3&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Building Resilience Into Seed Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resilient seed producers are ones that can withstand and quickly recover from shocks created by markets, weather, diseases, and conflict so they can continue to provide seed to their customers. One way to be resilient is to breed varieties that are resistant to drought, heat, disease, and insects and other pests. Another is to build operational resilience into the seed system itself using performance-based management, product traceability systems to spot problems quickly, quality testing—biological and DNA—to prevent seed-lot contamination, input insurance to reduce risk, and pre-approved credit lines that can be quickly accessed by farmers and seed sellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seed producers should also have emergency plans, such as standing agreements to participate in seed voucher programs that help customers purchase seed after a crop loss.
Most of Africa’s food supply is tied to seed, and the number one seed challenge in sub-Saharan Africa is quality. Low-quality seed of crops in high demand means lost opportunities to improve livelihoods and diets. Poor quality seed leads to poor germination rates and farmers wasting time, labor, and money to prepare their fields. When crop production goes down, consumer prices go up but not farmer profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of food grown in Africa is by smallholder farmers. Implementing these four recommendations will speed up the process of putting improved seed in the hands of Africa’s food growers permanently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Generation of EC Framework Contracts Offers Agile Programming for European Development Aid</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-generation-of-ec-framework-contracts-offers-agile-programming-for-european-development-aid</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 20:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-generation-of-ec-framework-contracts-offers-agile-programming-for-european-development-aid</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that DAI has once again been named one of the main implementing partners for the European Commission (EC) 2018–2022 Frameworks contracts for international development assistance. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Frameworks represent an agile development programming tool that enables the EC to quickly source and execute short-term research and pilot projects around the world. Unlike typical multiyear, donor-funded projects that work in a particular country or region—and can take more than a year to plan, bid, and launch—EC Frameworks contracts are capable of being designed, awarded, and deployed in a matter of weeks and can dispatch project teams to any country receiving development aid from the Commission. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI has a long history of supporting this unique contracting mechanism, dating back more than 20 years. Indeed, the challenging assignments and diverse technical work entailed under the Frameworks have accelerated our own learning and enriched our capabilities as a global development company. As we look forward to the next round of Framework assignments, we reflect back on our experiences and learning from this important facet of the EC’s external aid program. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A New and Flexible Development Tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EC Framework contracts have their origins in the early 1990s, when the Commission began helping Central and Eastern European countries prepare for accession to full membership in the European Union (EU). This pre-accession period demanded what was pioneering development work at the time: never before had so much support been needed for countries transitioning from highly centralized governments and economic regimes to open democracies and free market systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central administrations of 10 countries seeking EU accession had to be overhauled and modernised, with some ministries disbanded and others created. In many cases, Soviet-style state-owned companies needed support to adopt new ways of thinking as they were privatised and shifted overnight from five-year, state-run production plans to dynamic, demand-driven markets. There was also a massive effort to re-draft laws and regulations in pre-accession countries to harmonize with EU regulations across a range of sectors and concerns, from agriculture and the environment to energy efficiency and consumer protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the volume of this specialized work ballooned, the EC was almost overwhelmed by the administrative burden—at one point attempting to manage 10,000 contracts with individual consultants. Recognizing this approach as unsustainable, the Commission developed over-arching agreements called Framework contracts. Under the early agreements, each lot or sector was awarded to just one company, which was eventually expanded to three or four pre-approved Framework contractors bidding on assignments in a mini-tender. This allowed the EC to source experts for assignments in a matter of weeks rather than months and to more efficiently contract assignments by pre-qualifying bidding organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s experience with Framework contracts began when predecessor company PE was selected for early assignments that included developing an energy strategy in Lithuania and analyzing the impact of coal privatization in Poland—projects indicative of the early Frameworks’ focus on public administration reform, privatization, and restructuring in neighboring countries applying to join the EU. However, the EC’s use of Framework contracts would soon expand to new frontiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Estonia-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Estonia-1&quot; title=&quot;Tallinn, the capital of Estonia, which was one of the countries targeted by early EC Framework assignments focusing on decentralisation and democracy.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Global Expansion and Diversification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, 10 countries—Cyprus, the Czech Republic, Estonia, Hungary, Latvia, Lithuania, Malta, Poland, Slovakia, and Slovenia—completed the formal EU accession process and in doing so became ineligible for external development aid. As a result, the Commission shifted the focus of its external aid from Europe to other parts of the world, with Framework assignments now emphasizing technical areas such as agricultural development and economic growth rather than post-Soviet restructuring. Over the years, DAI’s Frameworks Unit has adapted to meet these changing needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Frameworks allowed DAI to build new expertise in areas such as education and social development. Over the past 15 years, DAI has led assignments including curriculum development, financial planning for school systems, and evaluations of national education systems. The host countries for these assignments have ranged from the Middle East (Jordan and Iraq) to Africa (Ghana, Morocco, Sierra Leone, and Zimbabwe) and even Greenland. The diversity of the Frameworks projects also enabled DAI to develop a growing pool of trusted technical experts with a wide assortment of specializations, from veterinary doctors and meteorologists to criminal justice and cyber security professionals.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2005, we have implemented more than 800 Framework assignments for the EC, valued at around €100 million, engaging 2,000 technical experts. Framework assignments continue to span the gamut of technical disciplines, from food security, economic growth, and governance to recent engagements related to human rights, migration, and climate change. Thanks in part to this breadth of expertise—complemented by our extensive work for the U.S. Agency for International Development, the U.K. Department for International Development, the World Bank, and other donors—DAI was awarded a presence on all six lots of the new EC Framework contracts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_86feb80e-d767-484d-82a9-01774d1c755a&quot; title=&quot;EC Frameworks&quot; src=&quot;https://e.infogram.com/js/dist/embed.js?tyb&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Amplifying Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our EC Frameworks portfolio has positioned DAI to serve both country-level EU Delegations and, at a  global level, the EC’s Directorate-General for International Development Cooperation. In turn, other European bilateral donors have entrusted us with important work: a multiyear monitoring and evaluation project for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Denmark on its Business Sector Programme Support in Tanzania, for example; a smaller project for its Global Green Growth Forum; a study on public pension reform in South Sudan funded by a consortium of donors including Canada, Denmark, the Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Spain, and the United Kingdom. A Framework assignment we conducted to compare the EC’s external aid operations with those of four other bilateral donors led us to work with Germany’s development Bank, KfW, to carry out a similar comparative analysis of its and other donors’ best practices. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a global development company, DAI is committed to capturing synergies and sharing knowledge across our projects. We are excited to leverage our cross-donor experience to better support the EC’s global development work, and we look forward to incorporating the lessons learned and best practices gained through our Framework assignments to benefit all of the organizations—and all of the communities—for which we work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addressing Jordan’s Youth Unemployment Bubble: USAID Program Aligns Workforce with Emerging Opportunities</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/addressing-jordans-youth-unemployment-bubble-usaid-program-aligns-workforce-with-emerging-opportunities</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 May 2018 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/addressing-jordans-youth-unemployment-bubble-usaid-program-aligns-workforce-with-emerging-opportunities</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Jordan is a relative bastion of stability in the Middle East but is struggling with an unemployment problem. More than 700,000 of its young people—&lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/%20SL.UEM.1524.ZS&quot;&gt;36 percent&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://databank.worldbank.org/data/Views/Metadata/MetadataWidget.aspx?Name=Labor%20force%20participation%20rate,%20total%20(%25%20of%20total%20population%20ages%2015+)%20(national%20estimate)&amp;amp;Code=SL.TLF.CACT.NE.ZS&amp;amp;Type=S&amp;amp;ReqType=Metadata&amp;amp;ddlSelecte&quot;&gt;available labor force&lt;/a&gt; ages 15–24—are without a job. This percentage is double that of Afghanistan and triple that of Bangladesh, even though those countries register poverty levels far worse than Jordan’s. The problem has intensified since 2011 with the influx of hundreds of thousands of refugees following the Syrian crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan is also a country surrounded by lingering conflicts in Syria, Iraq, and Palestine, and officials understandably &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/content/documents/16289Jordan.pdf&quot;&gt;view&lt;/a&gt; youth unemployment as a significant threat to stability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of a wide-ranging effort to transition its out-of-work youth into the formal economy, Jordan’s government partnered with the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID) on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-workforce-development-wfd-project&quot;&gt;Jordan Workforce Development (WFD)&lt;/a&gt; project, which recently concluded a 3½-year implementation. Among WFD’s many accomplishments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Producing and submitting policy papers and briefs for the government that address fair pay, flexible working hours, and incentives to “hire Jordanian.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating national standards for and training 40 career guidance counselors, and establishing career guidance offices in six vocational training institutes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Placing 5,100 Jordanians and Syrian refugees into new jobs in the food production, clean energy, and garment sectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing and launching three Employment Promotion Units, which facilitated the job placements and today enjoy good prospects for growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Jordan-WFD-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Jordan-WFD-1&quot; title=&quot;Akhtaboot job fair in Amman supported by a USAID Jordan Workforce Development Project Employment Promotion Unit.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Modernizing Jordan’s Workforce Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When WFD began in September 2014, Jordan’s vocational training system was churning out high numbers of potential workers for sectors with decreasing demand, such as tourism and hospitality. This was because supply-driven training programs had been failing to forecast workforce needs or even reach out to potential employers for input. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, many Jordanians harbored a cultural inclination to view vocational jobs—such as in carpentry, hospitality, and hairdressing—as less desirable than more prestigious “office jobs.” Combined with the country’s unfocused workforce development efforts, it was little wonder that young Jordanians trying to enter the workforce found scarce opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dynamic needed to change if Jordan was to meet the needs of job seekers and would-be employers. By creating Employment Promotion Units (EPUs) with the Zarqa and Irbid Chambers of Industry and Eastern Amman Investors Industrial Association, the country now has a better way to prepare employees and employers for workforce challenges.
The EPUs’ career counselors and marketing officers connect with clients in public, including by working at mall kiosks emblazoned with the Employment Promotion Unit brand and by networking at public gatherings such as Friday prayers. The WFD team produced movies shown by the EPUs that highlight career paths for vocations such as heating, ventilation and air-conditioning, die cutting, and electrical maintenance. The EPUs also keep updated websites with career opportunities with help lines for inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This outreach has succeeded in attracting a large pool of candidates—more than 15,000 registrants and counting—who have been vetted based on their qualifications and, when appropriate, referred to an employer. These efforts also seem to have improved the “cultural status” of vocational jobs among Jordan’s youth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Jordan-WFD1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jordan-WFD1&quot; title=&quot;Eastern Amman Investors Industrial Association job fair promoting Al-Quds University scholarships.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Making People Employable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with young people entering workforces all over the world, many young Jordanians come unequipped with the “soft skills” that employers need in their workplace—such as the ability to be on time, communicate effectively, work as part of a team, and solve problems independently. While these and other soft skills differ from job to job, by speaking directly with employers, EPU staff ascertained where otherwise qualified job candidates have fallen short of being employable. They designed eight modules of “Work Ready Now” training to build soft skills that bridge the gap between classroom and workplace. 
This effort by the WFD was so well-received by employers—mostly small or medium-sized enterprises—that many further committed to rewards programs designed to create career paths for workers and reduce turnover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Crafting Policies That Support Job Creation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its 2015 economic outlook, the International Monetary Fund outlined key challenges facing Jordan, including designing and implementing “broad-based policies in the labor market.” The IMF also cited the need to create more jobs for women, who held only &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jordantimes.com/news/local/women-unemployment-increases-33-q1&quot;&gt;one in seven jobs&lt;/a&gt; in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WFD team crafted policy reforms that will support workforce development, preparing and submitting policy papers to the Jordanian government that address:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible workplace hours for established employees, employees with family responsibilities, university students, and the disabled, to promote employment among women, young people, and the marginalized; the policy was endorsed in a Royal Decree by HM King Abdullah II.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incentives for employers to prioritize hiring Jordanians for labor-intensive occupations, which have a disproportionate number of lower-wage foreign workers; the brief is before the Ministry of Labor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum wage and benefits guidelines for compensating entry-level workers, with the goal of avoiding potential exploitation in the labor market, also before the Ministry of Labor. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Germany Signs On for the Road Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By addressing the supply, demand, and policy sides of workforce development, the WFD team delivered measurable results while building a foundation for job growth in Jordan. Thanks in large part to the EPU model, the WFD has placed more than 5,100 workers in sustainable jobs, exceeding USAID’s target by 20 percent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the value and effectiveness of the EPU model, the German development agency &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giz.de/en/worldwide/360.html&quot;&gt;GIZ&lt;/a&gt; has committed to further assistance. These funds aim to help the EPUs become self-sustaining units that would eventually operate using higher quality, fee-based services for employees, employers, and the government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand-driven EPU model has potential to be adopted by countries throughout the Middle East and North Africa, as does the WFD’s holistic approach, which offers an alternative to outdated, supply-driven workforce development. By offering flexible and targeted employment services that address emerging workforce supply and demand, countries can more effectively address the needs of their private sectors and underemployed youth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can We Keep the Promise?
Mobilizing Business on the Refugee Frontline in Jordan</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-we-keep-the-promisemobilizing-business-on-the-refugee-frontline-in-jordan</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2018 13:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>Elizabeth Drachman</author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/can-we-keep-the-promisemobilizing-business-on-the-refugee-frontline-in-jordan</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, lower- and middle-income countries have borne the brunt of the global refugee crisis, currently hosting more than 80 percent of the world’s refugees. But some host countries, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/calculating-syrian-refugee-crisis-fiscal-crisis/&quot;&gt;Jordan&lt;/a&gt;, are taking important steps to seize what opportunities they can in this situation, supporting refugee self-reliance and at the same time boosting their own economy by issuing work permits to refugees and connecting multinational companies to business opportunities with local firms and displaced people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blessed with a supportive government, preferential access to U.S. and E.U. markets, and strong investment incentives, Jordan provides opportunities for businesses to make investments or improve their sourcing, while at the same time creating jobs for refugees. But this model has not been without its challenges. What can we learn from Jordan’s experience, and where can we go from here?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The Scale of the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of Jordan’s challenge is the sheer scale and rapidity of the human influx: more than 1.5 million refugees and displaced persons—both registered and unregistered—in roughly the past seven years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report by Jordan’s Ministry of Planning and International Cooperation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://jordan.gov.jo/wps/portal/Home/GovernmentEntities/Ministries/Ministry/Ministry%20of%20Planning%20and%20International%20Cooperation?nameEntity=Ministry%20of%20Planning%20and%20International%20Cooperation&amp;amp;entityType=ministry&quot;&gt;MOPIC&lt;/a&gt;) estimates that the country has borne an additional $6.6 billion in direct costs—for health care, education, transport, and municipal services—since the beginning of the Syrian refugee crisis in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take health care, for example: MOPIC documented a 30 percent increase in hospital and health center occupancy nationwide, resulting in a 24 percent shortfall in the availability of hospital beds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As His Majesty King Abdallah II has noted, even those people who might one day return are expected to remain, on average, 17 years in the country, which means Jordan’s response to this crisis is not a stop-gap measure; today’s policy choices are, for all intents and purposes, setting Jordan’s development agenda for the foreseeable future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jordan_refugees.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of children at a clinic in Ramtha, northern Jordan.&quot; title=&quot;Children from Syria at a clinic in Ramatha, northern Jordan. (Photo: Russell Watkins, U.K. Department for International Development.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Finding Opportunity in Adversity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan has worked to transform the Syrian refugee crisis into an economic opportunity for all residents of Jordan—an effort that, many observers agree, has had mixed success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what we define as the Syria response in Jordan, particularly insofar as it has been supported by the international donor community, has been driven by the so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://reliefweb.int/report/jordan/jordan-compact-new-holistic-approach-between-hashemite-kingdom-jordan-and&quot;&gt;Jordan Compact&lt;/a&gt;. The Compact details specific macroeconomic interventions meant to stimulate growth in the Jordanian economy, creating jobs for Jordanian communities and for the hundreds of thousands of displaced Syrians they host. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key among these macroeconomic interventions is a 10-year trade regime that relaxes so-called “rules of origin” requirements for Jordanian exporters to the European Union. To take advantage of the scheme, though, Jordanian exporters must prove that 15 percent of their workforce is Syrian—a number which was originally planned to increase to 25 percent after the first two years of the Compact’s implementation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we get to the mixed results. Although the Jordanian government has issued tens of thousands of work permits to Syrians, fulfilling the World Bank’s Disbursement-Linked Indicators, far fewer of these workers have actually been hired by Jordanian companies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this disparity should be obvious: Even if we assume they are eager to join the formal economy, Syrian workers—although known for their prowess as tradespeople and craftsmen—seldom have the skills in demand by Jordanian factories. The costs of up-skilling them have outweighed the potential cost savings on offer through the E.U. trade deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to the point, Syrian refugees have proven reluctant to register with the Ministry of Labor, preferring instead to keep earning wages in the informal economy, where they can also collect aid from relief agencies and maintain their claim to restitution or repatriation when the Syrian conflict ends. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.odi.org/publications/11045-jordan-compact-lessons-learnt-and-implications-future-refugee-compacts&quot;&gt;recent report&lt;/a&gt; by the London-based Overseas Development Institute (ODI) makes clear, these demand-side issues could have been anticipated. The report’s authors note, for example, that the Compact’s design “did not integrate refugee perspectives at the outset.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the Compact has yielded significant gains in human welfare, especially for the most vulnerable. ODI cites the Jordanian Ministry of Education, which reported that, in the 2016-17 academic year, some 126,000 Syrian refugee children were enrolled in public education or certified to attend private or nongovernmental organization-run schools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a considerable achievement, with demonstrable results in the lives of children and their families. But these are what one might call “traditional” relief efforts—absolutely necessary but, in the context of a country with a 96 percent debt-to-GDP ratio, not nearly enough. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Doing Better&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the gap between our ambitions for the Jordan Compact and the often lackluster economic results, what would guide a more successful development program—one that takes our country from resilience to growth?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it will require an agreed-upon framework grounded in the government’s own vision. That vision is contained in the Jordan Economic Growth Plan, a five-year roadmap published most recently in 2018 by Jordan’s Economic Policy Council and closely tied to the requirements of the International Monetary Fund’s Extended Fund Facility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closely tied to the Economic Growth Plan and adding further rigor to the analysis is the World Bank’s recent Jump-Starting Growth and Job Creation in Jordan, a framework presented in October 2017—laying out “elements of a responsive adjustment program that will lead to higher GDP growth and better jobs outcomes”—that serves as a useful mechanism for organizing upcoming donor-supported efforts in Jordan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the donor community, too, has begun to realign its programs, taking its cues from the ODI report and others. The development firm for which I serve as a board member, DAI, recently published a wide-ranging &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/news/white-paper-offers-development-ideas-for-jordan-in-light-of-refugee-surge&quot;&gt;white paper&lt;/a&gt; outlining a path forward designed to generate economic development in the context of the Syrian refugee crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DAI’s recommendations cover everything from the natural environment, including developing new energy sources and managing scarce water resources; to the policy environment, including measures to promote e-government initiatives such as online resident services; to workforce development and entrepreneurship, including employment services and business incubators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/jordan_refugees2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo of children at a clinic in Ramtha, northern Jordan&quot; title=&quot;A woman from Homs, Syria, now a refugee in neighboring Lebanon. (Photo: Russell Watkins, U.K. Department for International Development).&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Prospects for Progress&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still room to make good on the promise of the Compact. A DAI-run project, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-competitiveness-program-jcp&quot;&gt;USAID Jordan Competitiveness Program&lt;/a&gt;, has completed two rounds of a hands-on, firm-level assistance program aimed at finding those Jordanian manufacturers with the greatest likelihood of exporting to the European Union—assisting them with packaging and marketing their products, and helping them identify buyers in the European market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And through a partnership between that DAI-run program and the Jordan Investment Commission, the American Chamber of Commerce in Amman, and the Ministry of Industry and Trade, the U.S. Agency for International Development is helping build the capacity of the Commission’s newly established Investment Promotion Directorate. Through that program, more than $140 million in promising leads have been identified, and the most eager of these international investors will be hosted in Jordan next month for field visits. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also actively marketing Jordan in the United States, where my colleagues in Jordan have organized two impact investment fora in June. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.connect.jo/jordan-impact-investment-forum-nyc/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;, in New York, will feature Jordan’s Minister of Planning, who oversees implementation of the Jordan Compact on behalf of the government; a second event in San Francisco will feature our Minister of Industry and Trade, who has long been a leading advocate for Jordan’s exporters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the long term, we need continued engagement from the donor community to make the most of the development assistance it has extended to the communities and countries that host millions of people forced from their homes. In Jordan, we are yet to realize the full potential of the Compact, but we would be doing the Jordanian people and the refugees among them a disservice if we fail to explore every avenue to deliver on that promise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>With U.K. Aid, Lebanon’s Social Enterprises Pilot a New Model of Development</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-uk-aid-lebanon-social-enterprise-pilot-new-model-of-development</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2018 17:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/with-uk-aid-lebanon-social-enterprise-pilot-new-model-of-development</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The influx of refugees from across the Syrian border is straining Lebanon’s economy and host communities. Since 2011, Lebanon’s population has &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.TOTL?locations=LB&quot;&gt;increased&lt;/a&gt; 30 percent to around 6 million as a result of this influx, and its young people are increasingly anxious to enter the workforce. Many even wish to start or join social enterprises to help address the country’s challenges, including problems stemming from the refugee crisis. But until recently there were few avenues for pursuing this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funded by the U.K. Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO), the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/lebanon-social-enterprise-pilot-project&quot;&gt;Lebanon Social Enterprise Pilot Project&lt;/a&gt;—known locally as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.souklb.co/&quot;&gt;SoUK.LB&lt;/a&gt; Social Enterprise Hub—has assisted 19 such enterprises in the past year. Among these is the SE Factory code school, an initiative of The Nawaya Network, a local nongovernmental organization. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sefactory.io/&quot;&gt;SE Factory&lt;/a&gt; offers introductory and boot camp courses to train working-class young people on the technical and soft skills needed to get jobs in the tech industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-1&quot; title=&quot;SE Factory founders Zeina Saab and Fadi Bizri. Photo: SE Factory.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In less than three years, SE Factory graduated 59 students through its boot camp, and nearly all received job offers within six weeks. Their new employers include local tech startups, such as those participating in the FCO’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uklebhub.com/&quot;&gt;UK-Lebanon Tech Hub&lt;/a&gt; accelerator programmes, and regional tech companies. Early indications show SE Factory graduates earn higher salaries on average than they would have earned coming straight out of university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Grant Opens Door to Coding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, SE Factory was awarded a £30,000 cash grant from SoUK.LB, plus training and one-on-one mentorship to develop an introductory online course to supplement its in-person coding boot camps. SE Factory developed a pilot one-month pre-boot camp course—Foundation of Computer Science. Ten students new to coding graduated from the pre-boot camp and are now prepared for the full-time, three-month coding boot camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 20, visitors from the British Embassy of Beirut and the FCO Conflict, Stability and Security Fund (CSSF) attended the first Foundation of Computer Science graduation event. There, the visitors learned about SoUK.LB’s 18 other social enterprise grantees—including enterprises in health, agriculture, women’s economic empowerment, transportation, and other sectors. These grantees—competitively selected from 147 applicants—comprise idea and early-stage startups and established, growth-stage cross-sector organisations. Their missions are to create transformational social or environmental change whilst becoming financially sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early-Stage Grantee Wins First Place at Global Social Venture Competition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of SoUK.LB’s early-stage social enterprises won first place at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gsvc.org/&quot;&gt;Global Social Venture Competition&lt;/a&gt;, a premier business competition organized by the University of California at Berkeley. The winning team, FabricAID, competed with 550 applicants from 60 countries, with teams first passing through rounds of national and regional competitions. FabricAID created a new industry in Lebanon by more easily connecting buyers and sellers in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/richardkestenbaum/2017/04/11/fashion-retailers-have-to-adapt-to-deal-with-secondhand-clothes-sold-online/#4a468cbd1a7f&quot;&gt;multibillion-dollar&lt;/a&gt; second-hand clothing market. In the 10-year history of the competition, this is the first time a team from Lebanon reached the international finals.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----Lebanon-SEPP-2&quot; title=&quot;FabricAID CEO Omar Itani accepting first prize at the Global Social Venture Competition finals in Milan, Italy.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Entrepreneur-Driven Social Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoUK.LB is demonstrating the viability of the small-enterprise model in Lebanon to achieve social and economic impact and potential scalability. This FCO flagship project addresses the challenges to both the supply of and demand for transformational and sustainable social and economic change in Lebanon. The investment harnesses the potential of the private sector to develop, incubate, and scale ideas that can catalyze positive change and shape the creation of a distinct social enterprise sector in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Select Results from the Lebanon Social Enterprise Pilot Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed recruitment campaign for social enterprises/innovators, resulting in 183 applicants for support in training, mentoring, and funding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Out of 147 eligible applicants, 48 percent were led by women, and 50 percent were ages 18–30.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awarded 19 grants to start-up and growth-stage organisations and provided training sessions to 52 of these grantees. Twelve of the grantees have begun generating sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disbursed £405,000 in grants. Grantees increased the number of beneficiaries they serve by 154 percent, and created 225 jobs covering full time, part time, and contractor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completed market study on the social enterprises&amp;#39; operating environment, challenges, and opportunities and an overview of international best practices that can be adopted in Lebanon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engaged policy makers in policy development discussions—including officials from the Ministry of Economy and Trade, Ministry of Finance, Banque du Liban, and Office of the President of the Council of Ministers.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By identifying, enabling, and sustaining Lebanon&amp;rsquo;s innovators and small social enterprises, SoUK.LB is transcending the traditional role of the grants-based challenge fund by enabling social enterprises too small for traditional financing to operate like businesses rather than development projects. It has also served to spotlight the unmet demand for such assistance, including in untapped markets outside of Beirut, where we are confident that similar assistance can succeed and ultimately benefit Lebanese communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New DFID Guidance Aims to Improve Emergency Schooling for Millions of Displaced Children</title>
      <link>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-dfid-guidance-aims-to-improve-emergency-schooling-for-millions-of-displaced-children</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 14:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author> </author>
      <guid>http://dai-global-developments.com/articles/new-dfid-guidance-aims-to-improve-emergency-schooling-for-millions-of-displaced-children</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An estimated 75 million children cannot go to school because they have been driven from their homes by war, crisis, and natural disaster. This deprivation in turn destabilizes vulnerable regions because uneducated children grow into at-risk teenagers and young adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To strengthen its education in emergencies (EiE) programming, the U.K. Department of International Development (DFID) drew on the DAI-led Expert Advisory Call Down service on resilience programming to research evidence on which interventions work to support high-quality schooling for displaced children—and where the evidence falls short. DAI consortium partner Cambridge Education led the research and produced six &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/worldwide-expert-advisory-call-down-services-eacds-lot-b-strengthening-resilience-and-response-to-crises&quot;&gt;Evidence Briefs&lt;/a&gt; about EiE, focusing on quality and learning; protection and inclusion; cost-effective delivery; data, monitoring, and evaluation; political settlements; and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE1&quot; title=&quot;Syrian refugee children attend class at a makeshift school near the Syrian border on the outskirts of Mafraq, Jordan. Photo by AP/Muhammed Muheisen and Freedom House.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these briefs, the team compiled the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/uploads/EiE_Guidance_Note-8fc7f4.pdf&quot;&gt;Education in Emergencies Guidance Note&lt;/a&gt;. DFID encourages policy makers and development practitioners worldwide to consider this guidance and researchers to fill in the many knowledge gaps in this field. Here we share select observations from the briefs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;aside&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Growing Need for Emergency Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violent conflicts tend to last longer today than in previous decades—26 years on average versus fewer than 10 years in 1970. These conflicts often involve non-state, regional, and global actors and are increasingly linked to complex global challenges such as climate change, natural disasters, and transnational organized crime. These protracted crises mean we are seeing more migrants, both within countries and across borders. Among those migrants, children and young adults are among the most affected.&lt;/aside&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protection and Inclusion—Ensuring Schools are Safe and Inclusive.&lt;/strong&gt; The team sought evidence on how to ensure formal and informal schools are safe spaces that protect children and welcome the vulnerable, particularly girls and the disabled. Distance to school is a major barrier for young children, girls, and children with disabilities. Strategies found to make schools safer and more accessible include chaperoned walking to school (Jordan) and recruiting village and female volunteers (Afghanistan). Tackling the effects of trauma emerged as another important theme—in Gaza, the Norwegian Refugee Council’s Better Learning Programme combined psychosocial and trauma-focused training for teachers and school counsellors. The programme significantly reduced nightmares for 70 percent of students and moderately reduced nightmares for 30 percent, with the improved wellbeing attributed to students’ improved enjoyment of school and increased level of effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data, Monitoring, and Evaluation—Understanding Change and Challenges.&lt;/strong&gt; There is consensus that better data is critical to understand the challenge of intervening at scale, to inform programming, monitor responses, and assess children’s access, attainment, and education pathways as their locations or circumstances change. For example, while an estimated 60 percent of the world&amp;rsquo;s 19.5 million refugees and 80 percent of its 34 million internally displaced persons (IDPs) live in urban environments, data on them is scarce. Many are not formally registered as refugees or IDPs, which limits the effectiveness of EiE because donors and United Nations projects typically do not fund programmes to educate unregistered refugees. The authors suggest revising assessment tools to better inform urban programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE6&quot; title=&quot;Teachers at a refugee camp in Rojava, Syria, lead students in exercise. Photo: Alberto Hugo Rojas.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality and Learning—Hurdles to Effective Emergency Teaching.&lt;/strong&gt; Both local and foreign teachers in emergency settings face unique challenges. While teacher quality is critical to learning quality, teachers who are refugees themselves—whether professional or recruited to fill gaps—often suffer from the same traumatic experiences, economic hardships, and unstable circumstances afflicting their students. Local-national teachers may have personal views on the conflict or crisis. On the other hand, well-meaning expatriates may have little or no experience in teaching or in crises. As a result, host-country teachers often take on increased class loads but are often not prepared to handle the psychosocial support needs of refugee students (or their expatriate colleagues). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effective Delivery—Creating Synergy of Efforts.&lt;/strong&gt; When it comes to delivering value for money, the team found that efforts to coordinate the separate funding streams of “first response” humanitarian relief and long-term development assistance have been ineffective. While humanitarian organizations can respond to crises in weeks or even days, their program funding typically lasts six months to one year and can vary year to year depending on priorities. In contrast, development programs tend to have consistent budgets over three to five years to achieve their goals, but can take more than one year to conceive, plan, and launch. Greater attention is required to finance, plan, and implement EiE assistance throughout education crises, which typically last for years and—for the children—multiple grade and learning levels. UNICEF’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.educationcannotwait.org/&quot;&gt;Education Cannot Wait&lt;/a&gt; fund, launched in 2016, was cited as a potential model for merging humanitarian and development activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE5&quot; title=&quot;Children of the Sheikh Misri refugee camp just south of Jalalabad, Afghanistan.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Settlements—Knowing What is Feasible.&lt;/strong&gt; The research aimed to summarise what is known about establishing political consensus and coordinating government response to education emergencies (in various political contexts). There are few examples of “what works” in this area. One ongoing example comes from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dai.com/our-work/projects/jordan-competitiveness-program-jcp&quot;&gt;Jordan Compact&lt;/a&gt; of 2016. Faced with an unprecedented influx of Syrian refugees, the Government of Jordan committed to schooling all Syrian refugee children in exchange for donor assistance to build more schools and address public service delivery and economic development. The Jordanian Ministry of Education reports that more than 126,000 Syrian refugee children had enrolled in school in host communities and camps for the 2016–2017 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/Devs----EiE3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devs----EiE3&quot; title=&quot;Young students in Takegon, Aceh, Indonesia, following the 2004 Tsunami. Photo by Daniel Ziv.&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability—Leveraging Local Commitment.&lt;/strong&gt; Providing EiE “should ideally be led by a national government, or aligned to national government policies or systems,” the authors write, because a locally led response is more sustainable and can also contribute to peacebuilding and national unity in the longer term. For example, in response to Typhoon Haiyan in 2013, the central Philippines government co-chaired the United Nations’ Education Cluster relief effort. The government-led approach was embedded within local Philippine government systems, where local actors employed their acute understanding of local needs and ways to organise. For example, they quickly identified alternative school spaces amid the destruction and inspected them for safety and suitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Systemic Solutions for Displaced Children&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, providing more stability for displaced children requires a long-term development approach, focused on inclusive economic growth and effective, legitimate institutions conducive to stability in fragile and conflict-affected states. This approach must include multi-year assistance in building systems for essential services such as education. If humanitarian, development, and peacebuilding actors can work in a more joined-up way to achieve education outcomes and ensure that EiE interventions are aligned as far as possible with national systems, the &lt;em&gt;Guidance Note&lt;/em&gt; suggests, they have a better chance of building resilient schools, supporting teachers, and providing a good education for displaced and refugee children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
